<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse of the sacrifice of the Mass</title>
            <author>Payne, William, 1650-1696.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 223 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 51 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56741</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P901</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19214</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13054561</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13054561</idno>
            <idno type="VID">96982</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56741)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96982)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 395:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse of the sacrifice of the Mass</title>
                  <author>Payne, William, 1650-1696.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 96 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Brabazon Aylmer ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Written by William Payne. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>"Imprimatur, Guil. Needham. October 24, 1687"</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. 4.</note>
                  <note>Advertisements: p. 96.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mass --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:96982:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DISCOURSE OF THE SACRIFICE OF THE MASS.</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="imprimatur">
                        <p>Imprimatur,</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Guil. Needham.</signed>
                           <date>
                              <hi>October,</hi> 24. 1687.</date>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Brabazon Aylmer,</hi> at the
<hi>Three Pidgeons</hi> over againſt the <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> in
<hi>Cornhil,</hi> MDCLXXXVIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:96982:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:96982:2"/>
            <head>The CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>THE charge of the Church of <hi>England</hi> againſt the ſacrifice of the Maſs. <hi>page 2, 3.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sect. 1.</hi> The ſacrifice of the Maſs founded upon two great Errors, the Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation, and the Opinion that Chriſt offered up himſelf to God at his laſt Supper. <hi>p. 5 to
11.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sect. 2.</hi> No Scripture ground for the ſacrifice of the Maſs. <hi>p. 11 to 41</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>Melchiſedec's offering Bread and Wine, <hi>Gen.
14.18.</hi> conſidered. <hi>p. 13</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Of the Melchiſedecian Priesthood. <hi>p. 16</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The figure of the Paſchal Lamb Examined. <hi>p.
19</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The propheſie of <hi>Malachy</hi> Examined. <hi>p.
22</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Other places out of the Old Teſtament Anſwered.
<hi>p. 25</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>An Anſwer to the places out of the New Teſtament.
<hi>p. 28</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Plain places of Scripture againſt the Maſs-ſacrifice out of the <hi>Epiſtle to the Hebrews. p. 33</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Their Evaſions to them Refuted. <hi>p. 35</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sect. 3.</hi> The ſacrifice of the Maſs has no juſt claim to Antiquity. <hi>p. 41 to 70</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>The Euchariſt called a ſacrifice by the Ancients upon account
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>1.</hi> Of the Oblations there made. <hi>p.
44</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>2.</hi> Of the Religious Acts there performed.
<hi>p. 47</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>3.</hi> As it is Commemorative and Repreſentative of the Croſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacrifice. <hi>p. 49</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Chriſt is offered mentally by every Communicant. <hi>p.
52</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>How the Miniſter may be ſaid to offer Chriſt to God in the Euchariſt. <hi>p. 53</hi>
               </item>
               <item>General Remarks out of Antiquity to prove the Euchariſt no proper ſacrifice. <hi>p. 54 to 70</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1.</hi> From the Chriſtian Apologists. <hi>p.
54</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2.</hi> From the Epithets they give to it when they call it a ſacrifice. <hi>p. 58</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>3.</hi> From the Novelty of private Maſſes which are a conſequence of this Doctrine. <hi>p. 60</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>4.</hi> From the Canon of the Maſs it ſelf.
<hi>p. 63</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>5.</hi> From the new form of Ordination in the <hi>R. C. p. 67</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sect. 4.</hi> The Maſs-ſacrifice in it ſelf <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſonable and Abſurd, and has a great many Errors involved in it.
<hi>p. 70 to 95</hi> 
                  <pb facs="tcp:96982:3"/>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1.</hi> It makes an external viſible ſacrifice of what is perfectly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible. <hi>p. 70</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2.</hi> It makes a proper ſacrifice without a proper ſacrificing Act. <hi>p. 71</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Their differences about the Eſſence of the ſacrifice. <hi>p. 73</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>3.</hi> It makes a living Body a ſacrifice. <hi>p.
76</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>4.</hi> The making it truly propitiatory is a great Error, and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with it ſelf. <hi>p. 77</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>5.</hi> How it is Impetratory. <hi>p. 80</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>6.</hi> The making it a ſacrifice truly Propitiatory, and yet only Applicatory of another is a great Abſurdity.
<hi>p. 82</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>7.</hi> The making it the ſame ſacrifice with
<hi>That</hi> of the Croſs, and yet not to have the ſame vertue and efficacy is ſtrange and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>accountable. <hi>p. 84</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>8.</hi> Making Chriſt, as they do, the true offerer of this ſacrifice hath great Abſurdities. <hi>p. 87</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>9.</hi> The Offering this ſacrifice to Redeem Souls out of Purgatory, one of the greateſt Errors and Abuſes that belong to it.
<hi>p. 88</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Of the Ancient Oblations for the Dead. <hi>p. 90 to
95</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>10.</hi> The ſacrifice of the Maſs muſt be either unneceſſary or elſe muſt reflect on the ſacrifice of the Croſs. <hi>p. 95</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The Concluſion and the Reaſon why no more of the Errors be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to it are added.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <list>
               <item>PAge 12. <hi>line â antepenult.</hi> for
<hi>deſire</hi> read <hi>derive.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>PAge 39. <hi>Line</hi> 8. for <hi>the</hi> read
<hi>that.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>PAge 68. To Concil. Carthag. <hi>in margin</hi> add 4.</item>
               <item>PAge 72. <hi>Line</hi> 8. for <hi>Maunday-Thurſday</hi> read <hi>Good-Fryday.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:96982:3"/>
            <head>A DISCOURSE OF THE SACRIFICE OF THE MASS.</head>
            <p>THE Sacrifice of the Maſs is the moſt conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable part of Worſhip in the <hi>Roman Church,</hi> It is their <hi>Juge ſacrificium,</hi> their dayly and continual Offering, and the principal Thing in which their Religion does conſiſt; It is, they tell us, of the greateſt profit and advantage to all perſons, and I am ſure their Prieſts make it ſo to themſelves, for by this alone a great number of them get their Livings, by making merchandiſe of the Holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and by ſelling the Blood of Chriſt at a dearer rate then <hi>Judas</hi> once did; The ſaying of Maſſes keeps the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> more Prieſts in pay, then any Prince in <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> can maintain Souldiers; and it has raiſed more Money by them, then the richeſt Bank or <pb n="2" facs="tcp:96982:4"/>Exchequer in the World was ever owner of; 'tis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the trueſt Patrimony of their Church, and has enricht it more then any thing elſe; it was that which founded their greateſt Monaſteries, and their Richeſt Abbies, and it had well nigh brought all the Eſtates of this Kingdom into the Church, had not the Statutes of <hi>Mortmain</hi> put a check to it; The Donation of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> were it never ſo true, and the Grants of
<hi>Charles</hi> and <hi>Pepin</hi> were they never ſo large, and the Gifts of all their Benefactors put together, are infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly outdone by it; the Gain of it has been ſo manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly great that one cannot but upon that account a little ſuſpect its Godlineſs, but yet if it could fairly be made out to be a true part of Religion, it were by no means to be rejected for that accidental though ſhameful abuſe of it: It is accounted by them the greateſt, and the moſt uſeful and comfortable part of Chriſtian Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and if it be ſo, it is a great defect in us that want it; they charge us very high for being without it, without a Sacrifice, which no Religion (they tell us) in the World ever was before: and one amongſt them of great Learning, and ſome temper in other things, yet upon this occaſion askes, <hi>whether it can be doubted, where there is no Sacrifice, there can be any Religion</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">An dubitari poteſt ubi nullam peculiare Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiciam, ibi ne Religionem qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem eſſe poſſe?
<hi>Canus in loc. Theol. l. 12. p. 813.</hi>
               </note>? We on the other ſide account it a very great corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion of the Euchariſt, to turn that which is a Sacrament to be received by us into a Sacrifice to be offer'd to God, and there being no Foundation for any ſuch thing in Scripture, but the whole ground of it being an Error and miſtake, as we ſhall ſee anon, and it being a moſt bold and daring preſumption, to pretend proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to Sacrifice Chriſts body again which implyes no leſs then to Murder and Crucifie him; we therefore call it a <hi>Blaſphemous Fable</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">See Article 31. of the 39 Articles of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</note>, and as it is made uſe of to deceive people into the vain hopes of receiving benefit by the Communion without partaking of it, and a true <pb n="3" facs="tcp:96982:4"/>pardon of ſin by way of price, and recompence is attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to it, and it is made as truly propitiatory as Chriſts ſacrifice upon the Croſs, both for the dead and living, and for that purpoſe is ſcandalouſly bought and ſold, ſo that many are hereby cheated not onely of their mony but of their ſouls too, it is to be feared, who truſt too much to this eaſie way of having a great many Maſſes ſaid for them, and becauſe when the prieſt pretends to do thoſe two great things in the Maſs, to turn the Bread and Wine into the very ſubſtance of Chriſts Body and Blood, and then to offer Chriſt up again to his Father as truly as he offered himſelf upon the croſs, (which are as great as the greateſt works which ever God did at the very Creation and Redemption of the World) yet that he really does no ſuch thing as he then vaunts and boaſts of; for theſe Reaſons we deem it no leſs then a
<hi>dangerous deceit</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Ibid.</note>.</p>
            <p>Theſe are high charges on both ſides, and it concerns thoſe who make them to be well aſſured of the grounds of them. And here I cannot but paſſionately reſent the ſad ſtate of Chriſtianity, which will certainly be very heavy upon thoſe who have been the cauſe of it, when the corruptions of it are ſo great, and the divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions ſo wide about that which is one of the moſt ſacred and the moſt uſeful parts of it, the Bleſſed Euchariſt; which is above any other the moſt ſadly depraved and perverted, as if the Devil had hereby ſhown his ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt malice and ſubtlety, to poyſon one of the greateſt Fountains of Chriſtianity, and to make that which ſhould yield the Waters of Life be the Cup of deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. That bleſſed Sacrament which was deſigned to unite Chriſtians, is made the very bone of Contention, and the greateſt inſtrument to divide them; and that bread of Life is turned into a ſtone, and become the great Rock of offence between them. Beſides the leſſer corruptions of the Euchariſt in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:96982:5"/>ſuch as uſing thin Wafers inſtead of bread, and inject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them whole into the mouths of the Communicants, and Conſecrating without a Prayer, and ſpeaking the words of Conſecration ſecretly, and the like; there are four ſuch great ones as violate and deſtroy the very ſubſtance and Eſſence of the Sacrament, and make it to be a quite other thing then Chriſt ever intended it, and therefore ſuch as make Communion with the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Altar</hi> utterly ſinful and unlawful: Theſe are the Adoration of the Hoſt, or making the Sacrament an object of Divine Worſhip; the Communion in one Kind, or taking away the Cup from the People; the turning the Sacrament into a true and proper Sacrifice propitiatory for the Quick and the Dead, and the uſing of private or ſolitary Maſſes, wherein the Prieſt who celebrates, Communicates alone. The two for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer of theſe have been conſidered in ſome late diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes upon thoſe ſubjects; the fourth is a reſult and conſequence of the third, for when the Sacrament was turned into a ſacrifice the people left off the frequent communicating, and expected to be benefitted by it another way; ſo that this will fall in as to the main Reaſons of it, with what I now deſign to conſider and Examine, The Sacrifice of the Maſs or Altar, wherein the Prieſt every time he celebrates the Communion is ſuppoſed to offer to God the Body and Blood of Chriſt under the forms of Bread and Wine, as truely as Chriſt once offered himſelf upon the croſs, and that this is as true a proper and propitiatory Sacrifice as the other, and that 'tis ſo not only for the Living but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo for the Dead. The Objections we make againſt it and the Arguments by which they defend it will fall in together at the ſame time, and I ſhall endeavour fairly and impartially to repreſent them in their utmoſt ſtrength, that ſo what we have to ſay againſt it, and what they have to ſay for it, may be offered to the <pb n="5" facs="tcp:96982:5"/>Reader at one view, that he may the better judg of thoſe high charges which are made, he ſees, on each ſide.</p>
            <p>Firſt then we ſay, That the very foundation of this Sacrifice of the Maſs, is eſtabliſhed upon two very great Errors and Miſtakes: The one is the Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation or Chriſts Corporal preſence in the Euchariſt; The other is the Opinion, That Chriſt did offer up his body and blood as a ſacrifice to God in his laſt Supper, before he offered up himſelf upon the Croſs: If either or both of theſe prove falſe, the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of the Maſs is ſo far from being true, that it muſt neceſſarily fall to the ground, according to their own principles and acknowledgments.</p>
            <p>Secondly, There is no Scripture ground for any ſuch ſacrifice, but it is expreſly contrary to Scripture; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which head I ſhall examine all their Scriptural pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences for it, and produce ſuch places as are directly contrary to it, and perfectly overthrow it.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, That it has no juſt claim to Antiquity, nor was there any ſuch Doctrine or practiſe in the Primitive Church.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, That it is in it ſelf unreaſonable and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd, and has a great many groſs Errors involved in it.</p>
            <p>Firſt we ſay, That the very Foundation of this ſacrifice is eſtabliſhed upon two very great Errors and Miſtakes, the firſt of which is the Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation, or which may be ſufficient for their purpoſe, the corporal preſence of Chriſts natural body and blood in the Euchariſt, though they diſclaim the belief of this without the other: but if Chriſts body and blood be not ſubſtantially preſent under the ſpecies of bread and Wine, they have no ſubject matter for a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, for 'tis not the bread and wine which they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend <pb n="6" facs="tcp:96982:6"/>to offer, nor the bare ſpecies and accidents of thoſe, nor can they call them a proper propitiatory ſacrifice, but 'tis the very natural body and blood of Chriſt, under the ſpecies of bread and wine, or toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with them, for they with the ſpecies make one entire ſubject for ſacrifice, and one entire object for Adoration, as they are forced to confeſs<note n="†" place="margin">Panis &amp; cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus Domini, Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num &amp; ſanguis Domini non ſunt duo ſacrificia ſed unum, — ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que enim offeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus corpus Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini abſolutè, ſed offerimus cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus Domini in ſpecie panis,
<hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larm. de Miſſ. l. 1. c. 37.</hi>
               </note> ; So that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their own principles, they muſt both ſacrifice and adore ſomething in the Euchariſt beſides the very body and blood of Chriſt, which is a difficulty they will never get off, but I deſign not to preſs them with that now, but Tranſubſtantiation upon which their ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of the Maſs is founded, is ſo great a difficulty that it bears down before it all ſenſe and reaſon, and only makes way for Church Authority to tryumph over both; Their wiſeſt men have given up Scripture for it, and frankly confeſt, it were not neceſſary to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it without the determination of the Church, and if ſo then without the Churches determination, there had been no foundation it ſeems for the ſacrifice of the Maſs. for there can be none for that without Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation, and 'tis very ſtrange that a ſacrifice ſhould be thus founded, not upon Scripture or a Divine inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but only in effect upon the Churches declaration, and ſhould have no true bottom without that, as ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to thoſe men it really has not. But Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation is a Monſter that ſtartles and affrights the boldeſt Faith, if the Church be not by to encourage and ſupport it;
'tis too terrible to be looked upon in its ſelf without having a thick miſt of Church Authority and Infallibility firſt caſt before a mans eyes, and then if there were not a ſtrange and almoſt faſcinating pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in ſuch principles, one would think it impoſſible that any man who has both eyes and brains in his head ſhould believe a Wafer were the body of a man, or that a crum of bread were a fleſhly ſubſtance, they do <pb n="7" facs="tcp:96982:6"/>not indeed believe them to be both, but they believe one to be the other which is the ſame thing; there is nothing can expoſe ſuch a doctrine, for nothing can be more uncouth and extravagant then itsſelf, it not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly takes away all evidence of ſenſe upon which all truth of miracles, and ſo of all Revelation does depend, but it deſtroys all manner of certainty, and all the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of truth and knowledge, it makes one body be a thouſand, or at leaſt be at the ſame time in a thouſand places, by which means the leaſt atome may fill the whole World; Again it makes the parts of a body to pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trate one another, by which means all the matter of the whole World may be brought to a ſingle point, it makes the whole to be no greater then a part, and one part to be as great as the whole; thus it deſtroys the nature of things, and makes a body to be a ſpirit, and an accident to be a ſubſtance, and renders every thing we ſee or taſte to be only phantaſm and appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and though the World ſeems crouded with ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lids, yet according to <hi>that</hi> it may be all but ſpecies and ſhadow, and ſuperficies. So big is this opinion with abſurdities and inconſiſtencies and contradictions, and yet theſe muſt all go down and paſs into an Article of Faith before there can be any foundation for the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the Maſs, and let any one judge that has not loſt his judgment by believing Tranſubſtantiation, what a ſtrange production that muſt be which is to be the genuine of-ſpring of ſuch a doctrine. It is not my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, nor muſt it be my preſent task to diſcourſe at large of that, or to confute the little ſophiſtries with which it is thought neceſſary to make it outface the common reaſon of mankind. There never was any pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radox needed more ſtraining to defend it, nor any Sceptical principle but would bear as fair a wrangle on its behalf, there is a known Treatiſe has ſo laid this cauſe on its back, that it can never be able to riſe again, <pb n="8" facs="tcp:96982:7"/>and though after a long time it endeavours a little to ſtir, and heave, and ſtruggle, yet if it thereby provokes another blow from the ſame hand, it muſt expect no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſs then its mortal wound.</p>
            <p>I paſs to the next Error and Miſtake upon which the ſacrifice of the Maſs is founded, and that is this, that our bleſſed Saviour did at his laſt Supper when he celebrated the Communion with his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples offer up his body and blood to his Father as a true propitiatory ſacrifice, before he offered it as ſuch upon the Croſs. This they pretend, and are forced to do ſo to eſtabliſh their ſacrificing in the Maſs, for they are only to do that in the Sacrament, they own, which Chriſt himſelf did, and which he commanded his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles to doe, and if this ſacrifice had not its inſtitution and appointment at that time, it never had any at all, as they cannot but grant. Let us then enquire whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Chriſt did thus ſacrifice himſelf and offer up his body and blood to God at his laſt Supper: Is there any the leaſt colour or ſhadow of any ſuch thing in any of the accounts that is given of this in the three Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts or in St. <hi>Paul? The Lord Jeſus the ſame night in which he was betrayed took bread and gave thanks, or bleſſed it, and brake it, and gave it to his Diſciples, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, take eat this is my Body which is given for you, this do in remembrance of me, after the ſame manner alſo he took the Cup and gave thanks, and gave it to them, ſaying, drink ye all of this, for this is my blood of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which is ſhed for you, and for many for the remiſſion of ſins.</hi> Is here any mention or any intimation of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering up any thing to God? Was not the bread and the cup, and what he called his body and his blood gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to his Diſciples to be eaten and drank by them? and was any thing elſe done with them? is there any thing like an offering or a ſacrificing of them? yes ſay they, Chriſt there calls it his <hi>body which is broken and his <pb n="9" facs="tcp:96982:7"/>blood which is ſhed,</hi> in the preſent tenſe; therefore the one muſt be then broken and the other ſhed; So indeed it is in the Original <hi>Greek,</hi> though in the Vulgar Latin it is in the future tenſe, and ſo it is alſo put in their Miſſal, <hi>ſanguis qui effundetur, this is my Blood which ſhall be ſhed,</hi> and is it not uſual to put the preſent tenſe inſtead of the future, when that is ſo near and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain? Does not our Saviour do it more than once at other times? <hi>The Son of man is betrayed into the hands of ſinners,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.45. before he was ſo, though <hi>Judas</hi> was then nigh and coming about it. So <hi>John</hi>
10.17. <hi>I lay down my Life,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, when he was ready to do ſo; as he was to have his body broken and his blood ſhed, when he was prepared as a victim to be offered the next day, ſo St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſays,
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>I now offer up my ſelf,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.6. when, as we tranſlate it, <hi>he was ready to be offered.</hi> That Chriſt here uſed the preſent tenſe for the future is owned by Cardinal
<hi>Cajetan</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">In Luc. <hi>22.</hi>
               </note>, and other Learned men<note n="†" place="margin">Sa. Barrad.</note> of the
<hi>Roman Church,</hi> and <hi>Janſenius</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Cancord. <hi>131.</hi>
               </note> ſayes, <hi>the pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of the blood is rightly underſtood of the pouring it out upon the Croſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Chriſts body was not broke, nor his blood poured out till the next day, nor did he offer up himſelf as a ſacrifice to his Father until then, Chriſt did not then command his Apoſtles to offer him up in the Euchariſt, when he bad them <hi>do this: hoc facite,</hi> does not ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie to ſacrifice, nor will it be ſuppoſed I hope our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour did then uſe the vulgar Latin, the phraſe in <hi>Virgil, cum faciam vitula,</hi> which is always quoted to this purpoſe, ſhows it only to be ſo meant when the occaſion or ſubject matter does require it; but in our Saviours words it plainly refers to thoſe acts of taking bread and breaking it, and taking Wine and Bleſſing it, &amp; then giving or diſtributing of them, as he had done juſt before, and as he commanded then <hi>to do in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance <pb n="10" facs="tcp:96982:8"/>of him,</hi> and that it does not relate to ſacrificing is plain from St. <hi>Paul</hi> who applyes it particularly to drinking the Cup, <hi>do this as oft as ye drink it in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of me,</hi>
1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.25. That the Apoſtles were made Prieſts by Chriſt at his laſt Supper, by thoſe words, <hi>hoc facite, do this,</hi> is ſo precarious and ſenſeleſs an opinion, that it only ſhows what wonderful ſtreights and extremities our adverſaries are driven to, who are forced to eſpouſe this to ſupport their ill-framed Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potheſis about the Holy Euchariſt, in thoſe two do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of the <hi>Communion in One Kind, and the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the Maſs.</hi> There is not one Father or Antient Interpreter, that gives any the leaſt countenance to it, and many of their own Authors are aſhamed of it, as may be ſeen in a late Diſcourſe of the <hi>Communion in One Kind</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">pag.
15.</note>, where this is ſo fully expoſed that I ſhall here ſay no more of it, but that if thoſe words make the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles Prieſts, it makes them ſo twice, for they are twice repeated by our Saviour after giving the Cup, as well as after giving the bread, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> witneſſes, 1
<hi>Cor.</hi> 11.25. and ſo the character of Prieſthood muſt be dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and they muſt be twice ordained at the ſame time, when there is nothing appears like any Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at all; but if they were then made Prieſts they were not made ſo to ſacrifice Chriſts Body and Blood, or to do more then he did at that time and ſo this is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the purpoſe if he himſelf did not then truly offer and ſacrifice himſelf, which is the plaineſt thing in the World he did not. And what ſhould make any man imagine that Chriſts body was broke, and his blood ſhed at his laſt Supper; or that he then ſacrificed and offered up himſelf I cannot conceive. Had he been no otherwiſe ſacrificed, nor his body any otherwiſe bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, nor his blood in any otherway ſhed beſides this the Jews had been liable to much leſs guilt, but mankind had bin in a more wretched condition, for Chriſt had not
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:96982:8"/>Redeemed them had he not dyed for them upon the Croſs. If the ſacrifice of Chriſt at his laſt Supper, the night before his crucifixion, was a true proper and propitiatory ſacrifice, what needed he have ſuffered the next day, if that was of the ſame nature and value with the other, as they ſay, and did truly propitiate God, and procure pardon and remiſſion of ſins for mankind, what need was there of the Croſs of Chriſt? it was hereby made void and of none Effect, or at leaſt of no neceſſity. If Chriſt had done the work with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it, his ſacrifice upon the Altar or the Table might have excuſed his ſacrifice upon the Croſs, and thus the bitter Cup might have paſt from him, and he might have been Crucifyed only in Effigie, and ſlain myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally and ſacramentally; and his body might have been thus broken and his blood ſhed, and yet the one have been ſtill whole, and the other in his veins.</p>
            <p>For theſe Reaſons one of their own Biſhops in the Council of
<hi>Trent</hi> denyed openly, <hi>That Chriſt offered up any proper ſacrifice at his laſt Supper</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Cornelius E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopus Biton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinus, in concilio apud Tridentum, —qui dixerit Chriſtum in cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nâ non ſuum cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus &amp; ſanguinem obtuliſſe,
<hi>Canus in loc. Theol. l. 12.</hi>
               </note> But if he did not then there was no ground for them ever to offer any in the Euchariſt, and therefore the Council was forced to declare he did, though no ſuch thing appears in the Evangelical Hiſtory, nor could any collect it from thence, but it was a neceſſary after-thought, and a groundleſs ſuppoſal, to help out and eſtabliſh the ſacrifice of the Maſs.</p>
            <p>Secondly, There is no Scripture ground for any ſuch ſacrifice, but 'tis expreſly contrary to Scripture, to ſacrifice Chriſt over again, and to have any other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiatory ſacrifice beſides that of the Croſs, and to offer up Chriſts body and blood every day which was to be but once offered and that by himſelf. I have already ſhown that the greateſt foundation of this their ſacrifice out of Scripture, which is Chriſt offering up himſelf at his laſt Supper and commanding others to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:96982:9"/>offer him there is a miſtake, and if it be ſo, all their other Scriptural pretences are vain and to no purpoſe; and muſt be ſo acknowledged by themſelves, for there is none other that does inſtitute and appoint any ſuch ſacrifice, or can with any colour or ſhadow be pretended to do ſo, and I hope they will own that without a divine inſtitution, there cannot be a proper and much leſs a propitiatory ſacrifice, and this indeed they do, they confeſs that <hi>it is not in the power of the Church to inſtitute a ſacrifice</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">Non eſt in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtate Eccleſiae. inſtituere Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum, <hi>Salme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron, Tom. 9. Tract. 28.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>And that the very being and Eſſence of this ſacrifice depends upon the Inſtitution of Chriſt</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Tota Eſſentia Sacrificii pendet ex inſtitutione Chriſti,
<hi>Salme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron,</hi> ib. <hi>Suarez. Tom. 3. Diſp.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>5.</hi>
               </note>. If that be then taken away, and there be no ſuch thing in Scripture as I have ſhown there is not, then whatever other places they can produce to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh this are all inſignificant and to no purpoſe; for if they did mention this either by way of Prophecy or of Hiſtory, yet if it be no where inſtituted, this will not do the buſineſs, for the Inſtitution ought not to be ſuppoſed but clearly proved and made out, and if that cannot be, every thing elſe that is to ſupport it as a collateral evidence falls to the ground. What will it ſignifie if <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> did offer Bread and Wine not to <hi>Abraham</hi> only but to God, and as a Prieſt did ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice them, rather then make an hoſpitable entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with them, is this any foundation for the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the Maſs? If Chriſt did not inſtitute that at his laſt Supper with his Diſciples,
<hi>Melchiſedec</hi> I hope did not inſtitute it with <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Souldiers. If the Prophet <hi>Malachi</hi> ſpeaks never ſo much of a pure offering, yet if Chriſt did not offer up himſelf in the Sacrament, nor command the Apoſtles to offer him up there, <hi>Malachi</hi>'s Propheſie will not make the Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt to be a ſacrifice or a pure offering, if Chriſt did not make it ſo: nor will the Prieſts I ſuppoſe deſire their power of ſacrificing either from <hi>Melchiſedecs</hi> act or
<hi>Malachi</hi>'s prediction without Chriſts Inſtitution; it is
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:96982:9"/>not only a preſumption but a demonſtration that thoſe Scriptures which they bring, do not really mean or truly ſpeak of any ſuch thing, as <hi>The ſacrifice of the Maſs,</hi> when there is no ſuch thing any where inſtituted or appointed by Chriſt, and without ſuch an inſtitution there cannot (as they confeſs) be any ground for it. All their little ſcattered forces therefore which they rally and pick up here and there out of Scripture, and which againſt their will they preſs into the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the Maſs-ſacrifice are hereby wholly cut off and utterly defeated, by having their main ſtrength without which they can do nothing of themſelves, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away from them, and I ſhall examine them only to ſhow the weakneſs of them, which they being ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſenſible of themſelves endeavour to make up their want of ſtrength by the greatneſs of their number; and ſurely never were ſo many places brought out of Scripture to ſo little purpoſe, as what they produce for the ſacrifice of the Maſs.</p>
            <p>Firſt then they go back as far as <hi>Geneſis</hi> for it, and it is very ſtrange they ſhould find it there; this will make it very primitive and ancient indeed, but where-ever they meet with bread and Wine, which are things of very great Antiquity, they reſolve to make a ſacrifice of them; eſpecially if there be but a Prieſt by who has the power of Conſecrating, for they ſuppoſe he muſt preſently fall to his office and put on his habit if bread and wine be before him, and that he cannot like other men eat and drink them as his ordinary food or entertain his friends and others with them, except he not only Religiouſly bleſs them by Prayer and Thanksgiving which every good man ought to do, and it was the cuſtom even of the Heathens to do this before they ate, but he muſt ſacrifice and offer them up to God. This they will needs have <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> do in the 14. of <hi>Gen.</hi> 18. <hi>verſe. Melchiſedec King of <pb n="14" facs="tcp:96982:10"/>Salem brought forth bread and wine, and he was the Prieſt of the moſt High God.</hi> What is there here to ſhow that <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> offered bread and wine as a ſacrifice to God, the very word in their own vulgar Latin anſwering to the Hebrew is <hi>protulit, he brought forth,</hi> not <hi>obtulit, he offered;</hi> and if it were the latter, could not he offer bread and wine to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany upon a Table, but muſt it neceſſarily be to God upon an Altar?<note place="margin">Ver. 14, 15.</note>
               <hi>Abraham</hi> with his Three Hundred and Eighteen Trained Servants, had been by night pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing thoſe who had taken away his brother <hi>Lot</hi> Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, and when they were thus weary and hungry, <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> hoſpitably and kindly entertained them with proviſion to refreſh them; and brought forth bread and wine to them, thus it lyes in the Sacred Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory and Context, and thus <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſephus</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. l. 1. c. 11.</note> relates it, and there is not the leaſt mention or intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of any ſacrifice as <hi>Cajetan</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">Nihil hic ſcribitur de ſacrificio ſed de prolatione ſeu extractione, quam <hi>Joſephus</hi> dicit factam ad reſiciendos victores,
<hi>Cajetan in Gen. 14.</hi>
               </note> owns upon the place, and ſo do many of their own Authors, whom <hi>Poſſevine</hi>
               <note n="(c)" place="margin">Biblioth. l. 4. c. 13.</note> the Jeſuit takes upon him to correct for it. <hi>Bellarmine</hi> indeed, as if he had been by at the enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment, and been one of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Souldiers, tells us, they had ate and drank very well before, and therefore deſires
<hi>Melchiſedec</hi> to excuſe them, for they had no need of his Bread and Wine at that time<note n="(d,)" place="margin">Quid igitur opus erat pane &amp; vino ijs qui ſpoliis abundabant &amp; paulo ante comederant &amp; biberant?
<hi>Bellarm. de Miſſ. l. 1. c. 6. D.</hi>
               </note> and yet in the ſame place owns that theſe were given to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Companions for food<note n="(e,)" place="margin">At nos non negamus data illa in cibum Abrahae &amp; ſociis, ſed dicimus fuiſſe prius Deo
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>plata &amp; conſecrata, &amp; tum data hominibus ut de ſacrificio participarent, <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </note> but that they were firſt offered to God and then given to them to partake of them as of a ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice: But why were they given as Food, if they had
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:96982:10"/>no need of Food? Did <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> know they had eaten? Or does the Scripture ſay ſo? Or might not he treat them as a King though they had victuals of their own? How does <hi>Bellarmine</hi> know they were firſt ſacrificed when there is not the leaſt word of that? Ay, but it is ſaid that he was the Prieſt of the moſt high God, therefore it is likely he ſacrificed, why elſe ſhould that be added? It was added becauſe he was ſo, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe as it immediately follows, <hi>he bleſſed</hi> Abraham,<note place="margin">Ver. 19.20.</note> 
               <hi>and</hi> Abraham <hi>gave him Tithes of all his ſpoils,</hi> this is more likely than becauſe he ſacrificed, for there is no menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that as of the other, and 'tis not ſaid he brought forth bread and wine becauſe he was the Prieſt of the high God, 'tis only a conjunctive particle, <hi>and, he was,</hi> not a cauſal <hi>for.</hi> It is ſaid alſo in the ſame place,
<hi>that he was King of Salem,</hi> and why might not his entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<hi>Abraham</hi> be as he was a King, becauſe he is ſaid there to be a King, as well as a Prieſt, and yet I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a Prieſt may be ſaid to treat his Friends, as ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man without officiating then as a Prieſt, though he be called a Prieſt. Why <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſhould cite any Fathers for his Opinion I cannot imagine, ſince the oldeſt of them are I ſuppoſe ſo much latter, and at ſo great a diſtance from the times of
<hi>Melchiſedec,</hi> that they could no more know what
<hi>Melchiſedec</hi> did at that time then we can now, and they are very impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per witneſſes of a matter of fact that was ſo long ago, which nothing but the Scripture hiſtory can give us any account of, to which itis not only precarious but raſh to add any of our own gueſſes and conjectures; however tho ſome of the Fathers do by way of figure and alluſion, make this bread and wine of <hi>Melchiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dec,</hi> to relate to the Sacramental bread and wine, as they make Manna, and ſeveral other things which were not ſacrifices, yet none apply it to the ſacrifice of the Maſs, nor could they well do it ſince they believed <pb n="16" facs="tcp:96982:11"/>no ſuch thing in the <hi>Romiſh</hi> ſenſe, as I ſhall ſhow af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards. But after all, what if <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> did ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice bread and wine? What ſervice will this do to the ſacrifice of the Maſs? The Prieſts do not there ſacrifice bread and wine according to this Myſtical Type, nor did <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> ſure offer up Chriſts body and bloud under the ſpecies of his bread &amp; wine; if we allow all that can be begged and deſired that <hi>Melchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedec</hi> did ſacrifice, and that this his ſacrifice was a Type and figure of another ſacrifice, why may not that be of the ſacrifice of the Croſs, which is the true and only proper Chriſtian ſacrifice, when Chriſt the Bread of Life was offered up unto God for us? So that there is no neceſſity to bring in the ſacrifice of the Maſs to complete and anſwer this figure, were there any thing in it beſides gueſſe and fancy which I ſee no manner of reaſon to believe there is, ſince there is nothing to countenance it in the New Teſtament, and 'tis very preſumptuous and ungrounded to make any thing a true Type, or to have a Typical meaning farther then Gods Spirit, which alone could know this, has given us warrant to do it by Revelation. Yet without any ſuch ground both <hi>Bellarmine</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">de
<hi>Miſſâ</hi> l. 1. c. 6.</note>, and the Council of
<hi>Trent</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Seſſ. 6. c. 1.</note>, make this to be the notion of Chriſt being a Prieſt after the order of
<hi>Melchiſedec,</hi> that he was to offer up a viſible and unbloody ſacrifice of bread and wine, and to appoint others to do this for ever, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the Scripture makes Chriſt to be a Prieſt after the Order of
<hi>Melchiſedec,</hi> not upon any ſuch account: for the Author to the Hebrews makes not the leaſt menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this in his large diſcourſe of this matter<note n="*" place="margin">Heb. 5.7.</note>, but in his having no Predeceſſor nor no Succeſſor in his Prieſthood, as
<hi>Melchiſedec</hi> is repreſented in Scripture without any account of his Family or Genealogy, <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Father, without Mother, without Deſcent, Heb.</hi> 7. <hi>v.</hi> 3. and in the excellency of that in general above the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect <pb n="17" facs="tcp:96982:11"/>
               <hi>Aaronic</hi> Prieſthood, and in the Eternity and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutability of it, <hi>becauſe he continueth ever, and hath an unchangeable Prieſthood, verſe</hi> 24. How little the
<hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedecian</hi> Prieſthood of Chriſt, upon which they lay ſo much ſtreſs, will ſerve the purpoſe of the Maſs-ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, nay how contrary 'tis to it, I ſhall endeavour to manifeſt in a few particulars.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, Chriſt it is plain did offer up to God not an unbloody, but a bloody ſacrifice upon the Croſs; I ask whether he did this according to his <hi>Melchiſede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian</hi> Prieſthood? If he did, then
<hi>Melchiſedec</hi> probably as Prieſt of the High God might offer the bloody ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of living creatures, and if he were <hi>Shem</hi> the Eldeſt Son of <hi>Noah,</hi> as is fairly conjectured by Learned men, he might learn this of his Father, who after the Flood <hi>built an Altar unto the Lord, and took of every clean beaſt, and of every clean fowl, and offered burnt-offerings on the Altar, Gen.</hi> 8.20. but then how will this be reconciled with what our adverſaries pretend, that it was the proper and peculiar office of <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> to offer the pure and unbloody ſacrifice of bread and wine? And that according to that the Roman Prieſts are to do that, and that Chriſt did that at his laſt Supper. Chriſts Prieſthood was the ſame at his Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and upon the Croſs, if he acted therefore as a Prieſt of <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> in one, he did ſo in both.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The Scripture mentions no Act or Office of
<hi>Melchiſedec</hi>'s Prieſthood but in bleſſing <hi>Abraham, Gen.</hi> 14.18, 19. <hi>Melchiſedec King of Salem brought forth bread and Wine, and he was the Prieſt of the moſt high God, and he bleſſed him, and ſaid, bleſſed be</hi> Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham <hi>of the moſt high God which hath delivered thine enemies into thine hand.</hi> And this the Authour to the
<hi>Hebrews</hi> takes particular notice of<note n="†" place="margin">ch.
7. v. 1.</note>, and this anſwers to what St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſays of Chriſt after his Reſurrection, <pb n="18" facs="tcp:96982:12"/>
               <hi>God having raiſed up his ſon Jeſus ſent him to bleſs you</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Acts 3.26.</note>, which general word of bleſſing may include in it, whatever is done for us by Chriſts Prieſthood after his Reſurrection, particularly his praying and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding to God for us. Had it been any part of Chriſts <hi>Melchiſedecian</hi> Prieſthood to offer up bread and wine, much more had it wholly conſiſted in this, 'tis ſtrange the Apoſtle in a ſet and large diſcourſe of this, ſhould not ſpeak one word, nor take the leaſt notice of it.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Chriſt is to have none to ſucceed him in his
<hi>Melchiſedecian</hi> Prieſthood, but he was himſelf to remain a Prieſt for ever; the Author to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> makes this difference between the <hi>Aaronical</hi> Prieſts and Chriſt, that they were to ſucceed one another, <hi>and they truly were many Priests, becauſe they were not ſuffered to continue by reaſon of death</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Heb. 7.23.</note>, but Chriſt was an immortal and ſo a perpetual Prieſt, <hi>but this man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he continueth ever, hath an unchangeable prieſthood</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Verſe
24.</note>, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a Prieſthood that paſſes not to others but is ever fixt and appropriate to his own perſon, <hi>and he is made a Prieſt, after the power of an endleſs Life</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Verſe 16.</note>. That which belongs then to Chriſt as he is an immortal Prieſt, and continueth ever, and hath none to ſucceed him, that it is which conſtitutes his Melchiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decian Prieſthood, and what that is the Apoſtle plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly informs us in the very next verſe to thoſe I have quoted, <hi>ſeeing he ever liveth to make interceſſion for us</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Verſe 24.</note>. Chriſts interceding with God by vertue of his ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice upon the croſs, and appearing in heaven in the preſence of God for us, and there preſenting his ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to his Father, and powerfully mediating on our behalf, this is his proper unchangeable, eternal, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tranſitive <hi>Melchiſedecian</hi> Prieſthood, and 'tis great ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogance for any to pretend to ſhare with him or to ſucceed him therefore in his proper Prieſthood, and to <pb n="19" facs="tcp:96982:12"/>call themſelves as the Romaniſts do, Prieſts after the order of <hi>Melchiſedec,</hi> when none but Chriſt is ſo; This his prieſthood is not committed to any upon Earth, but is to be for ever executed and diſcharged by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in heaven, and he has left none to be proper prieſts in this ſenſe, but only to be Miniſters to this great High prieſt, in performing ſome leſſer though pecliar Offices proper to them, as the Levites under the Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh diſpenſation had their proper work though they were not proper prieſts.</p>
            <p>The next thing they produce out of Scripture for the Sacrifice of the Maſs, is the Paſchal Lamb, which they will needs have to be a figure of the Euchariſt; and ſince that was a ſacrifice, therefore the Euchariſt which was figured by it ought to be ſo too; Now theſe ſigura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Arguments though they help to make ſome ſhow as they are dreſt out by fancy, yet they have generally this fault that they prove either too much or too little, and ſo either ſhoot over the mark, or fall a great deal ſhort of it, but ſeldom hit it. The Paſchal Lamb, and the Euchariſt, the Chriſtian Paſſeover do agree in this that they are both ſolemn and religious Rites, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memorative of a great deliverance, and that they are both Sacred and Myſtical Feaſts wherein ſomething is to be eaten with joy and thankfulneſs, and our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our inſtituted one to ſucceed and take place of the other, in theſe particulars they ſuit and have an agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Analogy with one another; but figures are like Circles, which may touch one another in ſome points but not in all, for if we go any farther they will nece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſarily divide and differ. The paſchal Lamb was to be eaten but once a year, the Euchariſt much oftner, that was a feaſt of viſible and ſolid fleſh, the Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt only of bread and wine; or if there be any fleſh, 'tis inviſible and as like bread and wine as can be, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:96982:13"/>this is the fleſh, according to our adverſaries, of a living man, that of a dead and roaſted Lamb, this is not to be ſlain but eaten whole and alive, the other was, and therefore why may we not adde, to go no further, this is no proper ſacrifice, that probably was, for it is not paſt queſtion whether it was or no, but yet ſuch a ſacrifice as was offered without a prieſt by every Maſter of a Family: and if the Euchariſt were to agree with it in this, the prieſts would looſe a great deal of their deſign in making it a ſacrifice, for then without hiring them every houſe-keeper would offer it himſelf; beſides the paſchal Lamb was not a propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiatory ſacrifice. I preſume, for the quick and dead, ſo then in correſpondence to that neither is the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the Maſs, but only an Euchariſtic one: but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all the paſchal Lamb was not truly a Type and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of the Euchariſt but of Chriſt crucified, ſo ſays St.
<hi>Paul</hi> expreſly, <hi>Christ our Paſſeover is ſacrificed for us</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">1 Cor. 5.7.</note>, and that not I ſuppoſe in the Sacrament, but up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the croſs, <hi>the Paſchal figure was fulfilled,</hi> ſays their own <hi>Janſenius, when our true paſſeover Chriſt was immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Impleta erat ſigura Paſchatis quando verum noſtrum Paſcha immolatus eſt Christus. <hi>Jan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen. Harmon. c. 131. f. 895.</hi>
               </note>. and to ſhow how exact a figure he then bare of the paſchal Lamb, <hi>a bone of him was not to be broken</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">John
19.33.</note>, as it was not likewiſe of that <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.46. and this expreſly remarkt, <hi>that the Scripture might be fulfilled</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">verſe 36.</note>. The ſacrifice of the paſchal Lamb, and the other Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh ſacrifices wherein atonement was made for ſin by ſhedding of blood, without which under the Law there was to be no Remiſſion, were all as the Apoſtle ſays <hi>ſhadows of good things to come</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Heb. 20.1.</note>, and Types of the more perfect ſacrifice of Chriſt upon the Croſs, who was <hi>the Lamb ſlain</hi> in Types and Figures as well as in deſign and intention <hi>from the beginning of the world,</hi> and I cannot but think that from hence aroſe the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal cuſtom of ſacrificing in all Religions over all the World, from an original tradition of the ſacrifice of <pb n="21" facs="tcp:96982:13"/>Chriſt, and out of a primary regard and reſpect to that, for I cannot imagine what elſe ſhould be the reaſon or give riſe to expiatory ſacrifices, and be the true cauſe of ſo general a practice; but that any of theſe ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices had relation to the Euchariſt, or were intended as figures of that is very precarious and ungrounded; Thoſe Euchariſtic ſacrifices indeed in which part of what was offered, was eaten by the offerers; or in holocauſts when the whole was conſumed, where a peace-offering was joined with them which the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers uſed to feaſt and partake of, as a token of their peace and reconciliation with God, theſe may fairly relate and have ſome reſpect to or at leaſt reſemblance with the Euchariſt, which is a kind of ſacrificial feaſt, or ſacramental feeding upon an
<hi>oblatum,</hi> Chriſts body and blood offered for us upon the Croſs, but that they were Types of this is more then we can be aſſured of, for a Type is a ſign or figure appointed and deſigned by God to ſignifie and mark out ſuch a thing, and we cannot know that God appoints or deſigns any ſuch thing further then we have ſome ground from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Revelation, and therefore we muſt reſtrain Typical matters within thoſe bounds and muſt not let fancy looſe to make what Types it pleaſes. There may be ſome ſimilitude and likeneſs by which one thing may be compared with another without its being a Type or a Figure of it as <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> in his Dialogue with <hi>Trypho</hi> the Jew calls<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Juſtin Martyr Dialog. cum Tryph. p. 260.
<hi>Par.</hi>
               </note>, <hi>The meat-offering of fine flour which the Leper was to bring for his cleanſing, Levit.</hi> 4.10. <hi>an Image or likeneſs of the Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtic bread which Chriſt our Lord appointed to be brought in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of his Paſſion whereby our Souls are cleanſed from ſin and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:96982:14"/>wickedneſs, and that we may hereby give thanks to God the Creator.</hi> So that he makes the Euchariſt to anſwer the Analogy of that meat-offering in three things in the Oblation of bread, and this in commemoration of Chriſts paſſion whereby we are delivered from ſin, and as a Thankſgiving to God, and in all theſe it does ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well correſpond with it, though that it was ſtrictly a Type of this, and ſo intended by God is ſtill to be queſtioned, and he that is acquainted with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and their Allegorical way of explaining Scripture, and applying all things in the Old Teſtament to mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in the New, will have great reaſon to doubt whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they did not give too much ſcope to their fancy in many things, and whether ſolid Arguments may be drawn from all their Allegorical diſcourſes and applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but yet none of them that I know of, do make any of the antient propitiatory ſacrifices to be Types and Figures of the Euchariſt, but of the ſacrifice of the Croſs; however if they ſhould do this by ſome remote alluſion and partial reſemblance, yet not as it is a proper ſacrifice or truly propitiatory, therefore not at all to the purpoſe of the ſacrifice of the Maſs.</p>
            <p>The Propheſie of <hi>Malachi</hi> is one of the great Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture proofs for this ſacrifice, but it can be at moſt but a collateral evidence, for if Chriſt did not in fact inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute any ſuch ſacrifice as I have proved he did not, this is a much better argument to ſhow there was none ſuch foretold, then it can be to prove he did inſtitute it becauſe it was foretold: Predictions are beſt under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by the completion of them, and if no ſuch thing was done as is pretended from this prediction, this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrates that no ſuch thing was intended or meant by it, ſo that by taking away that firſt ground of the Maſs-ſacrifice, I have taken away all theſe little under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>props and ſupporters of it; but let us ſee what ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <pb n="23" facs="tcp:96982:14"/>aſſiſtance this place of <hi>Malachi</hi> will afford them. God having reproved the Jews for their undue and unſit offerings, tells them that better and purer offerings ſhall be made him every where by the Gentiles, <hi>For from the riſing of the Sun even unto the going down of the ſame, my name ſhall be great among the Gentiles, and in every place incenſe ſhall be offered unto my name, and a pure offering, for my name ſhall be great among the Heathen, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Malac. 1.11.</note>. Thus it is both in the <hi>Hebrew</hi> and <hi>Greek</hi> Copies as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> owns, but it is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing different from both thoſe in the Vulgar Latin, where it is, <hi>In every place is ſacrificed, and is offered to my name a pure Oblation</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">In omni loco ſacrificatur &amp; offertur nomini meo para ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latio.</note>. They are ſo in love with the Word ſacrifice, that they chooſe to uſe that above any other, as if where-ever they meet with that in Scripture it muſt be meant properly, and of an exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ſacrifice, and of no other but the propitiatory ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of the Maſs. Tho the word here
<hi>Mincha,</hi> from which ſome of our Adverſaries are ſo fooliſh as to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive the Latin word <hi>Miſſa,</hi> that ſignifies only a diſmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the <hi>Catechumens</hi> and <hi>penitents</hi> before the Office of the Euchariſt, does not ſignifie a propitiatory ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice but only a meat-offering which was merely Euchariſtic, and whereas nothing is more commonly meant by ſacrifice in Scripture, then the ſpiritual ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of praiſe and thankſgiving, and prayer, and the like when a pious and devout Soul <hi>offers unto God Thanksgiving, and pays its vows unto the moſt high</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 50.14.</note> ; when the prayer of the Righteous <hi>is ſet forth as incenſe, and the lifting up of his hands, as an evening ſacrifice</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Pſal. 141.2.</note>. And this is the incenſe and pure oblation which the Fathers generally underſtand to be meant in that place, <hi>to wit glorifying and bleſſing God, and Praiſe and Hymns</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">In Eccleſiis benedicite Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num Deum, <hi>Pſal.
57.</hi> ut pariter concurreret <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lachiae</hi> prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, in omni loco ſacrificium maxdum. Gloviae ſc. relatio &amp; bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictio &amp; laus &amp; hymni, <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tull. contra Marcion. l. 3.</hi>
               </note> as <hi>Tertullian</hi> in ſo many words explains this place, and again, <hi>a pure offering as</hi> Malachi <hi>ſpeaks is an honeſt prayer from a pure Conſcience</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">Dicente <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lachia</hi> ſacrifici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um mundum ſc. ſimplex Oratio de conſcientia, pura <hi>Ib. l. 4.</hi>
               </note> and ſo in
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:96982:15"/>other places<note n="(c)" place="margin">Adverſus Judaeos,
<hi>Ib.</hi>
               </note> he explains it altogether of ſpiritual ſacrifices.
<hi>Euſebius</hi> calls this pure offering of <hi>Malachi, the incenſe of Prayers</hi>
               <note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Euſeb. Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrat.</hi> l. 1. c. 6.</note> St. <hi>Hierom</hi> upon the place ſays the prophet, <hi>teaches that the prayers of holy men ſhould be offered to the Lord not only in the ſingle Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince of</hi> Judaea, to which the Jewiſh ſacrifices were confined, <hi>but in every place</hi>
               <note n="(e)" place="margin">Docet ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones ſanctorum Domino offeren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das eſſe non in unâ orbis pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinciâ, Judaeâ, ſed in omni loco.
<hi>Hieron. in Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lach. 1.</hi>
               </note> There can be no ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice more acceptable to God, no offering with which he is ſo well pleaſed, no incenſe that is of ſo ſweet a ſavour as the prayers and praiſes of a devout mind, and a pure and unblemiſht Conſcience, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially when theſe are kindled and enflamed to the higheſt degrees and ardors at the bleſſed Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, when the ſoul truly ſenſible of the Love of God, and the infinite kindneſs of its dying Saviour, when it has the ſymbol and repreſentation of his death before it, ſhall pour out its grateful and hearty reſentments, and thereby offer up a more pure and pretious ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, then <hi>thouſands of Rams, or ten thouſand rivers of Oyl.</hi> This is that incenſe, and that pure offering of Chriſtians which is foretold by the prophet, and this eſpecially offered in the moſt ſacred office of our Religion, the bleſſed Euchariſt; and therefore ſome of the Fathers, <hi>Juſtin Martyr, Irenaeus,</hi> and St.
<hi>Auſtin</hi> apply this place to the bleſſed Sacrament, not as any proper ſacrifice is there offered, but only ſuch divine and ſpiritual ones as theſe; and in what ſenſe they call that a ſacrifice and we own it be ſo, I ſhall ſhow after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.</p>
            <p>Why ſhould our Adverſaries then charge us with having no ſacrifice, and therefore as they charitably tell us no Religion when we have the beſt and the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſt ſacrifice that can be, that <hi>which will pleaſe the Lord much better then an Ox or a Bullock that hath horns and hoofs</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 69.31. and 40.6. Iſai.
1.11.</note>. God was never pleaſed with thoſe external ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices for themſelves, but he often refuſes and diſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gards <pb n="25" facs="tcp:96982:15"/>gards them even under the Jewiſh diſpenſation, and they were all to ceaſe with that, and inſtead of ſuch mean ſacrifices and external oblations which were to be offered then but in one place, there ſhould in every place under Chriſtianity be offered the more pure and ſpiritual ſacrifices, the incenſe of prayer, and the pure oblation of praiſe and thankſgiving, and ſuch like Chriſtian ſacrifices as are often mentioned in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and which are meant in this prophecy of <hi>Mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chi,</hi> of which we ſhall have further occaſion to ſpeak by and by. 'Tis a ſort of Judaiſm then and a returning back to that leſs perfect and leſs ſpiritual ſtate to make the Religion of the Goſpel conſiſt in any viſible and external ſacrifice which our Adverſaries ſo earneſtly contend for, rather in thoſe ſacrifices which are more ſpiritual, and therefore more truly Chriſtian, and more agreeable to the ſpiritual Worſhip, and the ſpiritual Oeconomy of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>There are ſome other places of the old Teſtament brought by
<hi>Bellarmine,</hi> and other defenders of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of the Maſs, which are ſo weak and impertinent that they only ſerve to expoſe it, and therefore they are not at all montioned in the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> or in the Roman Catechiſm, ſuch is that ſaying of the prophet to <hi>Eli,</hi>
2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.35. <hi>That God would raiſe up a faithful prieſt, that ſhall do according to that which is in my heart and in my mind, and I will build him a ſure houſe, and he ſhall walk before mine anointed for ever.</hi> This new prieſt that was to ſucceed <hi>Eli</hi> was very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably to be a ſacrificing prieſt, but that he was to offer the ſacrifice of the Maſs, I leave thoſe who bring this place for it, to prove; for without doubt this was fulfilled long before Chriſt, in
<hi>Samuel</hi> who ſucceeded <hi>Eli,</hi> and in <hi>Zadoc</hi> who came in the room of <hi>Abiathar</hi> who was of the Family of <hi>Eli,</hi> and who
<hi>was thruſt out by Solomon from being prieſt unto the Lord, that he might <pb n="26" facs="tcp:96982:16"/>fulfil the word of the Lord, which he ſpake concerning the houſe of Eli in Shilo,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 2.27. as the Scripture obſerves, and to make this figurative or prophetical of the Chriſtian prieſthoods ſucceeding the <hi>Aaronical</hi> is great ſtrength of fancy, but a very weak argument however for the ſacrifice of the Maſs, unleſs that were the work of the Chriſtian prieſthood which is hard to be made out.</p>
            <p>The Second is that out of the 72, <hi>Pſalm</hi> at the 16.
<hi>v. There ſhall be an handful of corn in the earth upon the top of the Mountains.</hi> This handful of Corn is by ſuch Rabbinical men as
<hi>Galatinus</hi> made into a cake or <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centa,</hi> and that muſt needs be the wafer cake, which being upon the top of the Mountains, muſt be heaved and elevated over the head of the prieſts. This is ſuch an Argument for the ſacrifice of the Maſs as were ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to convert the Vicar of
<hi>Putney,</hi> who by the help of <hi>Galatinus</hi> can prove Tranſubſtantation out of the Rabbies, and had the good fortune to be brought into the true Church, not by Father <hi>P.</hi> or Father <hi>G.</hi> but by Rabbi <hi>Solomon,</hi> and thoſe two other ancient Rabbies of his,
<hi>Midras, Coheleth,</hi> which writ ſuch a Commentary upon
<hi>Eccleſiaſtes,</hi> that they are the very Commentary it ſelf. 'Tis ſtrange as he ſays,<note n="†" place="margin">Preſace to Conſenſus vete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram.</note> 
               <hi>that the Hebrow Writers ſhould long before Chriſts time have ſuch notions;</hi> but 'tis more ſtrange that ſome people ſince Chriſts time ſhould have no better Arguments for the great principles of their Religion, <hi>but the wind,</hi> as he goes on, <hi>bloweth where it listeth,</hi> and ſome men have ſuch a Wind Mill in their Crowns that any thing will turn it. Whatever Feaſts of ſweet Meats and dainties the Jews expected as foretold by this <hi>Pſalm</hi> in the days of the
<hi>Meſſiah,</hi> and were willing to mean by this handful of Corn on the top of the Mountains, they never dreamt of the ſacriſice of the Maſs.</p>
            <p>The next is that of the <hi>Proverbs</hi> 9. <hi>chap. 2d. verſe, <pb n="27" facs="tcp:96982:16"/>Wiſdom hath killed her beaſts, ſhe hath mingled her wine, ſhe hath alſo furniſhed her table,</hi> but I am ſure ſhe never made this Argument for the ſacrifice of the Maſs; I will improve this place if they pleaſe for the proof of other things, as of prieſts Celibacy, becauſe in the next words 'tis ſaid <hi>Wiſdom hath ſent out her maidens, verſe</hi> 4. of the Church of <hi>Romes</hi> being the houſe that was built by wiſdom, becauſe 'tis ſaid in the firſt verſe, <hi>She hath hewn out her ſeven pillars,</hi> which are as undoubtedly the ſeven Hills of <hi>Rome,</hi> as this Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legorical Banquet is the ſacrifice of the Maſs. Our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries ſure could not be very ſerious and in good earneſt, when they produced ſuch places as theſe, and therefore they muſt excuſe us for not being ſo in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering them.</p>
            <p>I ſhall mention but one more which if it be not as ridiculous, yet is as impertinent as the other, and that is out of <hi>Daniel, chapter</hi>
8. <hi>verſe</hi> 11. where it is ſaid <hi>the dayly ſacrifice was taken away,</hi> by a great prince, that is there prophetically deſcribed. It is plain that by the dayly ſacrifice there is meant that of the Jews, and by the prince who ſhould take it away <hi>Antiochus,</hi> who did literally perform this by deſtroying the Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſt. Worſhip, and horribly prophaning the Temple; if by him was allegorically and prophetically meant the Chriſtian Antichriſt, if I may ſo ſpeak, ſpoken of by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 2
<hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. and by St. <hi>John, Rev.</hi> 13. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed as a beaſt having ſeven heads and ten horns, as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> will have it<note n="†" place="margin">chap. <hi>9.</hi> de Miſ. l.
<hi>1.</hi>
               </note>, then whether this mark be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs not to him that ſets up the ſacrifice of the Maſs, and deſtroys as far as he has power, and takes away all the purer Worſhip of Chriſt, and has a great many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther characters upon him that look very ſuſpitious, will be a great queſtion, for which I dare ſay there are a great many more probabilities then that by the dayly ſacrifice here is meant the ſacrifice of the Maſs.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:96982:17"/>
            <p>I come now to the New Teſtament, where if there be any proofs for the ſacrifice of the Maſs, it is more likely to find them then in the Old, yet they produce twice as many ſuch as they are, out of that than this, and like ſome other people, are more beholden to dark Types and obſcure propheſies of the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to make out their principles, then to the clear light of the Goſpel, and to any plain places in the New, and yet if any ſuch doctrine as this were to be received by Chriſtians, and if any ſuch wonderful and eſſential part of Worſhip were appointed by Chriſt, or taught and practiſed by the Apoſtles, we ſhould ſurely have it more plainly ſet down in the New Teſtament then they are able to ſhow it.</p>
            <p>The firſt place they urge from thence belongs no more to the ſacrifice of the Maſs, then the firſt Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment does in the Decalogue, and they had as good have quoted our Saviour words to the Devil, <hi>Thou ſhalt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the Lord thy God,</hi> and ſo have proved from thence that God ought to be Worſhipt by the ſacrifice of the Maſs, as thoſe to the Woman of <hi>Samaria</hi> which <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">de Miſſ. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> brings to this purpoſe out of <hi>John</hi> 4.21, 23. <hi>The hour cometh when ye ſhall neither in this mountain, nor yet at Jeruſalem worſhip the Father, for the hour cometh and now is when the true Worſhippers ſhall worſhip the Father in ſpirit and in truth.</hi> From whence he infers that they muſt Worſhip him by ſacrifice, and that this muſt be the ſacrifice of the Maſs, and that this is to Worſhip him in ſpirit and truth. If this be not all evidence and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration, there is none in <hi>Euclid;</hi> and if we may not here cry out, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the Maſs is found, we are blind and obſtinate, but I ſee very little more for it here then from the other places I named, but rather ſomething againſt it, for to Worſhip God in Spirit and Truth, and that becauſe he is a Spirit as our Saviour there adds
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:96982:17"/>
               <hi>verſe</hi> 24. is not to Worſhip him by an external, viſible, Typical ſacrifice as the Maſs is, and as thoſe of the Jews were, but by a more pure and ſpiritual Worſhip of praiſe and thankſgiving, and prayer, ſuch as that of Chriſtians is to be, as more ſuitable to the ſpiritual na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of God; and theſe ſpiritual ſacrifices of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans are not to be tyed to one place, as thoſe more groſs and carnal ones of the Jews were, which was the thing our Saviour here deſigned. The greateſt part of the publick Jewiſh Worſhip was fixt to the Temple and to <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> their Tithes, and Firſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruits, and Firſtlings, and Feſtivals as well as their ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, and there may be divine Worſhip without ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice as well as with it, and whatever the Worſhip be, which our Saviour here ſays was to be ſpiritual it was not like the Jewiſh, to be fixt to one place, which is the true ſcope of thoſe words to the <hi>Samaritan</hi> Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in anſwer to her queſtion,
<hi>v.</hi> 20. whether mount <hi>Gerizim</hi> or <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was the true place of Worſhip, which was the great diſpute between the Jews and the
<hi>Samaritans;</hi> our Saviour determines for neither, but puts an end to the queſtion, and ſays, that now under the Goſpel, the Worſhip of God was not local, and as to the manner of it, that it was ſpiritual.</p>
            <p>The ſecond and principal Argument for the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the Maſs, is from Chriſts inſtitution and firſt ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebration of the Euchariſt with his Diſciples, and here indeed is the true place to find it if there be any ſuch thing, but I have already ſhown<note n="‖" place="margin">pag. 8, 9, 10.</note> that Chriſt did nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then ſacrifice himſelf nor command his Diſciples to do ſo, and have taken away that which is the very Foundation of the Maſs-ſacrifice, and without which every thing elſe that can be ſaid for it falls to the ground.</p>
            <p>There are but two other and thoſe very weak ones behind, the one out of the 13th. of the <hi>Acts,</hi> where it <pb n="30" facs="tcp:96982:18"/>is ſaid of <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> and the prophets and Teachers of the Church at <hi>Antioch, that they miniſtered unto the Lord;</hi> but could not they miniſter and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the divine office and ſervice without ſacrificing? it muſt be firſt proved that that was part of the religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous office before it can appear that it was meant here; it is ſaid they faſted and prayed, &amp; in that probably their <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or Miniſtry conſiſted, or as St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">Homil. <hi>37.</hi> in Act.</note>, and after him
<hi>Oecumenius</hi> explain it in preaching, but that they ſacrificed there is not the leaſt evidence. The word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, doth not ſignifie to ſacrifice but to perform any proper function and therefore it is attributed in the Scripture both to the Angels who are called <hi>mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring ſpirits</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Heb.
1.14.</note>, and to the Magiſtrates who are called the <hi>Miniſters of God</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Rom. 13.6</note>, and yet ſacrificing I ſuppoſe belongs to neither of them, nor does their own vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar Latin ſo Tranſlate it here.</p>
            <p>The laſt is out of the 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. for
<hi>Bellarmine</hi> gives up that out of the <hi>Hebrews</hi> 13. <hi>We have an altar of which they have no right to eat who ſerve the Tabernacle,</hi> though 'tis as much to his purpoſe in my mind as any of the reſt, <hi>but ſome Catholick</hi> Writers, he ſays, <hi>do by altar mean there, either the Croſs or Chriſt himſelf</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Quia non de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunt ex Catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis qui eo loco per altare intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligunt crucem aut ipſum Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stum non urgeo ipſum locum, <hi>Bellarm. de Miſ. c. 14.</hi>
               </note> ; but if it were meant of the Euchariſt, that is but an Altar in an improper ſenſe, as the ſacrifice offered on it is but im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper and metaphorical as we ſhall prove, but in the place to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> the Apoſtle Commands them not to eat of <hi>things offered to Idols,</hi> for to eat of them was to partake of things ſacrificed to Devils, and ſo to have communion with Devils, which was very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit for thoſe who were partakers of the Lords Table, and therein truly communicated of the Body and Blood of Chriſt, as thoſe who ate of the Jewiſh ſacrifices were partakers of the Jewiſh Altar. Now what is here of the ſacrifice of the Maſs, or any way ſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to it? Why, yes, the Apoſtle compares the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:96982:18"/>of the Lord with the Table of Devils, and eating of the Lords ſupper with eating the Jewiſh and the Heathen ſacrifices, therefore the Chriſtians ought to have an Altar as well as the Jews, and what they fed on, ought to be ſacrificed as well as the Heathen <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but the Apoſtle ſays nothing of this, nor makes any ſuch compariſon between them, but only ſhows the unfitneſs of Chriſtians eating of the Heathen ſacrifices who partook of the Lords Table; he does not call the Lords Table an Altar, nor the Euchariſt a ſacrifice, nor was there any danger that the Chriſtians ſhould go to eat in the Idol Temples, but he would not have them eat of their ſacrifices brought home, and the whole compariſon lyes here, the eating the Lords Supper did make them true partakers of the Lords body and blood ſacrificed upon the Croſs, as eating of the Jewiſh ſacrifices did make the Jews partakers of the Jewiſh Altar, and as eating of things offered to Idols was having fellowſhip with Devils, ſo that they who partook of ſuch holy food as Chriſtians did, ſhould not communicate of ſuch execrable and diabolical food as the Heathen <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> If indeed Chriſtians could not partake of Chriſts body and blood in the Euchariſt unleſs they firſt made a proper ſacrifice and oblation of them, then the Apoſtles diſcourſe would neceſſarily ſuppoſe and imply them to be thus offered, as the Jewiſh and Heathen ſacrifices were before they were eaten, but ſince Chriſts body and blood being once offered upon the Croſs is a ſufficient ſacrifice and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of them, and the Euchariſt is a religious and Sacramental Feaſt upon the ſacrifice of Chriſt once offered, this is ſufficient for the Apoſtles ſcope and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign in that place, where there is no other compariſon made between the Table of the Lord, and the Table of Devils, but that one makes us to be partakers of the body and blood of Chriſt, and the other to have <pb n="32" facs="tcp:96982:19"/>Fellowſhip with Devils, and as to the Jewiſh Altar the Antitheſis does not lye here as
<hi>Bellarmine</hi> would have it, between that and the Table of the Lord, that both have proper ſacrifices offered upon them, which are eaten after they are ſacrificed; but the Croſs of Chriſt rather is the Antitheſis to the Jewiſh Altar, on which ſacrifices were really and properly ſlain, which are not on the Chriſtian Altar, and the feeding and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking of thoſe ſacrifices ſo offered, whereby they were made partakers of the Altar, this anſwers to the ſacramental feeding upon Chriſts body and blood in the Chriſtian Altar whereby we are made partakers of the Croſs of Chriſt, and have the vertue and merit of his ſacrifice communicated to us.</p>
            <p>Thus I have conſidered and fully anſwered what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever our Adverſaries can bring out of Scripture for their ſacrifice of the Maſs, I ſhall now offer ſome places of Scripture that are directly contrary to it, and do perfectly overthrow it: and though their cauſe muſt neceſſarily ſink if the Scripture be not for it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe without a Scriptural Foundation there can be no divine inſtitution of a ſacrifice which is neceſſary by their own confeſſion, and ſo eſſential a part of worſhip ought ſurely to be appointed by no leſs an Authority then of God himſelf, ſo that if it be deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of Scripture-grounds it muſt like a Caſtle in the Air fall of it ſelf, and can have nothing elſe to ſupport it. Yet I ſhall ſhow that Scripture is plainly againſt it and that ſo ſtrong a battery may be raiſed and levelled at it from thence, that none of their Arts or devices can be able to withſtand it; it is from thoſe known places of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> from whence I have already ſhown how contrary their Doctrine is to our Saviours Melchiſedecian prieſthood, I ſhall now urge thoſe places out of that Epiſtle wherein the Divine <pb n="33" facs="tcp:96982:19"/>Authour of it, who was probably St. <hi>Paul,</hi> largely and deſignedly ſhoweth the excellency of Chriſts ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice above thoſe under the Law upon this account, that it had ſo much vertue and efficacy in it, that by <hi>one offering</hi> it obtained full and perfect Remiſſion of ſin, whereas this was the great imperfection of the others, and ſhowed their great weakneſs and inſufficiency that they were ſo often offered, and ſo frequently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated, <hi>every prieſt</hi> of the Jews <hi>ſtandeth dayly mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring and offering oftentimes the ſame ſacrifices which can never take away ſin, chap.</hi> 10.11. And it was plain they could not take away ſin becauſe they were ſo often offered over again, either every day or every year, <hi>For the Law can never with thoſe ſacrifices which they offered year by year continually, make the comers thereunto perfect, chap.</hi>
10. <hi>verſe</hi> 1. <hi>For then would they not have ceaſed to be offered? becauſe that the worſhippers once purged, ſhould have had no more conſcience of ſins. But in thoſe ſacrifices there is a remembrance again made of ſins every year, verſe</hi> 2, 3. Thoſe ſacrifices being but like the acknowledgments of a Debtor, that he owed a great ſumm which he had no way fully to pay off and diſcharge, but he raiſed and brought what he could, and ſo owned the Debt, and that he had not where withal to take it quite off, nor to make that ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution and ſatisfaction which was neceſſary. But ſuch was the value of the ſacrifice of Chriſt, that it was a perfect price and payment, and made full ſatisfaction at once; ſo that <hi>By one offering he hath perfected for ever them that are ſanctified, chap.</hi> 10. <hi>verſe</hi> 14. and made ſuch full atonement and expiation by that, that there is no more need, nor <hi>remains no more ſacrifice for ſins, but this man after he had offered one ſacrifice for ſins, for ever ſat down on the right hand of God, verſe</hi> 12. as having fully done the work of a prieſt upon Earth, and having no need to offer any furt her ſacrifice, <hi>nor <pb n="34" facs="tcp:96982:20"/>yet that he ſhould offer himſelf often, as the high prieſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treth into the holy place, every year with blood of others: chap.</hi> 9. 25. <hi>(For then muſt he often have ſuffered ſince the ſoundation of the world) but now once in the end of the world, hath he appeared to put away ſin by the ſacrifice of himſelf, verſe</hi> 26. <hi>and Christ was once offered to bear the ſins of many, verſe</hi> 28. <hi>And we are ſanctified through the offering of the body of Jeſus Chriſt once for all, chap.</hi> 10. verſe 10. <hi>So that Christ our high prieſt needeth not dayly, as thoſe high prieſts, to offer up ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, firſt for himſelf, and then for the people: For this he did once when he offered up himſelf,</hi> chap. 7. ver. 27. Nothing can be ſaid plainer againſt the ſacrifice of the Maſs, wherein Chriſt is often offered and that as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly and truly, they pretend, as the Jewiſh ſacrifices were, or as he was upon the Croſs, when it is here ſo much inſiſted upon that Chriſts ſacrifice was but once offered, whereas thoſe under the Law were often; and this made an argument of their weakneſs and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection, and of the full vertue and value of the other: Muſt it not appear very ſtrange after this that it ſhould be made the great part of ſome mens Religion, to repeat the ſame ſacrifice of Chriſt every day, and to offer him up again every day upon the Altar, as truly as the Jews offered their ſacrifices day by day continually, and as he once offered up himſelf upon the Croſs, and to make this dayly ſacrifice of him in the Maſs have as true a vertue to propitiate God and expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate ſins as the other had, and to be every way as true &amp; proper a ſacrifice as the other. I need not labour much to ſhow how contrary this is to this diſcourſe of the Authour to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> and to the true ſcope and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of it, it appears ſo evidently to be ſo, that our Adverſaries are put to the greateſt ſtreights and diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties imaginable to make themſelves think otherwiſe, and to reconcile what the Apoſtle here ſays of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice <pb n="35" facs="tcp:96982:20"/>of Chriſt, with what their Church ſays of the ſacrifice of the Maſs, and that they are perfectly incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent, notwithſtanding all their pretences and eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, I ſhall make appear by what follows.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, They tell us that their ſacrifice of the Maſs, is but the very ſame with the ſacrifice of Chriſt upon the Croſs, and ſo it does not at all take off from the vertue of that, or ſuppoſe that to be imperfect, ſince this is no other, nor no new ſacrifice, but only the ſame both in nature and vertue with <hi>that;</hi> if it were another ſacrifice indeed, or were ſuppoſed to have a diſtinct vertue and efficacy from that of the Croſs, it might reflect upon that, and be injurious to it, but ſince they declare it to be the ſame, they do not conceive how it is any way ſo. But the Apoſtles diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe (for it is probable an Apoſtle was Authour of this Epiſtle) in the forementioned places, is about re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peating the ſame ſacrifices, and offering them up year by year continually, and from hence he grounds the imperfection of them, and that they could not make the comers thereunto perfect, <hi>chap.</hi> 10. <hi>v.</hi> 1. Theſe ſacrifices indeed were many and of ſeveral ſorts which they offered, but they ſtill offered them up again and again, both dayly and yearly, and it was their often offering of them as well as their multitude which the Apoſtle reflects upon, <hi>their dayly miniſtring and offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing oftentimes the ſame ſacrifices, chap.</hi> 10. <hi>verſe</hi> 11. whereas Chriſt by <hi>one</hi> ſacrifice and that <hi>once</hi> offered,
<hi>chap.</hi> 9. <hi>verſe</hi> 28. did fully put away ſin, ſo that had the ſame ſacrifice of Chriſt been often offered, as the ſame ſacrifices of the Jews were, it had upon that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count been liable to the ſame charge of imperfection; for if <hi>by one offering it had for ever perfected them that are ſanctified,</hi> and had obtained perfect and plenary Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſins, and had done the whole work, and <pb n="36" facs="tcp:96982:21"/>had the whole effect of all that ſacrifices were intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for, then what need it be any further offered? the offering up the ſame ſacrifice, and continuing dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to offer it, ſhows that it was not ſufficient, nor did do the buſineſs at once offering, as the frequent uſing the ſame medicine ſhows that it has not fully cured the wound, nor yet perfectly done its work.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The ſacrifice of the Maſs, they ſay, is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to apply the vertue and merit of the ſacrifice of the Croſs; for though the ſacrifice of the Croſs like a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werful medicament have ſufficient vertue in it, yet what does that ſignifie unleſs it be applyed to us, which it is by the ſacrifice of the Maſs? But is there not another way to apply that to us? Is it not appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to us by Faith, and by the common means of Chriſts own inſtitution, the Chriſtian Sacraments, and eſpecially by the Worthy Receiving of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, wherein as the Apoſtle ſays, <hi>The cup of bleſſing which we bleſs, is it not the communion of the blood of Chriſt, and the bread which we break, is it not the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the body of Christ,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16. We do hereby communicate and are made partakers of Chriſts Body as it was ſacrificed for us, that is, of all the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues and benefits of his ſacrifice by being as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle adds, verſe 17. <hi>Made partakers of that One bread,</hi> that is ſurely by eating it ſacramentally and religiouſly as Chriſt has appointed; for it would ſound very hard and be a very odd expreſſion, to ſay we are partakers of that one bread by the ſacrificing or offering up of that bread, when they will not own that the bread is ſacrificed, or if it were, could we well be thereby partakers of it, but 'tis the eating of that bread which makes us partakers of it; and 'tis the eating Chriſts Body, and drinking his Blood in the bleſſed Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that communicates and applies the vertue of his
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:96982:21"/>ſacrifice of the Croſs to us, and not the ſacrificing of that again, as the Apoſtle goes on verſe 18. <hi>Are not they who eat of the ſacrifices, partakers of the Altar?</hi> 'tis eating and communicating, that makes us parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of Chriſts ſacrifice. We do then eat of the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and ſo partake of it as the Jews did of their ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices; the communion is a feaſting upon a true <hi>oblatum,</hi> the body and blood of Chriſt, as is excellently made out by a Learned man of our own, we do not there ſacrifice Chriſts body, but only ſacramentally eat of it, as being already ſacrificed and offered once for all, by Chriſt himſelf upon the Croſs. It is not at all neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry that it ſhould be ſacrificed again
<hi>by</hi> us to make us become partakers of it; for cannot a ſacrifice be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed without being ſacrificed again? It ſeems a very ſtrange and uncouth way to ſacrifice the ſame thing over and over in order to applying the vertue of it, as if the Jews when they had ſlain the Paſchal Lamb, muſt have ſlain another Lamb in order to the partak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the vertue of it, no they were to eat of it for that purpoſe, and ſo are we of Chriſts ſacrifice, and this is the way whereby we do communicate of it, and have its full vertue applyed to us. It was the weakneſs and inſufficiency of their ſacrifices that made them ſo often repeat them, and ſacrifice them anew, but Chriſts ſacrifice being perfect is to be but once offered, though it be often to be eaten and partaken of by us, which it may be without being again ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The Authour of this Epiſtle makes not the leaſt mention of Chriſts ſacrifice being offered again upon Earth, or of its being repeated in the ſacrifice of the Maſs, but after he himſelf had once offered it upon the Croſs, he immediately ſpeaks of his preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it to God in Heaven, and there by vertue of it <pb n="38" facs="tcp:96982:22"/>interceeding and mediating with him for us, <hi>that by his own blood he entered into the holy place, having ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained eternal Redemption for us, chap.</hi> 9.
<hi>ver.</hi> 12. as the Jewiſh high prieſt on the great day of expiation after he had offered the ſacrifice of atonement for the whole Congregation upon the Altar, carried the blood of it into the Holy of Holies, and there ſprinkled it before the mercy-ſeat, <hi>Levit.</hi> 16.15. This great An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſary ſacrifice for the whole Congregation was the great Type and Figure of Chriſts ſacrifice for all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, and the Holy of Holies was the Type of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and the High Prieſt, of Chriſt, as is confeſſed by all; Chriſt therefore our great High Prieſt to whom alone it belonged to offer this ſacrifice of Atonement and Expiation for the whole World, having done this upon the Croſs <hi>he entred not into the holy places made with hands which are the figures of the true, but into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven it ſelf, now to appear in the preſence of God for us, chap,</hi> 9. <hi>ver.</hi> 24. To appear there as our Advocate and Mediator, and by vertue of his own blood there preſented to his Father to make a very powerful inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion for us. Now from this diſcourſe of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle we have a full account of Chriſts ſacrifice that it was to be once offered upon the croſs, and then to be carried into the Holy of Holies in Heaven, and no more to be offered upon Earth, <hi>for this man after he had offered one ſacrifice for ſins, for ever ſat down on the right hand of God,</hi> chap. 10. ver. 12. The Apoſtle ſpeaks not one tittle, nor gives the leaſt hint or intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this ſacrifice being offered again by others up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Earth, this lyes croſs to the whole tenour of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and the ſimilitude and agreement which he repreſents between the Jewiſh ſacrifice of Atonement, and Chriſts is quite altered and deſtroyed by it, for beſides the High Prieſts offering this ſacrifice, this makes every leſſer Prieſt to be ſtill offering the ſame ſacrifice <pb n="39" facs="tcp:96982:22"/>upon the Altar, when the High Prieſt is entred with the blood of it into the Holy of Holies; and though he cannot go in there, upon which the vertue and the perfection of the ſacrifice does in great meaſure de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend, yet ſtill to offer the ſame ſacrifice; and beſides it makes this facrifice like to the Jewiſh, <hi>where every prieſt ſtandeth daily miniſtring and offering oftentimes the ſame ſacrifices, which</hi> for the reaſon ſhewed, they <hi>could never take away ſins, chap.</hi> 10. <hi>ver.</hi> 12. in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to which he ſays, <hi>this man after he had offered, one ſacrifice for ſins, for ever ſat down on the right hand of God, verſe</hi> 13. that is, Chriſts ſacrifice was never to be repeated as the Jewiſh were; for if it had been to be offered by others though not by Chriſt himſelf, and the Chriſtian Prieſts were to ſtand daily miniſtring and offering the ſame ſacrifice, both they and their ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice would have been the ſame upon this account with the Jewiſh, and there had not been that difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them, which the Apoſtle does there plainly mean and declare.</p>
            <p>Further it cannot but ſeem very ſtrange that when this Divine Author does ſo largely and copiouſly and deſignedly treat of the ſacrifice of Chriſt and of thoſe of the Jews, and compare them ſo much together, and ſhow the excellency of the one above the other, that he ſhould never ſay the leaſt word of the ſacrifice of the Maſs, when he had ſo much occaſion to do it, that it can hardly be imagined he ſhould have ſo wholly omitted it, had it been as others ſince account it, as true and proper a ſacrifice as any of the Jewiſh or of Chriſts himſelf upon the croſs.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, The Apoſtle here plainly layes down a principle directly contrary and wholly inconſiſtent with their Doctrine of the ſacrifice of the Maſs, and that is, that if Chriſt be offered he muſt ſuffer and that <pb n="40" facs="tcp:96982:23"/>without ſhedding of blood there is no Remiſſion. Nor yet ſaith he at the 25, 26. verſes, and 9th. chapter,
<hi>That he ſhould offer himſelf often, as the high priest entereth into the holy place every year with the blood of others. For then muſt he often have ſuffered ſince the foundation of the world, but now once in the end of the world hath he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to put away ſin by the ſacrifice of himſelf.</hi> For then muſt he often have ſuffered if he had been often offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, without ſuffering then Chriſt cannot be offered and ſacrificed, and indeed to ſacrifice any thing is to conſume and deſtroy it, ſo that it be wholly parted with and given up to God, and to ſacrifice any thing that is living, is to take away its life and to kill it, and ſo to make it ſuffer death, as a vicarious puniſhment in anothers ſtead; this is the common and allowed noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſacrifices, but Chriſt cannot thus ſuffer in the Maſs, therefore he cannot be truly offered or ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, ſince according to the Apoſtle if he be often offered he muſt often ſuffer; and they would not I hope cruciſie to themſelves the Lord of Life again, and put him to death upon the Altar as the Jews did upon the croſs, and yet without this they cannot truly ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice him, or properly offer him according to the Apoſtle. But this ſays their great Champion the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Meaux</hi> is done myſtically, <hi>Chriſt is myſtically ſlain, and doth myſtically ſuffer death upon the Altar,</hi> that is, by way of repreſentation and reſemblance, and the myſterious ſignification of what is done there, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſays to the <hi>Galatians, chap.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 1. <hi>Before whoſe eyes Jeſus Chriſt hath been evidently ſet forth crucified among you.</hi> Now ſo Chriſt may be crucified every time we hear or read his crucifixion lively repreſented to us, as we may ſee a bloody Tragedy without one drop of blood ſpilt, ſo Chriſt may be myſtically ſlain in the Sacrament when his body is broke, and his blood poured out in myſtery and repreſentation, but this is
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:96982:23"/>not true and proper Offering which is neceſſary to make a true and proper ſacrifice as they will have that of the Maſs to be; if they would be contented with a myſtical ſacrifice to repreſent and commemorate Chriſts death, that they know we are willing to allow, and then a myſtical ſuffering that is not a real and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, would be ſufficient for a myſtical that is not proper ſacrifice, but the ſuffering muſt be as true and proper as the ſacrifice, and if the one be but myſtical, the other muſt be ſo too; if the Bullock or Goat of the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>offering which was to be offered on the great day of Atonement had been only Myſtically ſlain, and Myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally offered upon the Altar, they had been as really alive for all that as any that were in the Fields, and had been no more true and proper ſacrifices of atone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and expiation then <hi>they</hi> were,
<hi>for without ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of blood,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſays, <hi>there is no Remiſſion, Heb.</hi> 9.22. it was the ſhedding or pouring out the blood in which the Life was ſuppoſed to be, and therefore the taking away the Life of the ſacrifice that did really make the ſacrifice to be truly propitiatory or avail able before God, as a price and recompence for the remiſſion of ſins; and how then can the ſacrifice of the Maſs be truly propitiatory, when the blood is not truly ſhed, when according to themſelves it is <hi>Incruentum ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium,</hi> an unbloody ſacrifice, and therefore according to the Apoſtle it cannot be propitiatory for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſins, as will be further inſiſted upon after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards. Thus we ſee how much there is in thoſe clear places of Scripture againſt the ſacrifice of the Maſs, and how little there is for it in thoſe dark ones, which are produced by our Adverſaries.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, It has no juſt claim to Antiquity nor was there any ſuch Doctrine or Practice in the Primitive Church; this is greatly boaſted and vaunted of, and <pb n="42" facs="tcp:96982:24"/>although their cauſe runs very low in Scripture, yet they pretend it carries all Antiquity before it, where nothing is more common than to have the name of Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, and Sacrifice, and Hoſt, and Victim attributed to the bleſſed Euchariſt, and to have it ſaid that we do there offer, and immolate and ſacrifice unto God; this we readily acknowledge, and though we can by no means allow Antiquity to take place of Scripture, or to ſet up either an Article of Faith, or eſſential part of Worſhip which is not in Scripture, and our Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries ſeem to agree with us in this, that there muſt be a divine Inſtitution for a ſacrifice, or elſe it can have no true foundation; ſo that if Scripture fails them,
'tis in vain to flye for refuge to Antiquity, yet we doubt not but that Scripture and Antiquity will be fairly recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled and be made very good Friends in this point; and both of them againſt the ſacrifice of the Maſs, as 'tis taught and practiſed in the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The name of Sacrifice and oblation is often given both in Scripture and Antiquity, in an improper gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and metaphorical ſenſe, thus it is applyed to the inward actions of the mind, to penitence and ſorrow for ſin, <hi>The ſacrifices of God are a broken ſpirit, a broken and a contrite heart, O God thou wilt not deſpiſe, Pſal.</hi> 51.17. To the outward Thankſgivings of the mouth, when <hi>we render unto God the Calves of our lips, Hoſea</hi> 14.2. <hi>When we offer unto him Thanksgiving, Pſal.</hi> 50.14. or as the Apoſtle more fully expreſſes it when he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands Chriſtians, <hi>to offer the ſacrifice of praiſe to God continually, that is the fruit of our lips, giving thanks to his name, Heb.</hi> 13.15. where the Metaphor is carried on in ſeveral words; and in the very next verſe 'tis ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to works of Mercy and Charity and beneficence to others, <hi>but to do good and to communicate, forget not, for with ſuch ſacrifices God is well pleaſed,</hi> verſe 16. and St.
<hi>Paul</hi> in another place calls the <hi>Philippians</hi> Charity,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:96982:24"/>
               <hi>an odour of a ſweet ſmell, a ſacrifice acceptable, well pleaſing to God, Philip.</hi> 4.18. Nay he calls preaching the Goſpel, a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which our Adverſaries earneſtly contend to mean nothing leſs then a ſacrifice, and the converting the Gentiles he calls a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>an offering acceptable to God, Rom.</hi> 15.16<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>. And in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place he calls the Faith of Chriſtians a ſacrifice, <hi>Philip.</hi> 2.17<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>. And his own Martyrdom an Oblati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<hi>Ib.</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.6. St. <hi>Peter</hi> not only calls works of Piety, <hi>Spiritual ſacrifices acceptable to God through Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt,</hi> but he aſcribes <hi>a holy Prieſthood</hi> to all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians <hi>to offer theſe up,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5. and upon that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count St. <hi>John</hi> alſo gives them the Title of Prieſts,
<hi>Rev.</hi> 1.6. Now as the holy Spirit of God often chooſes to uſe this phraſe, and metaphor which is very eaſie and natural, ſo from hence and in accommodation proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly both to the Jews and Heathens, the greateſt part of whoſe Religion was ſacrifices, the ancient Writers alſo do very frequently make uſe of it, and apply it both to actions of morality, and to all parts of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Worſhip, but eſpecially to the bleſſed Euchariſt, which is the moſt ſacred and ſolemn of all other, but they do not do this in the ſtrict and proper ſenſe of the word
<hi>ſacrifice,</hi> as is plain from the foregoing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances but in a large, and general, and metaphorical one, ſo that though our Adverſaries could muſter up ten times as many places out of the Fathers wherein the Euchariſt is called a ſacrifice and oblation, and in the celebrating of which we are ſaid to offer and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>molate to God, with which they are apt to make a great ſhow, and to triumph as if the victory were perfectly gained againſt us, yet they are all to no purpoſe, and would do no real execution upon us, unleſs they can prove that theſe are to be taken in a ſtrict and proper ſenſe, which it is neceſſary they ſhould be to make a proper ſacrifice, and not in a <pb n="44" facs="tcp:96982:25"/>large and Metaphorical one as we are willing to allow, &amp; in which the Scriptures, we ſee, do underſtand them, and ſo do the Fathers, as I ſhall evidently demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate. Upon what accounts and in what ſenſe the Fathers do call the Euchariſt a ſacrifice and oblation, and apply the phraſes of immolating and offering and the like to it, I ſhall now particularly conſider. And</p>
            <p n="1">1. They do this, upon the account of thoſe oblati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of bread and wine, and other things which it was the cuſtom for Chriſtians to bring when they came to the Communion, out of which a part was conſecrated for the Euchariſt, and the remainder was for a common Feaſt of love and a Religious entertainment, or for the maintenance of the Clergy, and the poor, to whom they were afterwards diſtributed. This Cuſtom the Apoſtle takes notice of the, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. and the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Writers expreſly mention it in ſeveral places, after the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or Feaſts of Love were for ſome abuſes laid aſide; <hi>Clemens Romanus</hi> in his firſt Epiſtle, the moſt anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent &amp; moſt unqueſtioned piece of Antiquity we have, ſpeaks expreſly of theſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Oblations, and joins them with the ſacred and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Offices<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Climens Ep. <hi>1.</hi> ad Corinth. p.
<hi>85.</hi> Edit. <hi>Oxon.</hi>
               </note>, and commends <hi>thoſe who make theſe their oblati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons orderly, and at the appointed times</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ib. p. 86.</note>. The Apoſtolic Canons that go under his name though their credit is not ſo authentic, ſpeak very particularly of theſe offerings, <hi>and of their being brought to the altar for a ſucri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. &amp;c. Canon. 3.</note>. <hi>Ignatius</hi> ſpeaks alſo of <hi>offering and of bringing the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. ſc. abſque Epiſcopo. Epiſt. ad Smyru.</note> 
               <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>theſe offerings as accompani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <pb n="45" facs="tcp:96982:25"/>with prayer and thanksgiving, and as the way by which Chriſtians worſhipt the Creator inſtead of the bloody ſacrifices and libations, and incenſe that were offered by others</hi>
               <note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. —Juſtin Martyr Apolog. 2.</note> 
               <hi>and theſe,</hi> ſays he,
<hi>we account the proper way of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouring him, not by conſuming his gifts in the fire, but by thus offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them for the poor, and for our ſelves. Irenaeus</hi> ſays, <hi>The Church offers to God, who affords us food, the firſt-fruits of his Gifts, and the firſt-fruits of his Creatures, not as if he wanted but that we may be grateful</hi>
               <note n="(*)" place="margin">Eccleſis, —offert Deo, ci qui nobis ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta praeſtat primitias ſuorum munerum, —pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitias Deo offerre ex ſuis creaturis non quaſi in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digenti ſed ut ipſi nec inſructuoſi, nec ingrati ſint.
<hi>Iraen. adverſ. Haereſ. l. 4. c. 32.</hi>
               </note> And though
<hi>Fevardentius</hi> in his Notes upon this and the other places of
<hi>Irenaeus,</hi> wherein he ſpeaks of this obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion would have it meant of the oblation of Chriſt himſelf in the Euchariſt, yet that is clearly diſproved by his ſo often calling it <hi>the offering. to God of his own Creatures,</hi> and <hi>the firſt-fruits of his Creatures</hi>
               <note n="(d)" place="margin">Primitias earum quae ſunt ejus crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turarum offerentes, — offerens ei ex gratiarum actione ex creatura ejus. <hi>Ib. c. 34.</hi>
               </note> which muſt be no other then of bread and wine and the like, and from hence he proves againſt the <hi>Marcionites</hi> that Chriſt was<note n="(e)" place="margin">Quomodo autem constabit eum panem in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quo gratiae actae ſunt — ſi non ipſum fabricatoris mundi filium dicant, <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </note> the Son of the Creator and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of the World, becauſe that his creatures were offered in the Euchariſt. St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> condemning and blaming ſome of the rich Women who came to the Sacrament without bringing theſe oblations, <hi>thou com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt,</hi> ſays he, <hi>into the Lords houſe, without a ſacrifice and takeſt part of that ſacrifice which the poor hath offered</hi>
               <note n="(f)" place="margin">in Dominicum ſine ſacrificio vonis, quae partem de ſacriſicio, quod pauper obtuli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſumis. <hi>Cypr. de Oper. &amp; Eleemoſ.</hi>
               </note> St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi> inſiſts upon the ſame thing and bids them <hi>offer the oblations which are conſecrated upon the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:96982:26"/>Altar, a man who is able ought to bluſh if he eat of anothers oblation</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Oblationes quae in altari conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cr antur oſſerte, erubeſcere debet homo idoneus; ſi de alienâ oblati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one communicet. <hi>Aug. Serm. 13. de Temp.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>without offering himſelf.</hi> Theſe oblations are expreſly called a ſacrifice in the Apoſtolic Canons, in <hi>Ignatius,</hi> and in St.
<hi>Cyprian,</hi> as Alms, and Works of Charity are in the Epiſtle to the
<hi>Hebrews</hi> chap. 13. ver. 16. and theſe in our Churches prayer before the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment we beg God to accept of. In the Apoſtolic Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions where we have the largeſt if not earlieſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the Euchariſtic office, the oblation is thus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, <hi>We offer to thee King and God according to thy appointment, this bread and this cup, and we beſeech thee to look graciouſly upon theſe gifts ſet before thee, O thou God who wanteſt nothing, and ſend thy holy Spirit upon this ſacrifice</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Apoſtol. Conſtit. l. 8. c. 12.</note> i. e. upon theſe oblations, <hi>and make them to be the body and blood of Chriſt, i. e.</hi> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crumentally and Vertually. In the <hi>Ordo Romanus,</hi> and in the Canon of the Maſs it ſelf<note n="(c)" place="margin">Te igitur Clementiſſime Pater per Jeſum Chriſtum Filium tuum Dominum noſtrum ſupplicts rogamus a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> petimus ut accepta habeas &amp; benedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cas haec dona, haec munera, haec Sancta Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficia illibata in primis quae tibi offerimus,—Hanc igitur oblationem ſervitutis noſtrae ſed &amp; cunctae familliae tuae quaeſumus Domine ut placatus acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pias— Quam Oblationem tu Deus in omnibus quaeſumus benedictam, aſcriptam, ratam, rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onabitem, acceptabilemque facere digneris: ut nobis corpus &amp; ſanguis fiat dilectiſſimi filii tui Domini noſtri Jeſu Chriſti. <hi>Ordo Romanus p. 62. Edit. Hittorp. Canon Miſſae.</hi>
               </note> there is this prayer over the oblations, <hi>that God would accept and bleſs theſe Gifts, theſe Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents, theſe Holy and undefiled ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices which we offer to thee,</hi> &amp;c. and another to the ſame purpoſe ſaid by their Prieſt with his hand ſtretched over the <hi>oblata, This oblation therefore of our ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and of thy whole Family, we beſeech thee, O Lord, mercifully to receive,</hi> &amp;c. And again, <hi>This oblation, O Lord, we beſeech thee to make bleſſed,</hi> &amp;c ſigning upon the <hi>oblata. That it may be to us the body and blood of thy deareſt Son our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> All theſe prayers over the oblations whereby they are preſented to God, are made before Conſecration, ſo <pb n="47" facs="tcp:96982:26"/>that the oblations which are here called Holy and pure Sacrifices are thought worthy of that Name before they are become the Body and Blood of Chriſt, and ſo made a proper facrifice in the preſent ſenſe of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> the Canon of the Maſs is Older then their New doctrine of the ſacrifice of the Maſs, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords plain evidence for applying the name of ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to the Euchariſt, upon the account of thoſe offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings and oblations that were made there.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Euchariſt is called a ſacrifice by the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents upon the account of thoſe religious Acts and Pious Exerciſes which are there performed by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout Communicants, and which are called ſacrifices both in Scripture and in the Fathers, thus our Prayers may be as well a morning as <hi>an evening ſacrifice, Pſ.</hi> 141.2. And therefore as
<hi>Irenaeus</hi> ſays ſpeaking of the Euchariſt, <hi>God would have us continually offer a gift at his Altar,</hi> to wit, <hi>our Prayers and Oblations, which are directed to the heavenly Altar</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Vult nos quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ſine intermiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſione offerre mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus ad altare, eſt ergo altare in coelis, illue enim preces &amp; obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones noſtrae di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riguntur. <hi>Iren.</hi> l. <hi>4. adverſ. Haereſ. c.
33.</hi>
               </note>, though they are made at the Earthly. So our Praiſes and Thankſgivings which are then raiſed to the higheſt pitch when we have the greateſt inſtance of the Divine Love offered to our minds, are <hi>that ſacrifice which we are then to offer to God giving thanks to his name, Heb.</hi> 13.15. Namely for that Miracle of kindneſs Chriſt dying for us, from which the Euchariſt has its name, and for which reaſon it is oalled a
<hi>ſacrifice of Praiſe</hi> in the <hi>Ordo Romanus</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Memento Domine famulorum famularumque tuarum &amp; omnium circumadſtantium, quorum tibi fides cognita eſt &amp; nota devotio qui tibi offerunt hoc ſacrificium laudis pro ſe ſuisque om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus pro Redemptione animarum ſuaerum, pro ſpo ſalutis, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> —tibique reddunt vota ſua, <hi>Ordo Romanus p. 62.</hi>
               </note>, <hi>viz. for our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption and hope of Salvation,</hi> and alſo <hi>for thoſe vows which we then render unto God, when we preſent our bodies a living ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, holy and acceptable unto God, Rom.</hi> 12.1. as the Apoſtle ſpeaks; and as St. <hi>Austin</hi> expreſſes it, the <hi>Church is then offered to God, and is <pb n="48" facs="tcp:96982:27"/>made one body in Chriſt, when we are made to drink into one Spirit,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.13. <hi>and this is the ſacrifice of Chriſtians</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">Hoc eſt ſacrificium Chriſtianorum, multi unum corpus ſumus in Chriſto, quod etiam ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento altaris fidelibus noto frequentat Eccleſia uhi ei demonſtratur, quod in eâ oblatione quam offert ipſa offeratur.
<hi>Auguſt. Civitate Dei, l. 10. c. 6.</hi>
               </note> not only a ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Praiſe as 'tis called by <hi>Euſebius</hi>
               <note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Demonſtrat.</hi> l. 1. c. 10.</note> St.
<hi>Baſil</hi>
               <note n="(d)" place="margin">Liturg.</note> St.
<hi>Auſtin</hi>
               <note n="(e)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ad</hi> Pet. Diac. <hi>c.</hi>
9.</note> and other Fathers, whereby <hi>we offer up unto God the calves of our lips</hi> in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture phraſe, <hi>but wherein we offer and preſent unto God our ſelves, our ſouls and bodies, to be a reaſonable holy and lively ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice unto him, and though we are unworthy to offer unto him any ſacrifice, yet beſeech him to accept this our bound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en duty and ſervice,</hi> according to the Prayer of our Church in its excellent office of the Communion. <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chior Canus,</hi> in his Defence of the ſacrifice of the Maſs, has unawares confeſt this Truth, That Chriſt did only offer up at his laſt Supper a ſacrifice of Praiſe and Thankſgiving, <hi>For to give thanks,</hi> ſays he, <hi>after the Jewiſh manner, and take the Cup into his hands, and lift it up, is truly to offer a ſacrifice of Thanksgiving. When Chriſt therefore ſaid, Do this, he plainly commanded his Apostles that what they ſaw him do they ſhould do alſo by offering up a ſacrifice of Eucharist,</hi> that is, <hi>of giving of Thanks</hi>
               <note n="(f)" place="margin">Ritu quippe Judaico gratias agere ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licem in manibus accipiendo, &amp; levando vere eſt hoſtiam gratiarum actionis offerre, Quùm itaque dixit Dominus, hoc facite, planè juſſit Apoſtolis ut quod ipſum facere cernebant, id quoque illi facerent Euchariſtiae hoc eſt gratiarum actionis hoſtiam exhlbendo. <hi>Canus in locis Theolog. l. 12. p. 806.</hi>
               </note> and he expreſly ſpeaks againſt
<hi>Chriſts offering up a Maſs-ſacrifice for ſin then when the day of the bloody ſacrifice was now near, and the very hour ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching, and when their general ſacrifice was nigh by which it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Father to forgive all ſins</hi>
               <note n="(g)" place="margin">—Chriſtum in caenâ ſacrificium non pro peccato quidem ſed gratiacum tamen actionis ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuliſſe, —quod cum ſacrificii cruenti dies insta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret jam planè, aut certè jam appropinquaret hora, non oportibat hoſtiam in caenâ pro peccato Myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam exhibere, cum impenderet generalis hoſtia illa in quâ Patri complacuit omnia peccata reſolvi. <hi>Ib. p.
834.</hi>
               </note> which is to make the Euchariſt what we are willing to own it a ſacrifice of Thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving, and is in a few words <pb n="49" facs="tcp:96982:27"/>to cut the very throat of their Cauſe, as to this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Euchariſt is called a ſacrifice as it is both a Commemoration and a Repreſentation of Chriſts ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice upon the Croſs, ſo 'tis a commemorative and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentative ſacrifice, as we call that a bloody Tragedy which only repreſents a Murder, and we give the name of the thing to that which is but the reſemblance and likeneſs of it. The Jews called that the Paſſover which was but a memorial of it, and the Apoſtle ſays, <hi>we are buryed with Chriſt in Baptiſm, and riſe with him, Col.</hi> 2.12. when thoſe are but remotely ſignified, thus
<hi>Chriſt is immolated and ſacrificed in the Euchariſt,</hi> as St.
<hi>Auſtin</hi> ſpeaks, when according to the Gloſſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his words,
<hi>his immolation is repreſented and there is made a memorial of his paſſion</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">Christus Immolatur i. e. Chriſti immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latio repraeſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur &amp; ſit memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria Paſſionis. <hi>de Conſec. Diſt. 2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſays he, <hi>was but once offered and yet in the Sacrament he is dayly immolated, neither does he lye who ſays Christ is immola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, for if Sacruments had not the likeneſs of thoſe things whereof they are ſacraments, they would be no ſacraments at all, but from this likeneſs they received the names of the things themſelves</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">Nonne Chriſtus ſemel oblatus eſt &amp; tamen in Sacramento quotidie populis immolatur, nec men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titur qui dicit Chriſtum immolari, ſi enim ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramenta non haberent ſimilitudinem, earum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum quarum ſunt ſacramenta, nullo modo eſſent ſacramenta, ſed ex ſimilitudine ſaepe nomina earum accipiunt.
<hi>Auguſt. Ep. 120. ad Honorat.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Thus</hi> as he there gives ſeveral inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <hi>wherein that which is the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial of a thing, does for its ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude to that thing of which it is a memorial receive its name. When</hi> Eaſter <hi>approcheth, we ſay to morrow or next day is the paſſion of Christ, and on the Lords day, we ſay this day Chriſt aroſe, when Chriſts paſſion was but once and that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral years ago, and that day is ſaid to be Chriſts Reſurrection which yet it is not</hi>
               <note n="(c)" place="margin">Illud quod alicujus memoriale eſt propter ſimilitudinem ſaepe ejus rei cujus memoriale eſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men accipiat, ut appropinquante Paſchate, dici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus cras aut perendie eſt paſſio Chriſti, cumſemel tantum ante multos annos ſit paſſus, &amp; die Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minicâ dicimus, hodie Chriſtus reſurrexit, prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſimilitudinem enim dies ille id eſſe dicitur, quod tamen non eſt.
<hi>Ib.</hi>
               </note> What we call then a ſacrifice is a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:96982:28"/>or a ſign and a repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of a ſacrifice, as he ſays in another place<note n="(d)" place="margin">Quod appellamus ſacriſicium ſignum eſt &amp; repraeſentatio ſacrificii.
<hi>Auguſt. de Civit. Dei l. 10. c. 5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>We offer the ſame ſacrifice that Chriſt did, for the paſſion of Chriſt is the ſacrifice? which we offer,</hi>
               <note n="(e)" place="margin">Paſſio enim Domini eſt ſacriſicium quod efferimus. <hi>Cypr. Ep. 3.</hi>
               </note> in St. Cyprians words; <hi>or rather we perform a remembrance of a ſacrifice</hi> as St. Chryſoſtom ſpeaks<note n="(f)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Chryſoſt. in Heb. 10. Hom. 17.</note>, and after him
<hi>Theophylact, We always offer him or rather we make a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of his offering</hi>
               <note n="(g)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Theophylact. in Heb. 10.</note> 
               <hi>don't we offer unbloody ſacrifices, yes, we make a remembrance of his</hi> bloody <hi>death</hi>
               <note n="(h)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ib.</note> 
               <hi>ſo that inſtead of a ſacrifice, i. e.</hi> a proper one, <hi>he hath commanded us perpetually to offer up a memorial,</hi> as <hi>Euſebius</hi> more ſtrictly words it<note n="(i)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Euſeb. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrat. l. 1. c. 10.</note>. If we come down to the Elder Schoolmen before the ſacrifice of the Maſs was under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood in ſo ſtrict and proper a ſenſe as it is now in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and in the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> we ſhall find them calling it a ſacrifice only upon this account that it is, <hi>a memorial and repreſentation of the true ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and of the ſacred immolation made upon the Altar of the croſs,</hi> which are the very words of <hi>Peter Lom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard</hi>
               <note n="(k)" place="margin">Ad hoc breviter dici poteſt illud quod offertur &amp; conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur à ſacerdote vocari ſacrifici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um &amp; oblatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem quia memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria eſt &amp; reprae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentatio veri ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificii, &amp; ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctae immolatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis factae in arâ crucis.
<hi>Bombard. l. 4. Diſt. 12.</hi>
               </note> Maſter of the Sentences, and Father of the Schoolmen; whom <hi>Thomas Aquinas</hi> ſeems wholly to follow, and more largely thus to explain the reaſon why the celebration of the Sacrament may be called a ſacrifice and immolation of Chriſt,
<hi>becauſe,</hi> ſays he, <hi>firſt it is an image of Chriſts paſſion, for as</hi> St. <hi>Austin</hi> ſays to <hi>Simplicius, Images uſed to be called by the names of thoſe things of which they are Images, as when we look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a painted Table or Wall, we ſay this is</hi> Cicero
<hi>and this <pb n="51" facs="tcp:96982:28"/>is</hi> Saluſt, <hi>but the celebration of this Sacrament is a repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentative image of Chriſts paſſion which is the true immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation. Another way as to the effect of Chriſts paſſion it may be called a ſacrifice, becauſe by this Sacrament we are made partakers of the fruit of the Lords Paſſion</hi>
               <note n="(c)" place="margin">Tum quia hujus ſacramenti celebratio ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go quaedam eſt paſſionis Chriſti, tum etiam quia per hoc Sacramentum participes eſſicimur fructus Dominicae paſſionis —convenienter dicitur Chriſti immolatio. Primò quidem quia ſicut <hi>Auguſtinus</hi> ad <hi>Simplicium,</hi> ſolent imagines earum rerum nominibus appellari quarum imagines ſunt, ſicut cum intuentes tabulam aut parietem pictum, dici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus ille <hi>Cicero</hi> eſt, &amp; ille <hi>Saluſtius,</hi> celebratio autem hujus Sacramenti imago quaedam eſt reprae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentativa paſſionis Chriſti, quae eſt vera ejus im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>molatio— alio modo quantum ad effectum paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis Chriſti quia ſc. per hoc ſacramentum participes efficimur fructûs Dominicae paſſionis. <hi>Thom. Aquin. ſum. 3. pars qu. 83.</hi>
               </note> Had the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> gone no further then this and not made the Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt a ſacrifice in any other ſenſe then as it is commemorative and exhibitive of Chriſts true ſacrifice and immolation upon the croſſe, we had not blamed them, nor had there been any controverſie between us in this matter; or had they been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to have uſed the word ſacrifice in a large and figurative and improper ſenſe as the Fathers do, when they call the Euchariſt a ſacrifice, and therefore they immediately correct themſelves as it were with this addition, <hi>or rather a remembrance of a ſacrifice,</hi> and explain the reaſon why they give it that name; but this would not ſerve our Adverſaries purpoſe, this would not make it a true proper propitiatory ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice for the quick and dead, this would not give it thoſe vertues which they aſſign to it as a proper ſacrifice in it ſelf diſtinct from its being a ſacrament, this would not make it ſo applicable to others who never partook or communicated of it, and ſo would not make it of ſo great price and value, that is, ſo marketable to themſelves, and therefore the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns this notion of its <hi>being a ſacrifice of Praiſe, and Thanksgiving or a meer commemoration of Chriſts ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice upon the croſs and not a propitiatory one, or that it profits only him that takes it; or that it ought not to be offered for the quick and dead, for ſins, for puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:96982:29"/>for ſatisfactions and other neceſſities</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">Siquis dixerit Miſſae ſacrificium tantum eſſe laudis &amp; gratiarum actionis aut nudam commemorationem ſacrificii in cruce peracli non autem propitiatorium vel ſoli prodeſſe ſumenti, neque pro vivis &amp; deſunctis, pro peccatis, pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, ſatisfactionibus &amp; aliis neceſſitatibus affer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri debere, anathema ſit. <hi>Concil. Trid. de ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crif. Miſſae. Canon 3.</hi>
               </note> They make it to have the true vertue of a ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice in its ſelf, as a true price and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and compenſation to God for ſin, and a true ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to divine Juſtice for the puniſhment thereof, as much as the ſacrifice upon the croſs, and that they have the power of applying this whenſoever, and for whomſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they offer it, which is to have the greateſt trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in the World in their hands, and to be able to make a proper propitiation for ſin, which belongs only to Chriſt; but they can offer Chriſt, as truly as he offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red himſelf, and ſet him upon the Altar as true a ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice as he hung upon the croſs. Chriſt I own is in ſome ſenſe offered up to God by every communicant in the Sacrament when he does mentally and internal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly offer him to God and preſent as it were his bleeding Saviour to his Father, and deſire him for his ſake to be merciful to him and forgive him his ſins, this internal oblation of Chriſt and his paſſion is made by every faithful Chriſtian in his particular private devotions, and eſpecially at the more ſolemn and publick ones of the bleſſed Sacrament. When he has the facred ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bols of Chriſts death before him, and does then plead the vertue of Chriſts ſacrifice before God, not of the ſacrifice then before him, but of the paſt ſacrifice of the croſſe. This is all done by the inward acts the Faith, the devotion of the mind, whereby as St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi> ſays, <hi>Chriſt is then ſlain to any one when he-believes him ſlain</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">Tum Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus cuique occi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditur cum evedit occiſum. <hi>Auguſt. quaeſt. Evang. l. 2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and when we believe in Chriſt from the very remains of this thought Chriſt is dayly immolated to us</hi>
               <note n="(c)" place="margin">Cum credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus in Chriſtum ex ipſis reliquiis cogitationis Chriſtus nobis quotidie immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latur, <hi>Id. in Pſal. 73.</hi>
               </note> as St.
<hi>Hierom</hi> ſays, <hi>when we hear the word of our Lord, his fleſh and blood is as it were poured into our Ears</hi>
               <note n="(d)" place="margin">cum audimus Sermonem Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini caro Chriſti &amp; ſanguis ejus in auribus no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris funditur. <hi>Hieron. in Pſal. 147.</hi>
               </note> and ſo St.
<hi>Ambroſe, calls the virgins minds <pb n="53" facs="tcp:96982:29"/>thoſe Altars on which Chriſt is dayly offered,</hi> for the <hi>Redemption of the Body</hi>
               <note n="(e)" place="margin">Veſtras men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes confidenter altaria dixerim in quibus quoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diè pro Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione corporis Christus offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, <hi>Ambr. de Virg. l. 2.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>The Miniſter alſo does not only offer to God the oblations of the faithful at the Altar, and their ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual ſacrifices of prayer and praiſe which it is his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per duty in their names to preſent unto God, but he does offer as it were Jeſus Chriſt and his ſacrifice for the people by praying to God for the people as a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blic Miniſter, in and through the merits of Chriſts death and paſſion, and by conſecrating and admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring the bleſſed Sacrament; which is hereby made not only a commemorative ſacrifice of Chriſts body and blood, but does with the outward ſign, really ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibit the thing ſignified to the people. So that
'tis no wonder to meet with the words offering, and offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſts body and blood as attributed peculiarly to the Miniſter, as in thoſe known places of <hi>Ignatius</hi> his Epiſtles, <hi>'tis not lawful for the Prieſt to offer without the leave of the Biſhop.</hi> And in
<hi>Tertullian, when the Prieſt is wanting, thou baptizest and offereſt, and art a Prieſt to thy ſelf,</hi> and in the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> where <hi>Deacons are forbid to offer the body of Chriſt, Can.</hi> 14. To offer, and to offer Chriſts body and blood is made the pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar office of the Prieſt, as he alone is the ſteward of theſe Myſteries of God, and the proper Miniſter to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrate and celebrate this Holy Sacrament, and in that to offer up the peoples requeſts to God in the name of Chriſt and his meritorious croſs and paſſion, and by vertue of that to mediate for the people, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent as it were Chriſts ſacrifice on their behalf; that is Chriſts body and blood as an objective ſacrifice in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and as formerly truly offered upon the croſs, and now ſacramentally and improperly upon the Altar, but not as an external viſible proper ſacrifice, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectively preſent and placed upon the Altar by the hands of the Prieſt, and by a viſible and external <pb n="54" facs="tcp:96982:30"/>action preſented to God, and offered up as the Jewiſh ſacrifices uſed to be by any conſumption or alteration as they hold the ſacrifice of the Maſs to be. No ſuch can be found in any of the Fathers or ancient Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtic Writers though they ſpeak often of ſacrifices and oblations, and ſometimes of offering Chriſt, and the body of Chriſt in the Euchariſt, yet not at all in the preſent ſenſe of the Romiſh Church, or according to the doctrine of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> or the Writers ſince that; which how contrary it is to Antiquity I ſhall ſhow by a few general Remarks and Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Had they had any ſuch ſacrifice they might have given another anſwer, to their Jewiſh and Heathen Adverſaries, who charged them with the want of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Sacrifices and Altars as with a great impiety; to which they made only this return in their Apologies, that they had indeed no proper Altars, nor viſible and external ſacrifices, but inſtead of thoſe they offered the more ſpiritual ſacrifices of Praiſe and Thanksgiving, and of an honeſt and good mind, and of vertuous and holy actions which were the only ſacrifices of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and more acceptable to God then any other: this is the anſwer which runs through all their excellent Apologies in return to that accuſation of their having no ſacrifices, which they owned to be true in the ſenſe their Adverſaries urged it; that is, that they had no proper external viſible ſacrifices, ſuch as the Jews and Heathens had, &amp; ſuch as the Roman Church will needs have the Maſs to be, but their ſacrifices were of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther nature, ſuch as were ſo only in an improper and metaphorical ſenſe which the
<hi>Romanists</hi> will by no means allow that of the Euchariſt to be. <hi>We are not Atheists,</hi> ſays <hi>Juſtin Martyr,</hi> as they were charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to be, becauſe they had not the viſible Worſhip <pb n="55" facs="tcp:96982:30"/>of facrifices, <hi>but we Worſhip the maker of all things who needs not blood, or libations, or incenſe, with the Word of Prayer and Thanksgiving, giving him Praiſe as much as we can, and counting this the only honour worthy of him</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Juſtin Martyr Apolog. 2.</note> 
               <hi>and we are perſwaded he needeth no material oblation from men</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ib.</note> And in another place he ſays, <hi>Prayers and Praiſes made by good men are the only perfect and acceptable ſacrifices to God</hi>
               <note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Dialog. cum Tryph.</note> 
               <hi>We are charged by ſome with Atheiſm,</hi> ſays <hi>Athena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goras, who meaſure Religion only by the way of ſacrifices, and what do ye tell me of ſacrifices which God wanteth not, though we ought to bring him an unbloody ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, and to offer him a rational Worſhip</hi>
               <note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Athanag. Legat. pro Chriſt.</note> where the rational worſhip explains the meaning of the unbloody ſacrifice.
<hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi> in his Apologetic anſwering that charge, <hi>That Chriſtians did not ſacrifice for the Emperours, it follows ſays he by the ſame reaſon we do not ſacrifice for others, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe neither do we do it for our ſelves</hi>
               <note n="(e)" place="margin">Pro Imperatoribus ſacriſicia non pendl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, ſequitur ut eadem ratione pro aliis non ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificemus quia nec pro nobis ipſis. <hi>Tertull. Apologet. adverſus gentes,</hi> c. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> but in anſwer to this he declares how Chriſtians prayed for the Emperour, <hi>c.</hi> 30. and in another place, he ſays, <hi>they ſacrificed for the Emperors health,</hi> that is, <hi>with a pure prayer as God has commanded</hi>
               <note n="(f)" place="margin">Sacrificamus pro ſalute Imperatoris, <hi>i. e.</hi> purâ price ſicut Dius praecepit, <hi>Idem ad Scapul.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and I offer to God,</hi> ſays he, in the ſame Apologetic ſpeaking againſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſacrifices, <hi>a rich and a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſacrifice then le commanded</hi> 
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:96982:31"/>the Jews, <hi>Prayer from a chaſt body, from an innocent ſoul proceeding from the Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi>
               <note n="(g)" place="margin">Ei offero opimam &amp; majorem hoſtiam quam ipſe man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>davit, orationem de carne pudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>câ, de animâ innocenti, de Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritu ſancto profectam. <hi>Ib. Apol. c.
30.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>This is the Host to be offered,</hi> ſays <hi>Minutius Felix, a good mind, a pure ſoul, a ſincere conſcience, theſe are our ſacrifices, theſe are the ſacred things of God,</hi> in anſwer <hi>to their not having Altars and Shrines</hi>
               <note n="(h)" place="margin">Cum ſit litabilis hostia bonus animus &amp; pura mens &amp; ſincera conſcientia— haec nostra ſacrificia, haec Dei ſacra ſunt—
<hi>Minuc. Octav.</hi>
                  <p>Sc. delubra &amp; aras non habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus. <hi>Ib.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> which objection made alſo by <hi>Celſus</hi> is af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſame manner replyed to by <hi>Origen, Our Altars are the mind of every one that is righteous from whence is truly ſent up ſweet ſmelling ſacrifices,</hi> to wit, <hi>Prayers from a pure conſcience</hi>
               <note n="(i)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Origen contra Celſum. l. 8. p. 389.</note>
               <hi>Lactantius</hi> when he propoſes to ſpeak of ſacrifice, ſhows how unſuitable any external one is to God, and that the proper ſacrifice to him, <hi>is praiſe and an hymn, bleſſing alone is his ſacrifice, we ought therefore to ſacrifice unto God by word, the chief way of worſhipping God is Thanksgiving out of the mouth of a juſt man directed to God</hi>
               <note n="(k)" place="margin">Nunc de ſacrificio ipſo pauca dicemus,— ſacrificium laus &amp; bymnus— hujus ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficium ſola benedictio, verbo ergo ſacrificari oportet Deo— ſummus igitur colendi Dei ritus est, ex ore justi hominis ad Deum directa laudatio. <hi>Lactantius de vero cultu l. 6. §. 25.</hi>
               </note> Could thoſe excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Advocates for Chriſtianity have no other ways aſſoiled the charge drawn up againſt them, that they had no ſacrifices like all other Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions, but by flying to ſuch ſpiritual and improper ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices as Praiſe and Thanksgiving? this plainly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrates that they had no proper and viſible ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, which indeed in ſo many expreſs words they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny when the word ſacrifice was under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood ſtrictly and properly<note n="(l)" place="margin">Quid ergo ſacrificia cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſetis nulla eſſe omnino ſacienda? nulla. <hi>Arnob. diſput. adverſus Gent. l. 7.</hi>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Clemens Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andrin. Strom. l. 7. p.
707.</hi> Par.</p>
               </note> Had they ſo accounted the ſacrifice of the Maſs as our Adverſaries do now, this might have been given in as the Chriſtian ſacrifice in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of all others, and yet it is ſtrange they ſcarce ever mention the Euchariſt in thoſe diſcourſes of theirs, wherein if it had <pb n="57" facs="tcp:96982:31"/>been a ſacrifice it had been moſt proper and pertinent to have ſpoke of it, and the ſacrifice of a man under the ſpecies of bread and wine had outdone all the Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh and moſt of the Heathen ſacrifices, and had been a full anſwer to the objection as it was made by them; but ſay our Adverſaries they would not ſpeak of ſo great a myſtery as the Euchariſt to unbelievers which they were uſed to conceal even to <hi>Catechumens</hi> that were not yet perfectly initiated into the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Rites; but ſurely they would not have told a downright lye, and denyed that they had any proper ſacrifices, had the Euchariſt been one, as we ſee they did, neither did they keep the ſervice of the Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt ſo ſecret as not to let the Heathens be acquainted with it, as is plain from
<hi>Juſtin Martyrs</hi> Apology, where he largely diſcourſes of its whole performance to <hi>Antoninus</hi> the Emperour<note n="(a)" place="margin">Apolog. <hi>2.</hi> verſus ſinem.</note> ; and to take off this little ſubterfuge of our Adverſaries, I ſhall adde one thing more on this head, which ſhows beyond all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute that the Primitive Church had no ſuch opinion of the Euchariſts being a ſacrifice, and that is the ſame charge of <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate who very well under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood Chriſtianity and had been a Reader of it in the Church, who notwithſtanding objected the ſame thing to the Chriſtians with the Jews and Heathens, namely <hi>that they had no Sacrifices, and that they did not erect altars to ſacrifice upon to God</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Julian apud Cyril. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexand. contra Jul. l. 10. p. 343.</note>. He knew too well the Myſteries of their Religion, ſo as not to be ignorant that the Euchariſt was a proper ſacrifice had it really been believed to be ſo by the Church at that time, and <hi>Cyril</hi>'s anſwer to him plainly ſhows that it was not, for he owns the charge, and pleads only that we have
<hi>ſpiritual and mental ſacrifices which are much better</hi>
               <note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ib. p. 345.</note> and inſtead of Sheep and Oxen, and <pb n="58" facs="tcp:96982:32"/>the like viſible ſacrifices, <hi>we offer,</hi> ſays he, <hi>for a ſweet ſavour Faith, Hope, Charity, Righteousneſs and Praiſe</hi>
               <note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ib.</note> but not a tittle of offering the ſacrifice of the Maſs which would have been greatly to the purpoſe had there been any ſuch thing, and there was no reaſon to have refuſed the mentioning it to
<hi>Julian</hi> who had once been a Chriſtian, and ſo muſt certainly have known it, had there been any ſuch thing in the Chriſtian Church.</p>
            <p n="2">2. When the Fathers do call the Euchariſt a ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, they adde ſuch Epithets and Phraſes to it as do quite ſpoil the Roman notion of it, for they call it a <hi>ſpiritual ſacrifice,</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as 'tis in <hi>Euſebi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">Demon ſtrat. Evangel. l. 5. c. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Cyril</hi> of
<hi>Hieruſalem</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">Myſtagog. Catech. 5.</note>
               <hi>Theodoret</hi>
               <note n="(c)" place="margin">Hiſtor. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig.</note> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers beſides the Greek Liturgies, and the Apoſtolick Conſtitutions, where the word <hi>ſpiritual</hi> is generally added to it. Now a ſpiritual ſacrifice they muſt own is not a proper one, for it cannot be an external and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible one, nor is there any matter or ſubſtance to be deſtroyed. So 'tis called alſo <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a <hi>reaſonable ſacrifice</hi>
               <note n="(d)" place="margin">Conſtitut. Apoſt l. 6. c. 23. Cvril Cat. my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtag. 5. Chryſoſt. Hom. 11. in Heb.</note> ſo then it cannot be an outward bodily one, which the Prieſt takes up in his hands and ſets upon the Altar, 'tis called an unbloody one, not only by the Fathers but themſelves, but if it be Chriſts bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy 'tis not without blood, and though it be unbloody in the manner of oblation, yet it could not be called ſo generally and in it ſelf. 'Tis called a myſtic and ſymbolic ſacrifice, and that is very different from a true one, <hi>Chriſt,</hi> is ſaid,
<hi>to be there ſacrificed without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſacrificed</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> diatypoſ. Concil. Niceni apud Gelaſ. Cvzic.</note>, <hi>i. e.</hi> in ſigure and repreſentation, <hi>he is offered in Image</hi> as St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> expreſly ſays<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Offertur in imagine,</hi> Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſ. de Officiis l. 1. c.
48.</note> and as it is in the book of ſacraments attributed to him, <hi>this oblation is for a figure of the body and blood of Jeſus <pb n="59" facs="tcp:96982:32"/>Chriſt</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">Quod ſit in ſigurant cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris &amp; ſanguinis Domini noſtri Jeſu Christi; <hi>de Sacram.</hi> l. <hi>4</hi> c. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> if it be a figure it cannot be the thing it ſelf, no more then a man is his own picture; 'tis called alſo a memorial and commemoration of the ſacrifice of Chriſt as St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſays, <hi>Chriſtians by the holy oblation at the Euchariſt, and by partak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the body and blood of Christ celebrate the memory of the ſame ſacrifice that was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed</hi>
               <note n="(c)" place="margin">Jam Chriſtiani peracti ejuſdem ſacriſicii memoriam cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brant ſacroſanctâ oblatione &amp; participatione corporis &amp; ſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis Chriſti. <hi>Auguſt. contra Fauſt. l. 20. c. 18.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>We offer,</hi> ſays Chryſoſtom, <hi>but 'tis by making a remembrance of Chriſts death and we offer the ſame ſacrifice or rather a remembrance of a ſacrifice</hi>
               <note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Chryſoit. in Heb. Hom. 17.</note> And <hi>Euſebius</hi> in his Demonſtrations giving an account why Chriſtians do not offer ſacrifices to God as the Jews did, ſays, <hi>Chriſt having offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed an admirable ſacrifice &amp; an excellent victim to his Father for the ſalvation of us all, hath ordered us to offer always to God a memorial inſtead of a ſacrifice</hi>
               <note n="(e)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Euſeb. Demonſtrat. Evang. l. 1. c. 10.</note> or in the place of a ſacrifice, as the word and drift of the diſcourſe clearly imply. If it be then a memorial of a ſacrifice, it cannot be the ſacrifice it ſelf, for the thing remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred muſt be diſtinct from that which is to remember it by; and if it be performing a remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of a ſacrifice rather then a ſacrifice, and the memorial of a ſacrifice <hi>in ſtead,</hi> or in the place of a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, theſe accounts of it do moſt perfectly deſtroy and are wholly inconſiſtent with that other notion of its being in it ſelf a true and proper ſacrifice.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The Novelty of private Maſſes which were brought in by making the Euchariſt a ſacrifice to God inſtead of a ſacrament to be partaken by Chriſtians, is a plain Argument of the late and novel Doctrine of the ſacrifice of the Maſs, as they are a certain conſequence
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:96982:33"/>of it, for when it began to be believed that the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt was a true ſacrifice that was beneficial and of extraordinary vertue meerly as it was offered to God without being received by themſelves, then the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple left off frequent communicating according to the Primitive cuſtom in which there is no ſuch thing to be found as is now introduced into the Church by this new Doctrine, namely, the Prieſts communicating alone without the people, and celebrating Maſs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Communion of others.
<hi>Bellarmine</hi> owns, <hi>that there is no expreſs instance to be found of this in any of the Ancients, but this he ſays may be gathered from con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectures</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Nam etiamſi nuſquam ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe legamus à veter ibus obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ſacrificium ſine communione alicujus vel aliquorum praeter ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum ſacerdotem, tamen id poſſumus ex conjecturis facilè colligere. <hi>Bellarm. de</hi> Miſſâ <hi>l. 2. c. 9.</hi>
               </note>, but how groundleſs they are, and how contrary theſe private Maſſes be to the Primitive practice, I ſhall ſhow from certain and undeniable Authorities. <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> in his account of the Chriſtian Aſſemblies, and their manner of celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Lord Supper, ſays, <hi>the Deacons give to every one of thoſe that are preſent to partake of the bleſſed Bread and Wine</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Juſtin Martyr Apolog. 2.</note>.
<hi>Ignatius</hi> who was before him ſays, <hi>one bread is broken to all, and one cup is diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to every one</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Ignat. Epiſt. ad Philadeiph.</note> ; the Apoſtolic Canons command, <hi>All the Faithful who were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at the Prayers and Reading of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, to continue alſo at the Communion, or elſe commands them to be turned out of the Church</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Canon 9.</note>. So do the Antient Canons of the Council of
<hi>Antioch Excommunicate all thoſe who come to the Church, and Prayers with their Brethren, but refuſe to communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate of the Holy Euchariſt</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Concil. Antioch. Can.
2.</note>. So great a crime was it for any not to keep to conſtant Communion, which was to be done as much by all the faithful as by the Prieſt himſelf; every Chriſtian in thoſe devout ages who was baptized, and had not notoriouſly violated <pb n="61" facs="tcp:96982:33"/>his baptiſmal Covenant, ſo as to be put into the ſtate and number of the publick penitents did always com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate as often as there was any Sacrament, which was I believe, as often as they aſſembled for publick Worſhip, and he that had not done that in thoſe firſt and pureſt times would have been thought almoſt to have been a Deſerter and to have renounced his Chriſtianity. All the
<hi>Catechumens</hi> indeed or the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didates for Chriſtianity, who were admitted to the Prayers and Sermons, but were not yet baptized, they were commanded to withdraw when the Maſs or Communion-ſervice began; and ſo were the Penitents and the <hi>Energumeni;</hi> and this is the true meaning of the word <hi>Miſſa,</hi> the Deacon in the Latin Church, crying out,
<hi>Ite Miſſa eſt,</hi> when they came to the office of the Euchariſt. In the Apoſtolick Conſtitutions<note n="†" place="margin">l. 8. c. 6,
7, 9.</note> he ſpeaks to them particularly, and diſmiſſes them in theſe words, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſo that only the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> faithful who receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Communion were allowed to be preſent at the celebration of it, which is a very good Argument againſt our Adverſaries opinion of the ſacrifice of the Maſs, for had they believ'd the Euchariſt though re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived only by the Prieſt had done good as a ſacrifice to thoſe who were preſent although they did not par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of it, as they now do in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> what need they have put out and excluded all thoſe who were Non-communicants; the Jews did not ſhut the people out of the Temple when the ſacrifice was offering. If the Euchariſt as a ſacrifice had been a part of Worſhip only to God, an oblation to him, and not a Sacrament to be received by themſelves, why might not they have been preſent at it as wellas at the Prayers which were offered to God, and at all the other parts of their Religious Worſhip? The moſt ancient ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts we have of the manner of celebrating the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt, <pb n="62" facs="tcp:96982:34"/>and the moſt ancient Liturgies or Euchariſtic forms have not the leaſt ſhadow of any private Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion by the Prieſt alone, but always ſpeak of the communion of others with him; in the Apoſtolick Conſtitutions there is a Relation in what Order all the Faithful received. <hi>First the Biſhop, then the Prieſts and Deacons, then the Deaconeſſes, and Virgins, and Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, then all the whole people in order, and after all have received then the Deacons take away the remainder.</hi> St. <hi>Cyril</hi> ſpeaks plainly of numbers receiving the Euchariſt and not of a ſingle perſon, for he mentions the Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons ſpeaking to them at firſt to embrace each other, (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,) &amp; give the kiſs of Charity: thoſe very ancient Forms and Reſponſes,
<hi>Lift up your hearts,</hi> and the anſwer, <hi>we lift them up unto the Lord</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>, <hi>Let us give thanks unto our Lord God, It is juſt and meet ſo to do,</hi> and afterwards
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, theſe all ſhow that the Prieſt did not communicate alone but had always the company of others at the Sacrament to join with him. St. <hi>Denys</hi> called the <hi>Areopagite</hi> ſpeaks <hi>of the Prieſts exhorting others at the Cummunion, and praying that they who partake of theſe Myſteries, may partake of them wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily.</hi> The ſame is in all the Lyturgies which go un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the name of St. <hi>James,</hi> St. <hi>Mark,</hi> and St. <hi>Peter,</hi> in which there are the diſtinct parts of the people, as well as of the Prieſt, as when the Prieſt is to ſay <hi>peace be with you all,</hi> the people are to anſwer, <hi>and with thy ſpirit,</hi> and the ſervice is ſo framed as to ſuppoſe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire company in Communicating, or elſe it would be nonſenſical and ridiculous for the Prieſt alone to pray to God <hi>to breathe upon us his ſervants that are preſent, to grant that the Sacraments may be to all us that partake of them, the Communion of the bleſſedneſs of eternal Life;</hi> and after the Communion is over, <hi>after all have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived,</hi> for the prieſt to give the bleſſing to all, and pray, <hi>God to bleſs and protect us all who were partakers <pb n="63" facs="tcp:96982:34"/>of the Mysteries;</hi> The ſame form of ſpeaking in the plural is in the more Authentick Liturgies of St.
<hi>Baſil,</hi> and St. <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> where it is very odd for the Prieſt to exhort others to pray, to give thanks and the like, and to pray God that <hi>they may be worthy partakers of the Sacrament,</hi> if none were to partake of it but him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. The Roman Miſſal which is much older then theſe private Maſſes, or then the Doctrine of the Maſs, as I ſhall preſently ſhow, ſpeaks after the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and makes the Prieſt pray <hi>for all that are preſent, and that all who have communicated may be filled with all heavenly benediction and Grace.</hi> Theſe muſt be all very improper for the Prieſt to ſay when he commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicates by himſelf, and he may with as good reaſon make a Congregation by himſelf alone, as make a Communion. Private Maſſes then which ſprang up from the ſacrifice of the Maſs, and are wholly ſuited and agreeable to that Doctrine, theſe being ſo contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the beſt Antiquity, ſhow that that Doctrine alſo on which they are founded, and from whence they aroſe is ſo too. And I have the more largely conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered theſe becauſe they are another great corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Euchariſt of the Roman Church, tho they are originally derived from the ſacrifice of the Maſs.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, The very Canon of the Maſs, as 'tis at preſent in the Roman Church, has very little in it agreeable to this new Doctrine of the ſacrifice of the Maſs, but though it is ſomewhat difficult to give a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain account of the time of its compoſition, it being made at firſt by an unknown Author, whom St. <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> calls <hi>Scholaſticus,</hi> who is ſuppoſed by ſome to be Pope <hi>Gelaſius,</hi> though had St.
<hi>Gregory</hi> known this he would hardly have given him that name; and it having a great many additions given to it by ſeveral Popes, as is owned by their own Writers upon the <pb n="64" facs="tcp:96982:35"/>
               <hi>Ordo Romanus</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Walaſrid. Strabo <hi>de rebus</hi> Eccleſ. c. 22. Micrologus
<hi>de Eccleſiaſt. Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vat.</hi> c. 12. Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no. Augienſis, c. 1.
<hi>&amp; alii in Collectione, Hittorpii.</hi>
               </note>, yet it is no doubt much ancienter then their preſent Doctrine of the ſacrifice of the Maſs, which is very near as late as the Council of <hi>Trent.</hi> The firſt manner of celebrating the Communion was very plain and ſimple, ſo that St.
<hi>Gregory</hi> tells us, <hi>The Apoſtles conſecrated the hoſt of oblation only with the Lords Prayer</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Mos Apoſtolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum fuit ut ad ipſam ſolammodo orationem Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicam oblationis hoſtiam conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent. <hi>Gregorii Regiſt. Epiſtol. 64. l.
7.</hi>
               </note>, if they did ſo, and uſed no other form in that ſacred Office, 'tis certain they could not make a ſacrifice of the Euchariſt nor offer it as ſuch to God, becauſe there are no words or expreſſions in that prayer, whereby any ſuch thing ſhould be meant or ſignified, ſo that this is a moſt authentick teſtimony againſt any ſuch Apoſtolick practice, but the preſent <hi>Canon Miſſae</hi> or Communion Office of the Roman Church does not fully come up to, nor perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expreſſe or contain the preſent Doctrine of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of the Maſs, there is no offering of Chriſts body and blood under the ſpecies of Bread and Wine in any formal words as might be expected in conformity to their <hi>Trent</hi> Doctrine, nor is there any mention of Chriſts being there in his natural body or offered to God by the Prieſt as a propitiatory ſacrifice for the quick and dead, for ſins, for puniſhments, and for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther neceſſities. Neither this nor their great Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation is contained in their preſent of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, ſo that 'tis to me a plain evidence of the novelty of both of them, and that they are a great deal later then the Canon of the Maſs; there are ſeveral prayers in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed that make mention of a ſacrifice and of an oblati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but moſt of them, and the moſt expreſſe of them are before conſecration, ſo that they plainly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to thoſe Gifts and Oblations, which according to the Primitive cuſtom were brought by the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cants, and which as I have ſhown were one great rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Euchariſt's being called a ſacrifice, <hi>God is deſired to accept and bleſs theſe gifts, theſe preſents, theſe <pb n="65" facs="tcp:96982:35"/>holy and pure ſacrifices which we offer to thee, for thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Catholick Church— together with thy ſervant our Pope</hi> N. <hi>and our Biſhop</hi> N.
<hi>and for all the Orthodox, and for all thoſe that hold the Catholick and Apoſtolick Faith.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Canon Miſſae.</note>, and then follows the commemoration Prayer, <hi>Remember O Lord, thy ſervants and thy handmaids,</hi> N. <hi>and</hi> N. <hi>and all thoſe who are preſent, whoſe Faith and Devotion is known to thee, for whom we offer to thee, or who offer to thee this ſacrifice of praiſe for themſelves, and for all others, for the Redemption of their Souls, for the hope of their Salvation and their ſafety, and render their vows to thee the Eternal, Living and True God,</hi> then after the memorial of the Saints,
<hi>We beſeech thee O Lord, that thou wouldst mercifully receive this Oblation of our ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and of all thy Family, and diſpoſe our days in peace, and command us to be delivered from eternal damnation, and to be numbred in the fold of thine Elect, through Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt our Lord;</hi> then immediately follows this prayer, <hi>which Oblation thou O God, we beſcech, vouchſafe to make altogether bleſſed, aſcribed, ratified, reaſonable and acceptable. Aſcripta</hi> and <hi>Rata</hi> are words which they are as much puzled to underſtand as I am to Tranſlate. All theſe prayers are before conſecration ſo that they cannot belong to the ſacrifice of Chriſts Body, but only to the oblation of the gifts, and the ſacrifice of praiſe, as 'tis there expreſly called; and yet theſe are a great deal more full and large then the prayers after conſecration, wherein there is no manner of mention of offering Chriſts Body and Blood, but only offering the conſecrated Elements as they were offered before when they were unconſecrated, <hi>We offer unto thy excellent Majeſty of thy gifts and preſents, a pure hoſt, an holy hoſt, an immaculate hoſt, the holy bread of Eternal Life, and the cup of Eternal Salvation.</hi> The firſt Compoſers would have uſed other words then Bread and Cup had they meant thereby Chriſts <pb n="66" facs="tcp:96982:36"/>very natural Body and Blood, and it is plain they were not thoſe by what follows, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon. which vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to look with a propitious and kind countenance, and to accept of them as thou didſt accept the gifts of thy righteous child</hi> Abel, <hi>and the ſacrifice of our Patriarch</hi> Abraham, <hi>and that which</hi> Melchiſedec <hi>thy High Prieſt offered to thee, an Holy Sacrifice, an immaculate Host.</hi> Now to compare Chriſts very Body and Blood with the ſacrifices of <hi>Abel, Abraham</hi> and <hi>Melchiſedec,</hi> and to deſire God to look upon his own Son, in whom he was always well pleaſed with a propitious and kind Countenance is very ſtrange and uncouth, to ſay no worſe of it; and to deſire according to what follows, <hi>that God would command theſe to be carried by the hands of his holy Angel, into thy ſublime Altar, in the preſence of thy Divine Majeſty.</hi> Theſe cannot be meant or underſtood of Chriſts natural Body and Blood, which is already in heaven, and is there <hi>to appear in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God for us,</hi> as
<hi>Menardus</hi> expreſly owns in his notes upon this prayer in
<hi>Gregories</hi> Sacramentary<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jube haec per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferri) non Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti carpus ſed memoriam paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis, ſidem, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces &amp; veta ſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam.</hi> Menardi notae &amp; obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vat. in lib. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament. Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorn Papae p. 19.</note>, and if ſo, as we have the confeſſion of the moſt Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Ritualiſt of their own Church, then there is nothing at all in the Canon of the Maſs, that does truly belong to theſe, or that does any way expreſs or come up to the new
<hi>Tridentine</hi> Doctrine of the ſacrifice of the Maſs; ſo that we need go no further then their own office to ſhow the Novelty of this, and as in other things, namely in their prayers to Saints they are forced to uſe very gentle and ſoftning interpretations to make the words ſignifie otherwiſe then what they do in their proper and literal meaning, ſo here they muſt put a more ſtrong and hard ſenſe upon them, then they will really bear or was at firſt intended to make them ſpeak the new meaning of the Maſs-ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice; ſo that they muſt here contrive a way to raiſe the ſenſe of the Church as they do in other caſes to <pb n="67" facs="tcp:96982:36"/>let it down, or elſe their Prayers and their Doctrines will never be brought to ſuit well together. The commemoration for the dead has nothing in it but a meer Remembrance and a Prayer, <hi>that God would give to them a place of refreſhment, light and peace through Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt our Lord,</hi> not through the merit or vertue of that ſacrifice which is then offered, there is not the leaſt mention or intimation of any ſuch thing nor any expreſſion that looks that way. The Prieſt indeed a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle before he communicates prays Chriſt, <hi>to deliver him from all his ſins, and from all evils by this his moſt ſacred Body and Blood,</hi> which he may do without its being a ſacrifice, and I know no Proteſtant would ſcruple the joining in ſuch a petition. There is a prayer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed deed at the laſt by the Prieſt to the Holy Trinity, <hi>that the ſacrifice which he has unworthily offered to the eyes of the Divine Majeſty may be acceptable to it, and through its mercy be propitiable for himſelf, and for thoſe for which he has offered it,</hi> and this ſeems the fulleſt and the moſt to the purpoſe of the Maſs-ſacrifice, and yet it may very fairly be underſtood in a ſound ſenſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any ſuch thing, as 'tis a ſacrifice of prayer and as God is thereby rendred merciful, and propitious both to our ſelves and others, but it is to be obſerved that this prayer is not in the old <hi>Ordo Romanus</hi> where the others are, nor in the <hi>Gelaſian</hi> or <hi>Gregorian</hi> Miſſal, nor in any other ancient one put out by
<hi>Thomaſius, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nardus, Pamelius,</hi> Cardinal <hi>Bona</hi> or
<hi>Mabillon,</hi> but was I ſuppoſe added of later days to thoſe old Forms.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, The new Addition to the form of Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the Roman Church, whereby<note n="*" place="margin">Accipe poteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem offerre ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificium Deo Miſſaſque cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brare tam pro vivis quam pro mortuis.</note> 
               <hi>power is given to the</hi> Prieſt <hi>to offer ſacrifice to God, and to celebrate Maſſes both for the dead and living,</hi> this diſcovers the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velty of their Doctrine of the ſacrifice of the Maſs; for there was no ſuch form of Ordination in the primitive
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:96982:37"/>Church, nor is there any ſuch thing mentioned in any Latin or Greek <hi>Ordinale</hi> for near a thouſand years after Chriſt; The moſt antient account of the manner of Ordaining is in the fourth Council of <hi>Carthage,</hi> where there is nothing elſe but,<note n="†" place="margin">Presbyter cum Ordinatur, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſcapo cum benedicente &amp; manum ſuper caput ejus tenente, etiam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nes Presoyteri qui praeſentes ſunt manus ſuas juxta manum Epiſcopi ſuper caput illius tenent. <hi>Canon 3. Concil. Carthag.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>the Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal Benediction and Impoſition of hands by the Biſhop and all the Priests.</hi> In the Apoſtolic Conſtitutions, there is a pretty long prayer of the Biſhops over the Prieſt who is to be Ordained,<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rut. Apoſtol. de Ordinat. Presbyt. l. 8. c. 16.</note> 
               <hi>that God would look upon his ſervant choſen into the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry by the vote and judgment of all the Clergy, and fill him with the ſpirit of Grace and Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to help and govern the people with a pure heart— that he may be ſilled with healing operations, and inſtructive diſcourſe, and may teach the people with all meekneſs, and may ſerve God ſincerely with a pure under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and a willing Soul, and may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the ſacred and pure Offices for the people through Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> And this with laying on of hands is all the Form of Ordination which is ſo anciently preſcribed; St. <hi>Denis</hi> who is falſly called the <hi>Areopagite,</hi> but was a Writer probably of the fifth Centu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry before the Council of <hi>Calcedon,</hi> he has acquainted us with much the like manner of Ordination in that time,<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Dionyſ. Hierarch. Eccleſ. c. 5.</note> 
               <hi>The Prieſt kneeling before the Altar with the Holy Bible and the Biſhops hand over his head was conſecrated with holy Prayers.</hi> Only there was then added the ſign of the croſs, and the kiſs of peace, but no ſuch thing as the receiving of power to offer ſacrifice, and to celebrate Maſſes for the living and the dead. This was a thing unheard of <pb n="69" facs="tcp:96982:37"/>in the ancient Church either Greek or Latin, neither was it brought into the Latin till about the year 1000 as is confeſt by <hi>Morinus</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">de ſacris Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinat. pars <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note>, nor is it to this day uſed in the Greek. In that age of Ignorance and Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition when Tranſubſtantiation and a great many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Errors and Corruptions crept into the Latin Church, this new Form of Ordination was ſet up, and the Prieſts had a new power given them, and a new work put upon them, which was to ſacrifice and ſay Maſſes for the quick and dead, which had it been agreeable to the Doctrine of the Primitive Church, and had there been any ſuch opinion then of the Maſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacrifice as there is now in the Roman Church, there would no doubt have been the ſame forme of Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, or ſomething like this would have been ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in the conſecration of a prieſt. They now make this the great and proper office of the prieſt, and theſe words with the delivery of the holy Veſſels or ſacred Inſtruments is made the very matter and form of the Sacrament of Orders, and if is made a charge by them againſt our Ordinations, that we want this eſſential part of prieſthood, which is to offer ſacrifice, but ſince the primitive Church had no ſuch Form as is fully made out by
<hi>Morinus,</hi> a man of great Learning and Credit among themſelves who has made a great collection of the moſt antient <hi>Ordinale</hi>'s to ſhow this, and there is no ſuch thing now in the Greek Churches as appears from
<hi>Habertus</hi> on the <hi>Greek Pontifical,</hi> we have hereby not only a full defence of our own Orders without any ſuch Form, but a plain demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the novelty of that in the Roman Church, and conſequently of that Doctrine which is brought in by it, or perhaps was the occaſion, of it, of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſice of the Maſs. <pb n="70" facs="tcp:96982:38"/>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. It is in it ſelf unreaſonable and abſurd, and has a great many groſs Errors involved in it. As</p>
            <p n="1">1. It makes an external viſible ſacrifice of a thing that is perfectly inviſible, ſo that the very matter and ſubſtance of the ſacrifice which they pretend to offer is not ſeen or perceived by any of the ſenſes, for 'tis Chriſts body, and not the Bread and Wine which is the ſubject-matter and the ſacrifice it ſelf. Now this is the ſtrangeſt ſacrifice that ever was in the World, a viſible oblation of an inviſible thing; had the Jews offered their ſacrifices in this manner, they had offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed nothing at all, and had Chriſt thus offered himſelf to God upon the croſs only in phantaſm and appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance as ſome Hereticks would have had him, and not in the viſible ſubſtance of his body, it would have been only a phantaſtick ſacrifice, and we had been redeemed by a ſhadow. 'Tis contrary to the nature of all proper ſacrifices to have the thing offered not to be ſeen, and not viſibly preſented to God; an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible ſacrifice may as well have an inviſible Altar, and an inviſible Oblation, and an inviſible Prieſt, for why the one ſhould be more viſible then the other, I cannot imagine. <hi>Bellarmines</hi> definition of a ſacrifice is this, which we are very willing to allow of, but how it agrees to the ſacrifice of the maſs I cannot ſee;<note n="*" place="margin">Sacrificium eſt oblatio externa facta ſoli Deo, quâ ad agniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem humanae in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitatis &amp; profeſſionem di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinae Majeſtatis à legitimo Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſho res aliqua ſinſibilis &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manens ritu my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlieo conſecratur &amp; tranſmuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. <hi>Bellarm. de Miſſ. l. 1. c. 2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>A ſacrifice is an external Oblation made to God alone, whereby for the acknowledging of humane infirmity, and owning of the Divine Majeſty, ſome ſenſible and perma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent thing is by a lawful Miniſter, and by a Miſtic Rite conſecrated and changed.</hi> Now Chriſts Body and Blood being the <hi>res ſacrificii,</hi> the matter of the ſacrifice, and that being offered to God, I cannot underſtand how that is a
<hi>res ſenſipilis,</hi> a ſenſible thing in the Euchariſt, and therefore how according to him it is a ſacrifice; ſo neceſſary is it for a great man to blunder in a bad <pb n="71" facs="tcp:96982:38"/>cauſe when he muſt either weigh in a falſe ballance, or whatever he ſays will quickly be found light.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It makes a proper ſacrifice without a proper facrificing Act, the Conſumption and Deſtruction of the ſacrifice was always neceſſary, as well as the offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and bringing it to the Altar, and without this it was not properly given to God, but kept to themſelves as much as it was before, if it were not either poured out, or burnt, or ſlain, which was parting with the thing and transferring it wholly to God; &amp; this conſumption is ſo Eſſential to all ſacrifices that
<hi>Bellarmine</hi> puts it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the definition of a ſacrifice<note n="*" place="margin">ut ſupra.</note>, and ſays,<note n="†" place="margin">ad verum ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificium requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritur ut id quod offertur Deo in ſacrificium planè deſtruatur. <hi>Id. de Miſſ. l. 1 c. 2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>that to a true ſacrifice it is required that that which is offered to God in ſacrifice be plainly destroyed.</hi> But how will this now belong to Chriſts body in the ſacrifice of the Maſs? Is that deſtroyed there? is not that the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice? and is not that now in a Glorious, impaſſible State that can ſuffer no deſtruction? <hi>Bellarmine</hi> is in a ſad plunge to get out here, and let us ſee how he throws himſelf about, but ſticks faſt ſtill in the mire. <hi>By conſecration,</hi> ſays he,
<hi>the thing which is offered is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained to a true real and outward change and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, which was neceſſary to the being of a ſacrifice, for by conſecration the Body of Christ receives the Form of food, but food is for eating, and by this it is ordained for change and deſtruction;</hi> Is the Body of Chriſt then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed by eating? If it be they are true Cannibals or Capernaitical feeders that eat it: I had thought that Chriſts body was not thus groſly to be broke by the Teeth, or chewed by the jaws of the prieſt, or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municants, ſo as to be deſtroyed by them. The Gloſs upon
<hi>Berengarius</hi> his Recantation ſays this is a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Hereſie then his, unleſs it be underſtood of the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and not of the body it ſelf; and they generally diſown that Chriſts body is thus carnally eaten, but only the Sacramental ſpecies, but the ſpecies are not
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:96982:39"/>the ſacrifice, and therefore 'tis not ſufficient that they be deſtroyed, but the ſacrifice, that is the body of Chriſt muſt be ſo. Chriſts body as it is food is not a ſacrifice but a Sacrament, they make two diſtinct things of it as it is a ſacrifice, and as it is a Sacrament, as it lies in the Pix, or is carried to the ſick it is food and a Sacrament but they will not allow it to be then a ſacrifice, and on Maunday Thurſday, it is eaten but not accounted a ſacrifice<note n="†" place="margin">Feriâ ſextâ majoris hebdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madae nou cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſetur ſacriſicium Miſſae propriè celebrari licet vera hoſtia adſit &amp; frangatur &amp; conſumatur. <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larm. de Miſſ. l. 1. c. 27. B.</hi>
               </note>. The Conſumption then by eating belongs to it not as a ſacrifice but a Sacrament, and the body of Chriſt is not then conſumed but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the ſpecies, nay the body of Chriſt is not then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed under the ſpecies, for the real conſumption be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs only to the ſpecies, for the real conſumption be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs only to the ſpecies and not to the body of Chriſt, which is no more truly conſumed with them, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them, then it is as ſitting in heaven, no more then a mans fleſh is conſumed when only his clothes or his mantle is tore tho he were in them.
<hi>What though it ceaſes to be really on the Altar, and ceaſes to be a ſenſible food,</hi> as he farther explains, or rather intangles it; Is Chriſts body ever a ſenſible food? And is its ceaſing to be upon the Altar, a conſumption of it? Then <hi>Iſaac</hi> was conſumed when he was took off from the Altar on which <hi>Abraham</hi> had laid him, and if his Father had been as ſubtle as our Roman Sophiſters and Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, he might only have covered him with the skin of the Ram, and have conſumed that as an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal ſpecies by fire, and ſo <hi>Iſaac</hi> had been both ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificed, and conſumed, and deſtroyed too, and yet have been as live as ever for all this. Such abſurdities do they run into when they will make their notion ſuit of a true ſacrifice and that which is not one, and a man of ſenſe muſt yet deſtroy his ſenſe one would think before he can talk at this rate. <pb n="73" facs="tcp:96982:39"/>
            </p>
            <p>They are moſt ſadly nonpluſt and moſt extremely divided among themſelves about the Eſſence of this their ſacrifice of the Maſs, and wherein they ſhould place the true ſacrificial act, whether in the Oblation of the Elements, or in conſecration of them whereby they ſuppoſe them turned into Chriſts Body and blood, and ſo in the expreſs Oblation of thoſe to God, or in the fraction and commiſtion of the conſecrated Elements, or in the manducation and conſumption of them:
<hi>Suarez</hi> and <hi>Vaſquez</hi> and others are for the laſt of all; the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> ſeems to be for Oblation; <hi>Bellarmine</hi> is for conſecration, whereby inſtead of Bread and Wine Chriſts Body and Blood are placed upon the Altar, and ordered for conſumption. <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chior Canus</hi> is for all the four laſt, and he tells us it is the Doctrine of
<hi>Thomas Aquinas,</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">docuiſſe
<hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam</hi> ſacrificium ante fractionem hoſtiae eſſe perac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, ſumptio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemque ſpectare propriè ad ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum, oblati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem verò ad ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificium. <hi>Can. Loc. Theol. l. 12. p. 833.</hi>
               </note> that the <hi>ſacrifice is performed before the fraction of the Elements, and that the ſumption of them belongs properly to the Sacrament, the Oblation to the ſacrifice;</hi> ſo that they know not what to pitch upon to conſtitute it a ſacrifice, and if we exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine them all we ſhall find no true proper ſacrificial act in any of them; the Oblation of the Elements be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore conſecration can by no means make ſuch a ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice as they deſign, for that is but an offering of earthly things not of Chriſts body, neither are they thereby changed or conſumed, and tho they are an offering, they are not a proper ſacrifice, though in ſome ſenſe they are a ſacrifice and were accounted ſo by the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as I have ſhown. The Fraction of the Elements after they are conſecrated which is done by the Prieſt, not for diſtribution, for they give them whole to the people, but for another myſtical reaſon, this is not the formal Eſſence of the ſacrifice, for Chriſt they own did not break them in this manner at his laſt Supper, when yet they will have him ſacrifice, and this is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times omitted by themſelves; neither is manducation,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:96982:40"/>for this is performed by the people as well as the prieſt when they communicate, and ſacrificing does not then belong to them, nor is it ever their work but only the Prieſts, and yet they then eat and conſume the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as well as the prieſt, ſo that ſacrificing cannot properly lye in this, neither can it be proved that Chriſt did himſelf eat when he is ſuppoſed to ſacrifice; and beſides both this fraction and manducation belongs only to the ſpecies, they are the only proper ſubject of thoſe actions, but it is the Body and Blood of Chriſt that is ſacrificed and not the ſpecies. For this reaſon therefore conſecration it ſelf cannot well paſs for the formal act of ſacrificing, for 'tis the Bread is conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted not Chriſts body: 'tis the bread only is changed by conſecration, that is ſuppoſed indeed to be deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed when it is conſecrated, and if this be ſacrificing it is ſacrificing of nothing, or at moſt 'tis but ſacrificing of bread which is a meaner ſacrifice then many of the Jewiſh, neither is this change of it viſible and external, but they will needs have the ſacrificing action to be ſenſible and external or elſe the ſacrifice will not be ſo, and if it be only a ſpiritual and internal and men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal offering up of Chriſts body and blood to God this is not proper ſacrificing of it again, but only by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Faith and Devotion which we are very willing to allow. But conſecration muſt ſet Chriſts body up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Altar and put it into the hands of the prieſt and then it muſt be viſibly offered to God, and viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly conſumed, and this is the true way of ſacrificing it, for <hi>Bellarmine</hi> takes in conſumption as neceſſary to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with conſecration, the oblation he owns is not verbal, neither did Chriſt thus offer his Body and Blood at his laſt Supper but after he had bleſſed and brake the bread he gave it to his Diſciples, but placing this upon the Altar by the words of conſecration is a real Oblation of it, and then eating and conſuming it <pb n="75" facs="tcp:96982:40"/>there formally conſtitutes the ſacrifice. The Biſhop of <hi>Meaux</hi> in his Expoſition ſeems to make the whole Eſſence of the ſacrifice conſiſt in Conſecration alone without any manducation or deſtruction, which <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> makes abſolutely neceſſary; <hi>Chriſt,</hi> he ſays, <hi>is placed upon the holy Table, clothed with thoſe ſigns that repreſent his death in vertue of the words of conſecration which are the ſpiritual ſword that make a mystical ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration betwixt the Body and the Blood.</hi> Now if Chriſt be thus only ſacrificed myſtically and by repreſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he is not ſacrificed truly and properly, nor is there any true and proper propitiation made hereby, which is the true ſtate of the Controverſie between us; Chriſt may be ſacrificed repreſentatively, as
<hi>Caeſar</hi> may be ſlain in a Tragedy, without being really preſent, and if he were preſent and placed upon the Altar, as they will needs have him, yet he is no more ſacrificed by the myſtical repreſentation then if
<hi>Caeſars</hi> Picture were ſtab'd and he were behind it unhurt. I ſee no reaſon why Chriſts preſence ſhould be neceſſary to make ſuch a myſtical repreſentative, or commemora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive ſacrifice, and if Chriſt were preſent I ſee not how he is more ſacrificed then if he were abſent. So that they only confound their thoughts to make a proper ſacrifice where there is none, and when they have boaſted of a true proper viſible external ſacrifice, they know not where to find any ſuch thing, and it comes to no more at laſt then a meer commemorative and repreſentative one, or in plain words to a ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental and Myſtical repreſentation and remembrance of a paſt ſacrifice, which there is neither any need nor any poſſibility of renewing.</p>
            <p>Their differences about the proper ſacrificial act whereby they do with good ſucceſs deſtroy one anothers notions of it, and ſo taken together deſtroy the thing it ſelf, theſe are the more conſiderable be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <pb n="76" facs="tcp:96982:41"/>'tis not the <hi>res ſacrificii</hi> which makes the ſacrifice, though that were never ſo truly preſent, but the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficing Act, or the Actual ſacrificing it, for as <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> ſays,<note n="*" place="margin">Nam non res illa, ſedgei illi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us oblatio proprie eſt ſacrificium, ſacrificium enim eſt actio non res permanens.
<hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larm. de Miſſ. l. 2. c. 4. D.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>A ſacrifice is an action not a permanent thing, and 'tis not the thing it ſelf, but the offering it is properly the ſacrifice.</hi> So that though Chriſts natural Body and Blood were never ſo much preſent in the Euchariſt even according to the Doctrine of Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation it ſelf; yet ſo long as there is no proper acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on there to ſacrifice it, or no ſacrificing act, it would ſignifie nothing to the making it a ſacrifice.</p>
            <p n="3">3. This Doctrine of the Maſs makes a living body a ſacrifice which requires it ſhould be dead, and yet at the ſame repreſents it dead when it ſuppoſes it preſent in a ſtate of life, which is as odd a jumble as making a man to be by at his own funeral, and at the ſame time bringing in the perſon alive, &amp; yet dreſſing up his picture to remember him dead and in the habit of death it ſelf. The Euchariſt is to remember and repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Chriſt in a ſtate of death, his body and blood as ſeparated from one another, and the one broken and the other poured out, and the words of conſecration <hi>are the ſpiritual ſword,</hi> as the Biſhop of <hi>Meaux</hi> calls them, that are to do this, and ſo to conſtitute the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, but whilſt this is a doing, nay by the very doing this thing, the ſame ſpiritual ſword becomes a ſpiritual word, and raiſes the ſame body living, and ſets it in that ſtate upon the Altar, ſo that by this means it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroys the ſacrifice a great deal more then it made it before, for it makes it be then truly living, whereas it only repreſented it before as dead. So that 'tis at the ſame time a dead repreſentative ſacrifice, and a living proper ſacrifice, which is in truth no ſacrifice at all, for a living ſacrifice is juſt as much ſenſe as a dead Ammal, that is, 'tis a contradiction, and one of the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:96982:41"/>Terms deſtroys the other. If a Jewiſh Prieſt had knockt down the Oxe with one hand, and raiſed him up with the other, or reſtored him to life after he had ſlew him, this would have made but a very odde ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice; and to make Chriſt dead <hi>by</hi> the ſacramental ſigns, and to ſacrifice him thus in <hi>Effigie,</hi> and to make him alive again <hi>under</hi> the ſacramental ſigns, and ſo to ſacrifice him truly this is a ſtrange and unaccountable riddle. I would ask whether the conſecrated ſpecies of Bread and Wine by <hi>which Chriſts blood is ſhed myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally, and death intervenes only by repreſentation,</hi> as the Biſhop of <hi>Meaux</hi> phraſes it, whether theſe would make a real ſacrifice without Chriſts living body under them? if not, 'tis not this myſtical repreſentation of death makes the ſacrifice? Or whether Chriſts liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing body without thoſe ſpecies and ſigns of his death would be a ſacrifice? If not then 'tis not the placing that upon the Altar and ſo a real Oblation of it there makes the ſacrifice, and then what is it that does ſo? Is it not very odd that the ſame perſon muſt be there ſeemingly dead, and yet really alive at the ſame time to make up this ſacrifice?</p>
            <p n="4">4. The making it truly propitiatory is a very great Error, and inconſiſtent with it ſelf. All our Religious Duties and all our vertuous actions may in a large and improper ſenſe be ſaid to be propitiatory, as they are ſaid alſo in Scripture to be ſacrifices, for no doubt but they make God kind and propitious to us, and incline him to have Mercy upon us; and the bleſſed Euchariſt as it exhibits to us all the graces and benefits which Chriſt hath by his death purchaſed for us, whereof Pardon and Remiſſion of ſin which is hereby ſealed to us, is a very great one, ſo far may be called propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiatory, and it may be inſtituted for the Remiſſion of ſin, ſo far as it is to apply to us the vertue of Chriſts <pb n="78" facs="tcp:96982:42"/>body and blood and make us partakers of his ſacrifice upon the Croſs, but this it may do as it is a Sacrament without being any ſacrifice, much leſs without being a propitiatory one as the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> hath deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined it, to be
<hi>truly propitiatory</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">Vere propitiatorium eſſe, Injus quippe oblatione placatus Dominus. <hi>Concil. Trident. Seſſ. 6. c. 2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>by the oblation of which God is appeaſed,</hi> and this in oppoſition to a ſacrifice of Praiſe and Thankſgiving<note n="(c)" place="margin">Si quis dixoit Miſſae ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſicium tantum eſſe laudis &amp; gratiarum actionis— non autem propitiatorium, <hi>Ib. Can. 3.</hi>
               </note> Now as it is a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of Praiſe and ſpiritual Devotion, it is no doubt, in the Biſhop of
<hi>Meaux</hi>'s words, <hi>acceptable to God and makes him look upon us with a more propitious eye</hi>
               <note n="(d)" place="margin">Expoſition of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Cathotick Charch, <hi>p. 35.</hi>
               </note> Is this then all the meaning of its being propitiatory? Did ever any Proteſtant deny it to be thus? And is not this to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain away the true meaning of the word, and to give up the Controverſie? The true notion of a propitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory ſacrifice is this, that it ſuffers a vicarious puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in anothersſtead, that by it the puniſhment is tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd from the offender to that, and ſo he is diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from it, and God is pleaſed for the ſake of that not to be angry but kind and propitious to him; this I think cannot be denyed, and let us ſee if this will fit to the Euchariſt; If Chriſt be really preſent there, yet does he ſaffer any puniſhment there in our ſtead? does he pay any price there for our ſins? If not, there can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be any true propitiation then made, nor can the ſacrifice be truly propitiatory; Chriſt did once upon the Croſs, where he ſuffered as our <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a vica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious puniſhment for our ſins <hi>by his one oblation of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf once offered make a full, perfect, and ſufficient ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice for the ſins of the whole World</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Prav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at. in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mun. Serv.</note>, and <hi>Bellarmine</hi> is forced to own, <hi>That 'tis the ſacrifice of the Croſs, is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly meritorious and ſatisfactory, becauſe Chriſt when he was then mortal could merit and ſatisfie, but the ſacrifice of the Maſs is properly only impetratory, for Chriſt being <pb n="79" facs="tcp:96982:42"/>now immortal can neither merit nor ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Nam ſacrificium crucis fait meritorium, ſatisfactorium &amp; impetratorium verè &amp; propriè, quia Christus tunc mortalis erat &amp; mereri ac ſatisfacere poterat, ſacrificium Miſſae propriè ſalum est Impetratorium quia Chriſius nunc immortalis nec mereri nec ſatisfacere poteſt. <hi>Bellarm. de Miſſa l. 2. c. 4. C.</hi>
               </note>. Thus truth will out at laſt, though there be never ſo much art uſed to ſtifle and conceal it, and this is very fairly to give up the queſtion, and ſurrender the cauſe; for he owns it is not properly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiatory and gives a very good reaſon for it, becauſe Chriſt in his immortal ſtate cannot merit or ſatisfie or be a true propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation for us; the Biſhop of <hi>Meaux</hi> was aware of this and therefore he makes Chriſts preſence upon the Altar to be not a propitiation, but <hi>a powerful Interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion before God for all mankind, according to the ſaying of the Apoſtle that Jeſus Chriſt preſents himſelf, and appears for us before the face of God,</hi> Heb. 9.24. <hi>So that Chriſt being preſent upon the holy Table under this figure of death, intercedes for us, and repreſents continually to his Father that death which he has ſuffered for his Church</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Expoſition of the Doctrine of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church.</note>. But how comes this Interceſſion of Chriſt to be upon Earth? Is it not to be in heaven, and is not Chriſt there to appear in the preſence of God for us? Is not Chriſt entered into the heavens for that purpoſe as the High Prieſt went into the Holy of Holies with the blood of the great ſacrifice of Atonement after that was offered upon the Altar? Does not the Apoſtle thus repreſent it in that place in alluſion, and with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to that Jewiſh Oeconomy, and could any but Monſieur <hi>de Meaux</hi> have brought that place to ſhow that Chriſt intercedes for us by being preſent upon the Altar, when the Apoſtles diſcourſe is as directly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to that as can be, and makes him to appear only in Heaven, or in the preſence of God for us, and there preſent himſelf and his ſacrifice to God, as the Jewiſh High Prieſt carried the blood of the Anniver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary ſacrifice of Expiation into the Holy of Holies, and there ſprinkled it before the Mercy-ſeat.
<hi>Chriſt is not <pb n="80" facs="tcp:96982:43"/>entred into the holy place made with hands which are the figures of the true, but into Heaven it ſelf, now to appear in the preſence of God for us.</hi> Chriſt therefore making Interceſſion for us only in heaven and propitiation on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon the Croſs, how the ſacrifice of the Maſs ſhould be either Interceſſory, which is a new way of <hi>de Meaux</hi>'s or propitiatory as the Council of
<hi>Trent</hi> has determined it, I cannot underſtand. Some of them tell us it is propitiatory only relatively, and by appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation as it relates and applyes to us the propitiatory vertue of the ſacrifice of the Croſs, but this it may do as a Sacrament, and then it is not propitiatory in it ſelf,
<hi>for ſins, for puniſhments, and for ſatisfactions,</hi> as the Council declares it, and as propitiatory ſacrifices uſed to be, which were in themſelves <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſatisfactory payments and prices for ſins, and for the puniſhments due to them. <hi>Bellarmin</hi> having owned it not to be properly propitiatory, he ſays,<note n="*" place="margin">Cum autem dicitur propitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torium vel ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factorium id eſt intelligendum ratione rei quae impetratur, dici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur enim propiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atorium quia impetrat remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem culpae, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactorium quia impetrat remiſſionem poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae. <hi>Bellarm. de Miſſ. l. 2. c. 4. C.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>When it is called pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiatory or ſatisfactory, this is to be understood by reaſon of the thing which is impetrated by it, for it is ſaid to be Propitiatory, becauſe it impetrates Remiſſion of ſin; Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactory becauſe it impetrates Remiſſion of puniſhment:</hi> But thus our Prayers may be ſaid to be propitiatory becauſe by them we beg and obtain Mercy and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don at the hands of God, but a propitiatory ſacrifice is to do this not only by way of petition and impetrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on but by way of price, and payment, and ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; ſo that after all this improper ſacrifice of the Maſs is but very improperly propitiatory, and when they come cloſely to conſider it they are forced to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs ſo, and cannot tell how to make out their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils Doctrine, that 'tis truly propitiatory for ſins and for puniſhments.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Let us conſider next how it is impetratory, if they mean only that it is ſo upon the account of thoſe <pb n="81" facs="tcp:96982:43"/>Prayers which are there made, and which are more efficacious in that ſolemn office of Religion, as the Euchariſt has relation to the Croſs, and the ſacrifice of Chriſt upon it, which is the foundation of all our Prayers, and by vertue of which we hope to have them heard and anſwered by God, ſo in that ſolemn, Religious and expreſs memorial of it, we may ſuppoſe them to have a greater vertue and efficacy; if this be all they mean who will deny it, and why may not this be without the Euchariſt's being a ſacrifice, 'tis only Chriſts ſacrifice and offering upon the Croſs that gives vertue and power to our prayers at that time when we are devoutly celebrating the remembrance of it, and 'tis not any offering of him up then any other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then by Faith and the inward devotion of our Mind that makes our prayers the more powerful either for our ſelves or others.</p>
            <p>We are to make Prayers and Supplications for all men, and for theirs and our own wants and neceſſities in this ſolemn and publick office of our Religion, and ſo did the firſt Chriſtians pray then for Kings and all that were in Authority as the Apoſtle commands, and as we find they did at large in St. <hi>Cyril</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Catech. My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtag. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note>, and the Apoſtolick Conſtitutions<note n="†" place="margin">l. <hi>8.</hi> c. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note>, and it was in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they uſed their Litanies or general Supplications for all men, and for all things; as is evident beyond all diſpute from thoſe places where they prayed not only for <hi>the Church and the Biſhops, Presbyters, and Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, and all the faithful, but for the King or the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror where they lived, for the City and all its inhabitants, for the ſick, for the Captives and baniſhed, for all that Travelled by Sea or by Land,</hi> and ſo for all things <hi>for the peace of the Church and for the quiet of the Empire, and for all temporal mercies, as well as ſpiritual, for the fruits of the Earth, and for the temperature of the Air,</hi> and for all things they ſtood in need of. Now they <pb n="82" facs="tcp:96982:44"/>did not think the Euchariſt did as a ſacrifice impetrate all this, or as a real inſtead of a verbal prayer as
<hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> repreſents it to be<note n="*" place="margin">Ipſa enim ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latio tacita quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam ſed officaciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſima eſt invoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio.
<hi>Bellarm. de Miſſ. l. 2. c. 8. B.</hi>
               </note> ; but they made particular and expreſs prayers for theſe in the Euchariſt, and did not think that was to ſupply the place of prayer or be a prayer in action, or in dumb ſigns inſtead of words, neither did the primitive Church ever ſay a Maſs for to quench a fire or ſtay an Earthquake, much leſs to cure the Murrain in Cattle, or to recover a Sheep, or a Cow, or Horſe when they were ſick, as is ſcandalouſly and ſhamefully done by thoſe who aſcribe ſuch an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petratory power to it that it ſhall do the work in all caſes.</p>
            <p n="6">6. To make it a ſacrifice truly propitiatory in its ſelf and yet only applicatory of the vertue of another ſacrifice is if not a contradiction, yet a great abſurdity, for if it only apply the vertue and efficacy of another ſacrifice, <hi>viz. That</hi> of the Croſs, which is the only ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of Redemption that made true expiation for ſin, how can this then be called truly propitiatory, if only <hi>that other</hi> be propitiatory and this is but applicatory of that other? A certain
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or infallible medicine for all Diſeaſes is given and applyed to us by ſuch a vehicle, is the vehicle therefore that applies this the Medicine it ſelf? Or has that an infallible vertue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Medicine that is applyed by it has ſuch a vertue? Is laying on a Plaiſter or applying it to the wound the ſame thing with the Plaiſter it ſelf that was made up or compounded long before? If the Maſs-ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice be truly propitiatory it muſt be a ſacrifice of Redemption, if it be only Applicatory, and not a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of Redemption in it ſelf then 'tis not truly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiatory. The Euchariſt we all ſay doth apply to us the ſacrifice of the Croſs, or the benefits of Chriſts death as it is a Sacrament, but it is not therefore pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiatory <pb n="83" facs="tcp:96982:44"/>as it is ſuch, nor is it any way neceſſary it ſhould, and as a ſacrifice it cannot be applicatory, for it muſt be offered to God, and therefore as ſuch it could not apply any thing to us, for our giving it up or ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificing it to God is quite another thing and very different from Gods giving or applying it to us. God gives Chriſts body and blood to us in the Euchariſt as it is a Sacrament, but as it is a ſacrifice we muſt give it to him, and that would be as ſtrange a way of applying it to our ſelves, as a Patients returning his Phyſick or making a preſent of it to the Doctor, would be a new and ſtrange method of taking it himſelf. And that the Prieſts intention ſhould apply this is ſtill as ſtrange, for the Prieſts intention in the Maſs is to conſecrate and ſo to ſacrifice, and that is giving the thing to God and not applying it to others; if he gives them the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament indeed to eat then he applyes the ſacrifice of Chriſts body and blood to them; but how he can do this when he does not give it them but only give it to God, that is, ſacrifice it, I do not underſtand: The Jews had the vertue of their ſacrifices applyed to them by eating of them, or by having the blood ſprinkled upon them or by ſome ſuch Ceremony to make them partakers of them, but that another ſacrifice was offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red or the ſame ſacrifice reiterated in order to apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them is a thing unknown and unheard of Chriſts ſacrifice is applyed to us by the ſacrament of Baptiſm and therefore that alſo is called a ſacrifice as it both re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents Chriſts death, and confers to us the benefits of it, thus
<hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> expounds that place of Scripture <hi>there remains</hi> no more ſacrifice <hi>for ſin</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Heb.
10.26.</note>, that is, <hi>he can be no more baptized</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Chryſoſtom. Homil. 16. in Epiſt. ad Hebr.</note>, and Biſhop <hi>Canus</hi> ſays,<note n="*" place="margin">hinc illi (an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiqui) baptiſma tranſlatitiè bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiam nuncupâ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt. <hi>Can. loci commun. l. 2. c. 12.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients from hence called Baptiſm. a ſacrifice,</hi> but figura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, and not properly, and juſt thus indeed they called the Euchariſt: <hi>Bellarmine</hi> was ſo ſenſible that this would deſtroy the notion of the Euchariſts being a <pb n="84" facs="tcp:96982:45"/>proper ſacrifice, that he abſolutely denies that<note n="*" place="margin">Nuſquam Patres baptiſmum vocant ſacrificium, hoſtiam— <hi>Bellarm. de Miſſ. l. 1. c. 15.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>the Fathers do ever call baptiſm a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice,</hi> but he is ſhamefully miſtaken, as appears from the confeſſion of Biſhop <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> and becauſe I will not wholly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon that I will produce one or two plain Authorities for it out of St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Holocaustum Dominicae paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionis to tempore pro ſe quiſque offert, quo ejuſdem Paſſionis ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de dedicatur. <hi>Auguſt. in Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſit. ad Roman.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Every one,</hi> ſays he, <hi>does offer for himſelf the ſacrifice of Chriſts paſſion, at that time when he is dedicated in the Faith of his paſſion. And the ſacrifice of our Lord is in a certain manner offered for every one then when in his name he is ſigned by Baptiſm</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Holocauſtum Domini tunc pro unoquoque offertur quodam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modò cum ejus nomine baptizan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do ſignatur.
<hi>Ib.</hi>
               </note>. Baptiſm is then called a ſacrifice as well as the Euchariſt, though it is only properly a Sacrament, and the ſacrifice of Chriſt is there plainly applyed to us without a ſacrifice, and ſo it may be as well in the Euchariſt.</p>
            <p n="7">7. They ſuppoſe it to be the ſame ſacrifice with that of the Croſs, but not to have the ſame vertue and efficiency,
<hi>which</hi> as <hi>Bellarmin</hi> ſays, <hi>ſeems very ſtrange</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">mirum videtur cur valor ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficii bujus ſit fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitus, cum idem ſit hoc ſacrifici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um cum ſacrificio crucis. <hi>Bellarm. de Miſſ. l. 2. c. 4. F.</hi>
               </note>, for the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> declares <hi>it to be one and the ſame ſacrifice with that of the Croſs, and one and the ſame offerer</hi> namely Chriſt by the Miniſtery of the Prieſts, and <hi>to be differing in nothing but in the manner of offering</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>na enim ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demque eſt hoſtia idemque offerens ſacerdotum mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterio— ſola offerendi ratione diversâ. <hi>Concil. Trid. Seſſ. 6. c.
2.</hi>
               </note>. Now if the manner of offering be not ſuch as makes it a ſacrifice, it can be no ſacrifice at all, if it be, it can make no difference as to its value and efficacy, for 'tis not the way of offering but the worth of the thing offered that gives value to the ſacrifice. The Beaſts were ſlain upon an Altar and had their blood ſpilt there as Chriſts was upon the Croſs, but his being the blood of a perſon of the greateſt dignity even of the Son of God, this made his ſacrifice once offered to be of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite value and efficacy, and ſufficient to propitiate God and make expiation for all the ſins of the World, now if the ſame ſacrifice be as truly offered in the Maſs <pb n="85" facs="tcp:96982:45"/>though not after the ſame manner, and Chriſt does by the hands of the Prieſt as truly offer himſelf there as he did upon the Croſs, why ſhould not this be of as infinite value and efficiency as the other, but if it were ſays
<hi>Bellarmine, what need ſo many Maſſes be offered for the ſame thing</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Nam ſi Miſſae valor infinitus eſſet, frustrà multae Miſſae praeſertim ad rem eandem impetran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam offerrentur. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </note>, ſo many thouſand for example to get a ſoul out of Purgatory, which if it were not, it would quite ſpoil the market and utterly deſtroy the Trade of them; but ſurely this is but like paying the ſame full ſumme of a debt ſo many times over, when one pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment amounts to the whole, and 'tis but the ſame is brought ſo many times again; It is to be feared that it is not accepted by God or elſe it need not be ſo often tendered, and paid again and again ſo many ſeveral times, but as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſays, <hi>both the ſacrifice it ſelf, and Chriſt who then offers it are infinitely acceptable to God</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Ipſa hoſtia &amp; offerens Chriſtus infinito modo ſunt Deo grata. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </note>. What account then can be given of this? He is the moſt miſerably put to't that ever good gueſſer was at this unaccountable thing, and <hi>with a ſalvo to better judgment</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Videntur mihi, ſalvo meliore ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicio, tres eſſe cauſae hujus rei. <hi>Bellarm. de Miſſ. l. 2. c. 4. F.</hi>
               </note>, which is a ſqueamiſh piece of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty that he is ſeldom guilty of at other times, he of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers at three reaſons, though he owns the cauſe of it is not certain<note n="†" place="margin">Cauſa non eſt adeo certa. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </note>. The firſt is, <hi>in reſpect of the ſacrifice it ſelf which is offered, in the ſacrifice of the croſs,</hi> ſays he, <hi>Chriſt in his very natural being, and human form was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, but 'tis only his ſacramental being is ſo in the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Prima ſumitur ex parte hoſtiae quae offertur, nam in ſacrificio de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struebatur ad honorem Dei ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum eſſe naturale Chriſti in formâ humanâ, in ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificio Miſſae deſtruitur tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſſe ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentale. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </note>, but Chriſt I hope is as much in his natural being in the Euchariſt as he was upon the croſs, elſe what becomes of the Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation; and he is offered as truly to God in his natural being there, why ſhould not then his natural being be as valuable in the one as in the other, if his natural be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings not being deſtroyed there makes it to be no true ſacrifice as one would think he had it here in his thoughts, then indeed he gives a good and a true rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why the one is not a ſacrifice nor upon that account <pb n="86" facs="tcp:96982:46"/>ſo valuable as the other, but for fear of that he quits this reaſon and goes to the next, which is,<note n="*" place="margin">Secunda ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitur ex parte offerentis, nam in ſacrificio crucis offerens eſt ipſa perſona filii Dei per ſe at in ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificio Miſſae offerens eſt filius Dei per mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrum. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>in reſpect of the offerer, becauſe in the one the offerer is the very per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Son of God by himſelf, but in the other the offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is the Son of God by his Minister,</hi> but ſurely if the oblation be the ſame, of the ſame worth and value, the offerer will by no means leſſen and diminiſh it, and how often do they tell us that Chriſt himſelf is the offerer of the ſacrifice of the Maſs, when we charge them with the great boldneſs and preſumption of hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a mortal man offer up Chriſt, and ſo conſequently purchaſe our Redemption, and make propitiation for ſin, which none but Chriſt can do; to avoid this the Biſhop of <hi>Meaux</hi> ſays, <hi>That Chriſt being preſent upon the Table offers up himſelf to God for us in the Eucharist</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Expoſition of the doctrine of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church.</note>. So that the Prieſt is only to ſet him upon the Table according to him by the words of conſecration, and then Chriſt offers up himſelf to God, <hi>and Christ being preſent upon the holy Table under this figure of Death, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercedes for us, and repreſents continually to his Father that death which he has ſuffered for his Church</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Ib.</note>. And the Council of
<hi>Trent</hi> ſays, It is the ſame offerer as well as the ſame ſacrifice that was upon the croſs, and the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between that and the ſacrifice of the Maſs is not at all upon the account of the offerer, but only the manner of offering<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>na eademque hoſtia, idemque offerens, ſola offerendi raetione di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versâ. <hi>Conc. Trid. Seſſ. 6. c. 2.</hi>
               </note>. This therefore can be no true reaſon of the different va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue of the two ſacrifices and oblations.</p>
            <p>The Third is taken from the will of Chriſt, for though Chriſt<note n="(c)" place="margin">Tertia ratio ſumitur ex ipſâ Chriſti voluntate, nam etiam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi poſſit Chriſtus per unam obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem ſacrificii incruenti ſive per ſe, ſive per miniſtrum oblati quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> à Deo &amp; pro quiouſcunque impetrare, tamen noluit petere nec impetrare niſi ut pro ſingulis oblationibus applicetur certa men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſura fructûs paſſionis ſuae ſive ad peccati remiſſionem ſive ad alia beneficia, quibus in hâc vitâ in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digemus. <hi>Bella. de Miſſ. l. 2. c. 4. H.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>could by one oblation offered either by himſelf or his mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster obtain any thing or for any perſon, yet he would not otherwiſe deſire or impetrate this, but only that in every oblation a certain meaſure of the fruit of his paſſion be applyed either to Remiſſion of ſin, or to other beneſits <pb n="87" facs="tcp:96982:46"/>which we want in this Life,</hi> but where does this will of Chriſt appear? Chriſt may diſpoſe of his merits and the fruits of his paſſion as he pleaſeth, but how do they know that he intends thus to parcel them out, and to diſtribute them in ſuch ſmall meaſures and ſcantlings as they think fit and as ſerves only for their purpoſe? If the ſacrifice and oblation be the ſame, it ought to be without doubt of the ſame infinite value with that upon the Croſs, and though it be very bold and preca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious to gueſſe at Chriſts will without ſome declaration of it from himſelf, yet I cannot ſee how it was poſſible that it ſhould be Chriſts will to have it the ſame ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and yet not have the ſame vertue, which is as if a Phyſician ſhould have an Univerſal Midicine, that by once taking would certainly cure all Diſeaſes whatever, and yet ſhould for ſome reaſons ſo order the matter that the very ſame Medicine ſhould if he pleaſed have only a limited vertue, &amp; cure but one Diſeaſe at a time, or only ſome leſſer &amp; ſmaller illneſſes, and that even for thoſe it muſt be often taken; This would certainly bring a ſuſpicion either upon his Medicine or himſelf, and no body but would doubt either that it had not ſuch a vertue in it at firſt, or that it was not the ſame afterwards, nor made truly by him as he pretended.</p>
            <p n="8">8. They make the Prieſt in the Maſs-ſacrifice, to do all in the name of Chriſt, and to act as his Agent and Deputy, and ſo they ſay 'tis the ſame Prieſt who offers, as well as the ſame Sacrifice which was offered upon the Croſs, and that he pronounces thoſe words of Conſecration, <hi>This is my Body</hi> in Chriſts name, not by an Hiſtorical reciting of them, but as ſpeaking authoritatively in the Perſon of Chriſt himſelf, and that this makes the Sacrifice great and valuable, as it is thus offered to God by Chriſt himſelf. I ask then whether all the ſacrificial Acts in the Maſs, are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:96982:47"/>by Chriſt? Does Chriſt conſecrate his own Body? for Conſecration is the moſt principal part of the ſacrificing Action, if not the whole of it; or if as ſome think, the Conſumption of the Sacrifice is the great thing that makes it perfect and conſummate, I ask whether Chriſt does then eat his own Body every Maſs, when it is eaten by the Prieſt; If as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> owns the Conſumption of the Sacrifice be abſolutely neceſſary to make a ſacrificial Oblation, and the true Offerer be Chriſt himſelf, as the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> ſays, then Chriſt himſelf muſt conſume the ſacrifice, that is, he muſt eat his own body: <hi>Bellarmine</hi> is really pincht with this difficulty, and he hath ſo wiſely managed the matter, that as he brought himſelf into this ſtreight, ſo he knows not how to get out of it, but he is forced to confeſs,<note n="†" place="margin">Tamen ipſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci poteſt conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mere ſacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum. <hi>Bellarm. de Miſſ. l. 1. c. 27.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>That Chriſt may in ſome ſenſe be ſaid to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume the Sacrament, i. e.</hi> himſelf, for 'tis Chriſts body and blood is the Sacrament, and not the ſpecies, at leaſt not without thoſe. We always thought it a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious if not a horrid thing for another to conſume Chriſts real body, but now for Chriſt himſelf to be made to do this, is to expoſe, Chriſt ſhall I ſay? or themſelves? or that cauſe which is driven to theſe Abſurdities, and which can never avoid them whileſt it makes the Maſs a true ſacrifice, and Chriſt himſelf the offerer of it.</p>
            <p n="9">9. The Offering this Sacrifice to redeem ſouls out of Purgatory, as it is made one of the greateſt ends and uſes of this Sacrifice of the Maſs, ſo is one of the greateſt Errors and Abuſes that belong to it, for beſides that it contains in it all the foregoing Errors and Abſurdities of its being a proper Sacrifice, and ſo bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitting thoſe who do not at all receive it as a Sacrament, and being properly propitiatory at leaſt for leſſer ſins, and for the temporal pains that they ſuppoſe due to <pb n="89" facs="tcp:96982:47"/>greater ſins after they are forgiven, which is another cluſter of Errors that grows likewiſe to this Doctrine, though it belongs to another place to conſider them. I ſay beſides all thoſe Errors it takes in alſo the ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and uncomfortable and erroniou; opinion of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory, whereby a great many departed Souls are ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be in a ſad ſtate of extream pain and torment till they are delivered from it by theſe Maſſes and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices which are offered for them to that purpoſe. And this is indeed the great advantage of them, I mean to the Prieſts that offer them, who hereby make Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize not only of the Souls of Men, but of Chriſts Body and Blood, and are made by this ſacrifice a ſort of Mony-changers in the Temple, and inſtead of Doves ſell Chriſt himſelf, and the ſouls in Purgatory are redeemed out of it by ſuch corruptible things, as Silver and Gold, which are to purchaſe Maſſes, that is, Chriſts body and bloud at a certain price. This is a moſt horrible abuſe of Chriſtianity, which expoſes it to infinite ſcandal and reproach, the ſelling of Maſſes and Indulgences is ſo viſible a blot in Popery that though nothing has more enriched, yet nothing has more ſhamed it then theſe have done; both thoſe have relation to Purgatory which is an unknown Countrey in the other World, that hath given riſe to thoſe two profitable Trades and to all that ſpiritual Traffic that is carried on by it. A Late excellent diſcourſe has ſo fully conſidered that ſubject, that I am no further to meddle with it here then as the ſacrifice of the Maſs is concerned in it. Our Adverſaries moſt plauſible and ſpecious pretence for both thoſe Doctrines is taken from the antient cuſtom of oblations for the Dead, which cannot be denyed to be of great antiquity and general uſe even very near the beginnings of Chriſtianity, and to have had a long continuance in the Chriſtian Church. <hi>Tertullian</hi> mentions them <hi>as
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:96982:48"/>made on every. Anniverſary of their birth</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Oblationes pro defunctis pro na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talitiis annuâ die facimus. <hi>Tertul. de Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rona militis, c. 3.</hi>
               </note>, <hi>i. e.</hi> on the day wherein they died to this World, and were born into immortality. St.
<hi>Cyprian</hi> ſpeaks of them as ſo generally uſed for all perſons, that it was made the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of him who ſhould leave a Clergyman his Executor, and ſo take him off from his ſacred employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to ſecular Troubles and Affairs, that<note n="(a)" place="margin">Ac ſiquis hoc feciſſet non offerretur pro eo nec ſacrificium pro dormitione ejus celebraretur. <hi>Cyprian Epiſt. l. 1.</hi> Edit. Ox.</note> 
               <hi>no offering ſhould be made for him, neither ſhould any ſacrifice be celebrated for his departure,</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">Epiſcopi anteceſſores no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stri religioſe conſiderantes &amp; ſalubriter providentes cenſuerunt nequis frater excedens ad tutelam vel curam Clericum nominaret, <hi>&amp;c. Ib.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and this was an Order,</hi> he ſayes, <hi>made by former Biſhops in Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil,</hi> and therefore he commands that <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minius Victor,</hi> who had made <hi>Geminius Fanſtinus</hi> Tutor to his Will, or his Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor,<note n="(d)" place="margin">Non eſt quod pro dormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione ejus apud vos fiat oblatio, aut deprecatio aliqua nomine ejus in Eccleſiâ frequentetur, <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſhould have no oblation made for his departure nor any Prayer uſed in his name in the Church.</hi> St.
<hi>Auſtin</hi> gives it in as the <hi>custom of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Church</hi> in his time, that a ſacrifice was offered for the dead,<note n="(e)" place="margin">Non parva eſt Eccleſiae <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſae quae in hâc conſuetudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neclaret, authoritas —, ſi nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam in Scripturis veteribus ſcriptum legeretur—ſc. oblatum pro mortuis ſacrificium, <hi>Auguſt. cura pro mortuis.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and this,</hi> he ſays, <hi>is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent authority for it, though there were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of it in Scripture;</hi> and having ſhown that what happens to the dead body is of no concern to the departed ſoul,<note n="(f)" place="margin">Non exiſtimemus ad mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuos pro. quibus curam gerimus pervenire, niſi quod pro eis ſive altaris, ſive orationum ſive ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>oſyn arum ſacrificiis ſolenniter ſupplicamus. <hi>Ib. verſus finem.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>none of our care,</hi> ſays he, <hi>can reach the dead but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that we ſupplicate for them by the ſacrifices of the Altar, of Prayers or of Alms,</hi> and the ſame thing he mentions in ſeveral other places of his works, and in his own oblations at the Altar for his Mother <hi>Monica</hi> after ſhe was dead. Now what can we think of theſe Oblati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons unleſs with the Papiſts we allow ſuch a ſtate of departed ſouls as they call Purgatory, that is, neither Heaven nor Hell; for if they were either in the one or the other of thoſe, theſe oblations would ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie nothing to them, and how plain is it that they
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:96982:48"/>thought them to be ſome way benefitted or relieved by the ſacrifice of the Maſs or Altar. I anſwer that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of thoſe Opinions as they are now held, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> do follow from the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Cuſtom of offering for the Dead, but that they were of another nature then what they account them, and this I ſhall evince from the following conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Then theſe Oblations were made for departed Souls who were not ſuppoſed to be in a ſtate of pain, as they now believe Purgatory to be, but in a ſtate of eaſe and happineſs, as St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> believed his Mother to be when he offered for her, and when he prayed for her,<note n="*" place="margin">&amp; credo quod jam ſeceris quod te rogo, ſed vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntaria or is mei approba Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, <hi>Auguſt. Confeſſ. l. 9. c.
12.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>he did believe that God had already granted her what he prayed for, but he beg'd him to accept theſe free Will offerings of his mouth.</hi> It was not then a doubt of her ſtate but only the voluntary expreſſions of his Love and Duty which he deſigned by his Prayers and Obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for her, and thoſe Olations were made even for Saints and Martyrs, and the moſt holy Chriſtians of whoſe future happineſs there was no manner of que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, and for all indeed who dyed in the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Church. And therefore</p>
            <p n="2">2. They were an honorary Teſtimony given to them of their good ſtate, and of their dying in the Peace and Communion of the Church: to have their names recited at the Altar ſervice out of the Diptychs or folded Tables was an honorary memorial and men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them as members of the Church, and 'twas a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owning them as ſuch to expunge, or blot their names out of thoſe Diptychs; and ſo the making or receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Oblations for them at the Altar, was an acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment of their right to the Altar, &amp; to the Chriſtian Communion, and therefore no oblations were receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:96982:49"/>of the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of thoſe who were not Communicants, or had not a right to Communion, of thoſe who were guilty of ſcandalous ſins or of thoſe who were in a ſtate of Penance for them, as may be ſeen in the Apoſtolick Conſtitutions<note n="†" place="margin">l. 4. c. 5. l. 3. c. 8.</note>, and in one of the moſt ancient Councils,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Epiſcopum placuit ab eo qui non communicat, murera accipere non dibere. <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil Eliber. c.
28.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>which forbids the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop to take oblations from him who does not communicate. Petavius</hi> has largely made this out in his Notes on
<hi>Epiphanius</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">Animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſ. in Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phan. Expoſit. fid.</note> and produces a Council which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides<note n="†" place="margin">Concil. Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſe. Ib.</note> 
               <hi>that the Oblations of thoſe penitents ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, who were ſurprized by a ſudden death in a journy.</hi> Which was a receiving them into the Churches Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion,
<hi>quaſi ex Postliminio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. By having theſe Oblations received and offered for them they were made partakers of the prayers that were made for them at the Altar: what ever bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit theſe prayers were believed to be of to departed ſouls, which I am not here to examine, that did accrue to them by having theſe oblations made and received for them; for by this means they were particularly men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned and recommended in the Prayers at the Altar, and thus both
<hi>Tertullian,</hi> St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> and St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> explain the ſacrifices and oblations which they menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as made for the dead.<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xor pro animâ defuncti mariti or at &amp; offert annuis die<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus dormitionis ejus. <hi>Tertull. de Monogam.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>The Wife prays for her hushands ſoul and offers on his Anniverſary.</hi> And again,<note n="(d)" place="margin">Neque enim ad altare meretur nominari in jacerdotum prece qui ab altari jacerdotes &amp; miniſtros ſuos avocari voluit. <hi>Cypr. Ep. 1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>He deſerves not to be named in the prayer of the Priests at the Altar of God, who takes off Gods mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters from the Altar,</hi> in the fore-menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned caſe of making a Clergy-man Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor.<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi in precibus ſacerdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis quae Domino Deo ad ejus al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare funduntur, locum ſuum ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet etiam commendatio mortuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum. <hi>Auguſt. cura pro mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uis.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>And in the prayers of the Prieſt which are poured out to God at his Altar, the commendation of the dead has place.</hi> So that the good they had by theſe oblations was upon the account of theſe Prayers, <pb n="93" facs="tcp:96982:49"/>and not by any vertue in theſe oblations as they were a ſacrifice, diſtinct from the benefit of the Prayers; as they were Alms indeed together with prayers they thought the dead benefitted by them together with the prayers, and ſo St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> in the fore-quoted place mentions the ſacrifices of the Altar which he explains by prayers and Alms, both which he calls ſacrifices<note n="*" place="margin">ſive altaris, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve orationum, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve eleemoſyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſacrificiis ſupplicamus. <hi>ut ſupra.</hi>
               </note>, but not in a proper and ſtrict ſenſe as our Adverſaries muſt acknowledge. For theſe ſacrifices I hope were not true and proper ones ſuch as the ſacrifice of the Maſs is held to be, nor were they properly propitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory for their ſins, nor did the Antients who prayed for the dead at the Altar and made oblations for them, think that theſe oblations were properly propitiatory, or ſatisfactory for their ſins, as the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> believes the ſacrifice of Maſs now to be: there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that amounts to this in any of thoſe places where they ſpeak of offerings for the dead, nor would St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> or the Biſhops who ordained in Council that no offerings ſhould be made for him who appointed a Clergy-Man Executor to his Will, have inflicted ſo ſevere a puniſhment upon ſo ſmall a fault, had they thought this would have deprived his ſoul of a true and real propitiation for his ſins, nor would blotting out of the Diptychs have been ſo commonly put in uſe, had this been conſigning the ſoul to the puniſhments of another World.</p>
            <p>There was therefore no ſuch thing meant as our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries would now draw from that ancient cuſtom of Oblations for the Dead; and yet that this quickly degenerated into ſuperſtition and has been farther im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved in aftertimes and is now come to very great perfection in the Roman Church we willingly own; &amp; that the firſt beginnings of this were lay'd in this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptural cuſtom, as the Worſhip of Saints was from the Anniverſary memory of the Martyrs is not to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed: <pb n="94" facs="tcp:96982:50"/>But corruptions in Religion like Diſeaſes in the body might proceed at firſt from very ſmall cauſes, but by neglect and careleſsneſs grow oftentimes very great and dangerous, eſpecially when the Phyſicians that ſhould have cured them, thought it for their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and intereſt rather to heighten and increaſe them.</p>
            <p n="10">10. The ſacrifice of the Maſs muſt either be unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, or elſe muſt reflect on the ſacrifice of the Croſs, if it be not neceſſary for obtaining the pardon and remiſſion of any ſin, or for the relief of any ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual want and neceſſity for which there has been no proviſion made by the ſacrifice of the croſs, then it is wholly uſeleſs &amp; unprofitable; if it be neceſſary for any ſuch purpoſe then the ſacrifice of the croſs is not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and ſufficient for all thoſe ends, but requires this ſacrifice of the Maſs to make up what is lacking, and behind of the ſufferings of Chriſt upon the croſs, which is a great diminution to the infinite value of them. It is impoſſible to avoid theſe inconveniences, for if the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the croſs be ſo great as to expiate all manner offin, and to take away all kinds of puniſhment that are due to it, and to ſupply all the ſpiritual wants and neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties whatever of all Chriſtians, then what poſſible need can there be of any other ſacrifice? And if Chriſts ſacrifice once offered upon the croſs can do all this, why ſhould there be any new offering or any reiteration of the ſame ſacrifice, when by being once offered it hath done the whole buſineſs that it can do were it offered never ſo often: but if there be any kinds of ſins, which becauſe they are dayly commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by us therefore require a dayly ſacrifice, as they pretend, to be offered for them, which implyes that the conſtant and abiding vertue of the croſs cannot reach them, which is yet as efficacious to all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans <pb n="95" facs="tcp:96982:50"/>now as the firſt day it was offered, or as it could be if it were offered every day by Chriſt himſelf; or if there be any ſuch temporal remains of puniſhment after the eternal guilt of them is pardoned, which are not diſcharged by Chriſts ſacrifice upon the Croſs, but there is this ſmall hand-Writing ſtill however againſt us and continues uncancelled notwithſtanding the Death of Chriſt, then we are not perfectly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed from all puniſhment, and from the whole Curſe of the Law by the ſacrifice of the croſs, but there is ſomething more neceſſary to deliver and ſave us if not from Hell yet from Purgatory, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Chriſt has done for us yet the Maſs ſacrifice muſt ſtill help us, not as an inſtrument of Religion to work upon us and make us better, but as a ſacrifice to God to prevail with him to free us from puniſhment, or elſe we are in a miſerable condition, which is the true contrivance of the ſacrifice of the Maſs, that neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily renders it very injurious to the moſt perfect and ſufficient ſacrifice of the croſs.</p>
            <p>I might add many other Errors belonging to this Doctrine of the ſacrifice of the Maſs, ſuch as ſaying their Maſſes in an unknown Tongue, putting confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in the meer <hi>opus operatum,</hi> offering up Maſſes to the honour of the Saints, and the like, but thoſe do more properly fall under other heads of controverſie, and are the peculiar ſubjects of other Treatiſes that are written on purpoſe upon thoſe matters; for though theſe all run into this Doctrine of the ſacrifice of the Maſs, which is the great Lake into which moſt of the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Errors empty themſelves, yet the firſt head and riſe of them is not from hence, and ſo I ſhall not take them in here.</p>
            <p>The Maſs ſacrifice contains in it a whole Legion of Errors, but 'tis only the principal one which I have endeavoured by this Diſcourſe to caſt out, and that <pb n="96" facs="tcp:96982:51"/>is its being a proper and truly propitiatory ſacrifice, which I have ſhown <hi>to be founded upon two monſtrous Errours, to have no true foundation in Scripture, nor no juſt claim to Antiquity, but to be plainly contrary to both thoſe, and to be in it ſelf very abſurd and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſonable,</hi> which is enough in conſcience againſt any one Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine or any Church that maintains it, however In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible they may both of them pretend to be, if this be clearly and ſtrongly made out againſt them, as has been Attempted in this Treatiſe.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>Books Sold by <hi>Brabazon Aylmer,</hi> at the <hi>Three Pidgeons</hi> over againſt the <hi>Royal Exchinge</hi> in
<hi>Cornhil.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>A Diſcourſe concerning the Adoration of the Hoſt, as it is Taught and Practiced in the Church of</hi> Rome; <hi>Wherein an Anſwer is given to</hi> T. G. <hi>on that Subject, And to Monſieur</hi> Boleau<hi>'s late Book,</hi> De Adoratione Euchariſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Diſcourſe of the Communion in One Kind: In Anſwer to a Treatiſe of the Biſhop of</hi> Meaux<hi>'s, of</hi> Communion of both Species.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An Anſwer to a Book, Entituled, Reaſon and Authority: Or the Motives of a Late Proteſtant's Reconciliation to the Catholick Church: Together with a brief Account of</hi> Auguſtine <hi>the Monk, and Converſion of the</hi> Engliſh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Requeſt to Roman Catholicks, To Anſwer the Queries upon theſe their following Tenets. Sect. 1.</hi> Their Divine Service in an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nknown Tongue. <hi>2.</hi> Their taking away the Cup from the People.
<hi>3.</hi> Their with-hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scriptures from the Laicks. <hi>4.</hi> The Adoration of Images. <hi>5.</hi> The In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation of Saints and Angels.
<hi>6.</hi> The Doctrine of Merit. <hi>7.</hi> Purgatory. <hi>8.</hi> Their Seven Sacraments. <hi>9.</hi> Their Priests Intention in Baptiſm.
<hi>10.</hi> The Lambo of unbaptized Inſants. <hi>11.</hi> Tranſubſtantiation. <hi>12.</hi> The Propitiatory Sacrifice of the Maſs.
<hi>13.</hi> Private Maſſes. <hi>14.</hi> The Sacrament of Penance.
<hi>15.</hi> The Sacrament of Marriage, with the Clergies Restraint therefrom.
<hi>16.</hi> Their Sacrament of extream <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction. <hi>17.</hi> Tradition.
<hi>18.</hi> That Thred<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bare Queſtion, Where was your Church before
<hi>Luther? 19.</hi> The Infallibility of the Pope with his Councils.
<hi>20.</hi> The Pope's Supremacy. <hi>21.</hi> The Pope's De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing Power.
<hi>22.</hi> Their <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncharitableneſs to all other Chriſtians.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
